[
  {
    "id": 1,
    "question": "In the Ancient Kingdom of Mali and in the Roman Republic, an important feature of life was the development of",
    "option": [
      "codified laws",
      "social and political equality",
      "the Islamic religion",
      "agricultural communes"
    ],
    "answer": "codified laws"
  },
  {
    "id": 2,
    "question": "Which statement best explains the periods of the Gupta Empire of India, the Golden Age of Greece, and the Renaissance in Italy?",
    "option": [
      "the winning of a war often inspires scientific and artistic achievement",
      "a combination of wealth and a time of relative peace often leads to cultural achievement",
      "a dictatorship usually encourages cultural growth and development",
      "periods of censorship are needed for a nation to achieve cultural and scientific greatness"
    ],
    "answer": "a combination of wealth and a time of relative peace often leads to cultural achievement"
  },
  {
    "id": 3,
    "question": "One way in which Medieval European society, Latin American colonial society, and society in Imperial China were similar is that each",
    "option": [
      "placed great value on public education",
      "experienced a surplus of skilled labor",
      "was organized according to a rigid class structure",
      "de-emphasized the role of religion"
    ],
    "answer": "was organized according to a rigid class structure"
  },
  {
    "id": 4,
    "question": "Which idea did Napoleon Bonaparte, Sun Yat-Sen, and Simone Bolivar have in common?",
    "option": ["divine right", "nationalism", "totalitarianism", "nonviolence"],
    "answer": "nationalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 5,
    "question": "Eighteenth-century Russia and nineteenth-century Japan were similar in that both countries",
    "option": [
      "began the process of modernization after a long period of isolation",
      "developed democratic governments after years under absolute monarchies",
      "refused to accept western technological ideas",
      "adopted socialist economic systems after capitalism had failed"
    ],
    "answer": "began the process of modernization after a long period of isolation"
  },
  {
    "id": 6,
    "question": "Until the 1500 s, China and Japan were similar in that both",
    "option": [
      "were invaded by the Mongols",
      "welcomed Christian Missionaries",
      "had little contact with Western European nations",
      "were developing democratic traditions"
    ],
    "answer": "had little contact with Western European nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 7,
    "question": "During the Middle Ages, Europeans did not eat potatoes or corn because these vegetables",
    "option": [
      "were forbidden by the Catholic Church for religious reasons",
      "had not yet been introduced to Europe from the New World",
      "were believed to be poisonous",
      "were too expensive to import from China"
    ],
    "answer": "had not yet been introduced to Europe from the New World"
  },
  {
    "id": 8,
    "question": "One way in which Medieval European society, Latin American colonial society, and society in Imperial China were similar is that each",
    "option": [
      "placed great value on public education",
      "experienced a surplus of skilled labor",
      "was organized according to a rigid class structure",
      "de-emphasized the role of religion"
    ],
    "answer": "was organized according to a rigid class structure"
  },
  {
    "id": 9,
    "question": "The societies of traditional China, Feudal Japan, and Czarist Russia were all characterized by",
    "option": [
      "a rigid class structure",
      "much interaction with other cultures",
      "great economic change",
      "rapidly changing social values"
    ],
    "answer": "a rigid class structure"
  },
  {
    "id": 10,
    "question": "One similarity between the decline of the Roman Empire and the fall of the Manchu Dynasty was that both initially led to",
    "option": [
      "improved economic conditions",
      "democratically elected governments",
      "political chaos and decentralization of government",
      "major accomplishments in art, science, and technology"
    ],
    "answer": "political chaos and decentralization of government"
  },
  {
    "id": 11,
    "question": "The Japanese feudal system and the Hindu caste system are similar in that both systems",
    "option": [
      "promoted social mobility",
      "developed a rigid class structure",
      "encouraged the people to take part in government",
      "resulted in economic opportunities for the lower classes"
    ],
    "answer": "developed a rigid class structure"
  },
  {
    "id": 12,
    "question": "Eighteenth-century Russia and nineteenth-century Japan were similar in that both countries",
    "option": [
      "began the process of modernization after a long period of isolation",
      "developed democratic governments after years under absolute monarchies",
      "refused to accept western technological ideas",
      "adopted socialist economic systems after capitalism had failed"
    ],
    "answer": "began the process of modernization after a long period of isolation"
  },
  {
    "id": 13,
    "question": "Changes in Russia under Peter the Great were most similar to changes that occurred in",
    "option": [
      "China before the Opium War",
      "Japan during the Meiji Restoration",
      "Iran after the fall of Shah Pahlevi",
      "France during the feudal period"
    ],
    "answer": "Japan during the Meiji Restoration"
  },
  {
    "id": 14,
    "question": "The Tamils in Sri Lanka, the Sikhs in India, and the Zulus in South Africa have all attempted to",
    "option": [
      "establish colonies in Asia",
      "practice passive resistance",
      "achieve political separatism",
      "encourage mercantilism"
    ],
    "answer": "achieve political separatism"
  },
  {
    "id": 15,
    "question": "Which was characteristic of France under Napoleon s rule and Germany under Hitler s rule?",
    "option": [
      "democratic ideas and diversity were encouraged",
      "authoritarian control and a strong sense of nationalism prevailed",
      "peaceful relations with neighboring countries wee fostered",
      "artistic and literary freedom flourished"
    ],
    "answer": "authoritarian control and a strong sense of nationalism prevailed"
  },
  {
    "id": 16,
    "question": "A study of the French Revolution and the Russian Revolution of 1917 would lead to the conclusion that",
    "option": [
      "revolutions only occur when a majority of citizens become directly involved",
      "university students are most often responsible for starting revolutions",
      "control of revolutions often shifts from moderates to radicals",
      "revolutions seldom result in long-term changes"
    ],
    "answer": "control of revolutions often shifts from moderates to radicals"
  },
  {
    "id": 17,
    "question": "The French Revolution, the Bolshevik Revolution in Russia, and the Communist Revolution in China were similar in that all three",
    "option": [
      "brought about few political changes",
      "were influenced by the peasants  desire for more land",
      "were inspired by Marxism",
      "were supported primarily by the nobility"
    ],
    "answer": "were influenced by the peasants  desire for more land"
  },
  {
    "id": 18,
    "question": "The ancient Greek city-state of Sparta and the Soviet Union under Stalin were similar in that both societies",
    "option": [
      "were primarily concerned with the health of their people",
      "were powerful military states",
      "granted universal suffrage to their people",
      "placed great emphasis on literature and the arts"
    ],
    "answer": "were powerful military states"
  },
  {
    "id": 19,
    "question": "In China, the building of the Great Wall, the use of the tribute system, and the government s support of the Boxer Rebellion are examples of attempts by different dynasties to limit",
    "option": [
      "foreign influence",
      "nationalism",
      "communist expansion",
      "industrialization"
    ],
    "answer": "foreign influence"
  },
  {
    "id": 20,
    "question": "The French Revolution of 1789 and the Cuban Revolution of 1959 were similar in that both were caused primarily by the",
    "option": [
      "desire of the people to be free from foreign rule",
      "pressure of religious leaders for government reform",
      "failure of the government to meet the needs of the people",
      "ambition of the upper class to attain wealth and property"
    ],
    "answer": "failure of the government to meet the needs of the people"
  },
  {
    "id": 21,
    "question": "The philosophies of Confucius and Mao Zedong both emphasized",
    "option": [
      "individual rather than cooperative gain",
      "industry rather than agriculture",
      "group rather than individual welfare",
      "religious values rather than economic profits"
    ],
    "answer": "group rather than individual welfare"
  },
  {
    "id": 22,
    "question": "Japan during the Meiji Restoration was similar to Japan after World War II in that during these periods Japan",
    "option": [
      "pursued a foreign policy of isolationism and limited political freedoms",
      "reduced the powers of the Emperor and the nobility",
      "underwent political reform and economic expansion",
      "was ruled by dictators and the military"
    ],
    "answer": "underwent political reform and economic expansion"
  },
  {
    "id": 23,
    "question": "Since the late 1940 s, India, Northern Ireland, and Israel have faced the common problem of",
    "option": [
      "adjusting to a post-Communist political and economic system",
      "continued violent confrontations between different religious groups",
      "economic depression as a result of rapid industrialization",
      "uncertainty of their acceptance by the European Community"
    ],
    "answer": "continued violent confrontations between different religious groups"
  },
  {
    "id": 24,
    "question": "The events that led to the overthrow of Czar Nicholas II in 1917 and to the forced resignation of Mikhail Gorbachev in 1991 show that",
    "option": [
      "economic crises often lead to political change",
      "Russian absolutism continued into the 1990 s",
      "international conflicts often strengthen the power of leaders",
      "Russia is an ethnically unified nation"
    ],
    "answer": "economic crises often lead to political change"
  },
  {
    "id": 25,
    "question": "Events in both Eastern Europe in the early 1900 s and in the Soviet Union in the late 1980 s were mainly the result of",
    "option": [
      "movements toward the repression of individual rights",
      "declines in the use of advanced technology",
      "the influence of religion on government",
      "challenges by ethnic groups desiring independence"
    ],
    "answer": "challenges by ethnic groups desiring independence"
  },
  {
    "id": 26,
    "question": "During the late 1980 s and early 1990 s, the Soviet Union experienced ethnic tensions that were most similar to those experienced by",
    "option": [
      "Japan in the early 17th century",
      "Austria-Hungary in the late 19th century",
      "Spain in the mid-18th century",
      "Cuba in the late 20th century"
    ],
    "answer": "Austria-Hungary in the late 19th century"
  },
  {
    "id": 27,
    "question": "The Holocaust in Europe and the actions of the Khmer Rouge in Kampuchea (Cambodia) were similar in that they were examples of",
    "option": ["Interdependence", "Segregation", "Genocide", "Empathy"],
    "answer": "Genocide"
  },
  {
    "id": 28,
    "question": "One similarity between Mao Zedong and Fidel Castro is that they",
    "option": [
      "achieved their goals through the use of peaceful resistance",
      "worked to protect citizens  rights to freedom of expression",
      "considered capitalism to be the best economic system",
      "led revolutionary movements that established communist governments"
    ],
    "answer": "led revolutionary movements that established communist governments"
  },
  {
    "id": 29,
    "question": "Germany Will Make Reparations For WWI    OPEC Supports Oil Embargo Against Western Nations",
    "option": [
      "economic measures are often designed to achieve political goals",
      "communism as an economic system has failed",
      "economic policies are often formulated to encourage investment",
      "nationalism plays a small role in economic decisionmaking"
    ],
    "answer": "economic measures are often designed to achieve political goals"
  },
  {
    "id": 30,
    "question": "A study of the policy of  ethnic cleansing  in Bosnia and the Holocaust in Europe would suggest that",
    "option": [
      "world opinion is effective in stopping genocide",
      "countries generally use reason and negotiation in dealing with important ethnic issues",
      "anti-Semitism and ethnic hatred remain powerful forces in the 20th century",
      "military leaders cannot be held responsible for acts committed during wartime"
    ],
    "answer": "anti-Semitism and ethnic hatred remain powerful forces in the 20th century"
  },
  {
    "id": 31,
    "question": "Which factor has most limited the development of national unity in India, Lebanon, and Bosnia-Herzegovina?",
    "option": [
      "lack of natural resources",
      "inability to end colonialism",
      "religious and ethnic differences",
      "rapid growth of industry"
    ],
    "answer": "religious and ethnic differences"
  },
  {
    "id": 32,
    "question": "Both the Chinese Mandate of Heaven and the Japanese belief that the Emperor descends from the Sun Goddess are similar to the",
    "option": [
      " master race  theory of Adolf Hitler s Third Reich",
      "natural rights theory of the Age of Reason",
      "divine right theory of the French monarchy",
      "Marxist theory of a workers  revolution"
    ],
    "answer": "divine right theory of the French monarchy"
  },
  {
    "id": 33,
    "question": "One way in which the caste system and apartheid were similar is that both",
    "option": [
      "described specific religious practices and beliefs",
      "supported a rigid class structure",
      "were created by British colonial governments",
      "gave power to the lower classes in their respective societies"
    ],
    "answer": "supported a rigid class structure"
  },
  {
    "id": 34,
    "question": "Within their respective nations, both Ho Chi Minh and Fidel Castro achieved their goals by",
    "option": [
      "seeking aid and support from the European Union",
      "using armed conflict to bring a communist government to power",
      "following a policy of nonalignment",
      "working to build a capitalist system"
    ],
    "answer": "using armed conflict to bring a communist government to power"
  },
  {
    "id": 35,
    "question": "One way in which the Meiji Restoration in Japan and the Golden Age of India are similar is that in each region these events led to",
    "option": [
      "the persecution of minority peoples",
      "periods of rapid change",
      "the rise of feudalism as the dominant political system",
      "governments ruled by absolute monarchs"
    ],
    "answer": "periods of rapid change"
  },
  {
    "id": 36,
    "question": "The Sepoy Rebellion in India and the Boxer Rebellion in China were similar in that both were",
    "option": [
      "attempts to improve foreign trade",
      "nonviolent resistance efforts",
      "revolts against foreign influence",
      "revolutions against traditional monarchs"
    ],
    "answer": "revolts against foreign influence"
  },
  {
    "id": 37,
    "question": "Suleiman held complete religious and political power.  Charles I stormed the English Parliament.",
    "option": [
      "scientific theory",
      "natural rights",
      "mercantilism",
      "absolutism"
    ],
    "answer": "absolutism"
  },
  {
    "id": 38,
    "question": "What would a study of the recent civil wars in Cambodia, Bosnia-Herzegovina, and Rwanda show about these conflicts?",
    "option": [
      "Ethnic conflict was not a factor in the late 20th century.",
      "The United Nations was successful in resolving these disputes.",
      "Genocide was used as a political and military tactic.",
      "Civilians were not affected by these disputes."
    ],
    "answer": "Genocide was used as a political and military tactic."
  },
  {
    "id": 39,
    "question": "A similarity of the goals of Nelson Mandela and Mohandas Gandhi is that both leaders wanted to",
    "option": [
      "secure political power for the majority of the people",
      "encourage a greater degree of industrialization",
      "improve the economy by expanding governmental control",
      "gain independence from the Soviet Union"
    ],
    "answer": "secure political power for the majority of the people"
  },
  {
    "id": 40,
    "question": "Statement 1:   This organization is created for the purpose of realizing the national ideal:",
    "option": [
      "War is a means of achieving national policies.",
      "Industrial growth is critical to a country s prosperity.",
      "Social class differences are the source of all conflicts.",
      "Self-determination of the people is an important goal."
    ],
    "answer": "Self-determination of the people is an important goal."
  },
  {
    "id": 41,
    "question": "One way in which Sim n Bol var, Jomo Kenyatta, and Ho Chi Minh are similar is that each leader",
    "option": [
      "sought independence from colonial rule",
      "ruled during a period of peace and prosperity",
      "demanded human rights for all citizens",
      "established a totalitarian government"
    ],
    "answer": "sought independence from colonial rule"
  },
  {
    "id": 42,
    "question": "Which document is an example of a primary source?",
    "option": [
      "a textbook on Russian history",
      "an encyclopedia article on religions of the Middle East",
      "a novel on the Age of Exploration",
      "the diary of a survivor of a Nazi death camp"
    ],
    "answer": "the diary of a survivor of a Nazi death camp"
  },
  {
    "id": 43,
    "question": "Which historical events are in the correct chronological order?",
    "option": [
      "Crusades -> Renaissance -> Neolithic Revolution -> Roman Empire",
      "Roman Empire -> Neolithic Revolution -> Crusades -> Renaissance",
      "Renaissance ->Neolithic Revolution -> Crusades -> Roman Empire",
      "Neolithic Revolution -> Roman Empire -> Crusades -> Renaissance"
    ],
    "answer": "Neolithic Revolution -> Roman Empire -> Crusades -> Renaissance"
  },
  {
    "id": 44,
    "question": "The United Nations Declaration of Human Rights",
    "option": [
      "secondary sources",
      "examples of oral traditions",
      "primary sources",
      "statements of different religious beliefs"
    ],
    "answer": "primary sources"
  },
  {
    "id": 45,
    "question": "Which statement best explains why most of the population of the people s Republic of China live in the eastern third of the nation?",
    "option": [
      "best agricultural land is in the East",
      "largest forests are in the East",
      "best fishing areas are off the eastern coast",
      "largest oil deposits are in the East"
    ],
    "answer": "best agricultural land is in the East"
  },
  {
    "id": 46,
    "question": "Which is an accurate statement about Japan s natural resources?",
    "option": [
      "Japan has extensively used the seas for fishing",
      "large reserves of petroleum are located in the northern part of Japan",
      "Japan has large fertile plains suitable for growing grain",
      "large coal and iron-ore deposits are located in the mountain region"
    ],
    "answer": "Japan has extensively used the seas for fishing"
  },
  {
    "id": 47,
    "question": "In Japan, a major economic problem has been the lack of",
    "option": [
      "natural resources",
      "investment capital",
      "skilled labor",
      "experienced management"
    ],
    "answer": "natural resources"
  },
  {
    "id": 48,
    "question": "Which statement best describes an effect that geography has had on Japan?",
    "option": [
      "Japan s smooth coastline has prevented the development of a fishing industry",
      "Japan s large plains have made wheat growing a primary industry",
      "the lack of important natural resources has led Japan to depend on trade with other nations",
      "the location of Japan has encouraged great ethnic diversity within the nation"
    ],
    "answer": "the lack of important natural resources has led Japan to depend on trade with other nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 49,
    "question": "Both Japan and Indonesia are made up of a chain of islands called",
    "option": ["an archipelago", "a peninsula", "a delta", "an atoll"],
    "answer": "an archipelago"
  },
  {
    "id": 50,
    "question": "The term  Latin America  most accurately refers to the",
    "option": [
      "areas of the Western Hemisphere south of the United States",
      "countries that belong to the Organization of American States",
      "continents of North and South America",
      "countries that have close economic ties with Spain"
    ],
    "answer": "areas of the Western Hemisphere south of the United States"
  },
  {
    "id": 51,
    "question": "Which generalization about geography of Latin America is accurate?",
    "option": [
      "geographic features prevented foreign imperialism",
      "harsh climatic conditions have prevented the development of large-scale agriculture",
      "the lack of geographic barriers facilitated the development of transportation and communication systems",
      "great variations in latitude and landforms resulted in a diversity of climates"
    ],
    "answer": "great variations in latitude and landforms resulted in a diversity of climates"
  },
  {
    "id": 52,
    "question": "Which geographic factor has had the most influence on Poland's historical and cultural development?",
    "option": [
      "a severe climate",
      "vast deposits of oil",
      "location on the great European Plain",
      "a rugged coastline"
    ],
    "answer": "location on the great European Plain"
  },
  {
    "id": 53,
    "question": "Which of these nations is located closet to the Philippines, Malaysia, and Indonesia?",
    "option": ["Korea", "Vietnam", "Somalia", "Pakistan"],
    "answer": "Vietnam"
  },
  {
    "id": 54,
    "question": "One effect that mountain ranges, rain forests, and river systems have had on Latin America has been to",
    "option": [
      "encourage cultural diffusion",
      "limit the development of transportation and communication systems",
      "permit the nations of the area to use a single form of government",
      "allow the development of large amounts of arable land"
    ],
    "answer": "limit the development of transportation and communication systems"
  },
  {
    "id": 55,
    "question": "In addition to providing water for Indian agriculture, the Ganges River remains important to India because it is",
    "option": [
      "the only source of Indian hydroelectric power",
      "a sacred river for the Hindu population",
      "the birthplace of Hindu culture",
      "an unofficial boundary between the Hindus and Muslims"
    ],
    "answer": "a sacred river for the Hindu population"
  },
  {
    "id": 56,
    "question": "An effect of a mountainous topography on Inca and Chinese civilizations was the development of",
    "option": [
      "industrialization",
      "single-crop economy",
      "desalinization projects",
      "terrace farming"
    ],
    "answer": "terrace farming"
  },
  {
    "id": 57,
    "question": "A major effect of geography on Japan is that the",
    "option": [
      "export of oil has helped Japan maintain a favorable balance of trade",
      "fertile plains have enabled Japan to keep food prices low",
      "mountains have prevented invasions obey foreign nations",
      "scarcity of natural resources has forced Japan to obtain raw materials from other nations"
    ],
    "answer": "scarcity of natural resources has forced Japan to obtain raw materials from other nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 58,
    "question": "Which geographic factor has most strongly influenced Russia s foreign policies and economic development?",
    "option": [
      "lack of natural resources",
      "vast desert regions",
      "limited access to warm-water ports",
      "extensive mountain ranges"
    ],
    "answer": "limited access to warm-water ports"
  },
  {
    "id": 59,
    "question": "Many people in Southeast Asia hope for the timely arrival of the summer monsoons each year because",
    "option": [
      "floods are the only way to water their farmlands",
      "daily temperatures often reach 100 degrees Fahrenheit",
      "little rain has fallen for many months",
      "oases provide water for nomadic herders"
    ],
    "answer": "little rain has fallen for many months"
  },
  {
    "id": 60,
    "question": "A topographical map would most likely be used to",
    "option": [
      "identify the major agricultural products of Egypt",
      "determine the population of Beijing, China",
      "estimate the elevation of Bangkok, Thailand",
      "count the number of provinces in India"
    ],
    "answer": "estimate the elevation of Bangkok, Thailand"
  },
  {
    "id": 61,
    "question": "On a map of the world, Asia is to Japan as Europe is to",
    "option": ["Great Britain", "the Netherlands", "Austria", "Italy"],
    "answer": "Great Britain"
  },
  {
    "id": 62,
    "question": "The Russian steppe is most similar in topography to the",
    "option": [
      "mountains in Switzerland",
      "deserts in the Middle East",
      "rainforests in South America",
      "savannas in Africa"
    ],
    "answer": "savannas in Africa"
  },
  {
    "id": 63,
    "question": "Areas of Africa and parts of Siberia in Russia are often said to be gems-in-the-rough because they have",
    "option": [
      "extensive tracts of permanently frozen land",
      "well-developed coastal fishing industries",
      "many undeveloped natural resources",
      "decreasing populations"
    ],
    "answer": "many undeveloped natural resources"
  },
  {
    "id": 64,
    "question": "In Africa, an effect of topography and climate has been to",
    "option": [
      "encourage rapid industrialization of the interior",
      "prevent the development of kingdoms",
      "promote large-scale trade between African and Asia",
      "promote the growth of diverse societies"
    ],
    "answer": "promote the growth of diverse societies"
  },
  {
    "id": 65,
    "question": "The Suez Canal, the Strait of Hormuz, and the Strait of Gibraltar are important because they",
    "option": [
      "prevent attacks on bordering nations",
      "control access to vital trade routes",
      "limit Russian access to warm-water points",
      "prohibit the movement of ships carrying nuclear weapons"
    ],
    "answer": "control access to vital trade routes"
  },
  {
    "id": 66,
    "question": "Geographic diversity in the Middle East has contributed to",
    "option": [
      "unequal standards of living",
      "a common economic system",
      "similar political systems",
      "military alliances with Japan"
    ],
    "answer": "unequal standards of living"
  },
  {
    "id": 67,
    "question": "The Suez Canal, the Panama Canal, and the Straits of the Dardanelles are similar because they",
    "option": [
      "are strategic waterways that have been the center of conflicts",
      "was part of the French colonial empire",
      "are located in regions that are rich in natural resources",
      "prohibit the movement of ships carrying nuclear weapons"
    ],
    "answer": "are strategic waterways that have been the center of conflicts"
  },
  {
    "id": 68,
    "question": "The map shows that the",
    "option": [
      "economies of all the regions of China are developing at the same rate",
      "distribution of income in China is unequal",
      "economies of the interior provinces of China are developing faster than those of the coastal provinces",
      "economic development in China is dependent upon the cash crops of Xinjiang and Tibet"
    ],
    "answer": "distribution of income in China is unequal"
  },
  {
    "id": 69,
    "question": "One factor that accounted for Chinese influence on traditional Japanese culture was the",
    "option": [
      "continuous warfare between the countries",
      "geographic location of the countries",
      "refusal of western nations to trade with Japan",
      "annexation of Japan into the Chinese Empire"
    ],
    "answer": "geographic location of the countries"
  },
  {
    "id": 70,
    "question": "Throughout the 1800 s, Russia was interested in acquiring Turkey mainly because Russia wanted",
    "option": [
      "to maintain peace in the Middle East",
      "access to the Mediterranean Sea",
      "to reestablish the Byzantine Empire",
      "the rich farmland of the Anatolian Plateau"
    ],
    "answer": "access to the Mediterranean Sea"
  },
  {
    "id": 71,
    "question": "Which geographic factor has contributed most to the economic growth of Japan, Egypt, and Great Britain?",
    "option": [
      "variety of natural resources",
      "reliable amount of rainfall",
      "abundance of arable land",
      "access to important waterways"
    ],
    "answer": "access to important waterways"
  },
  {
    "id": 72,
    "question": "In which way have the Andes Mountains and the Amazon rain forest affected the development of Latin America?",
    "option": [
      "promoting international unity",
      "increasing cultural diversity",
      "encouraging trade agreements",
      "strengthening political alliances"
    ],
    "answer": "increasing cultural diversity"
  },
  {
    "id": 73,
    "question": "Which geographic factor has helped China remain isolated for many centuries?",
    "option": [
      "many natural harbors",
      "navigable river systems",
      "severe climate",
      "northern and western mountain ranges"
    ],
    "answer": "northern and western mountain ranges"
  },
  {
    "id": 74,
    "question": "Which statement best describes an impact of topography on eastern Europe?",
    "option": [
      "Many different languages, religions, and customs developed.",
      "A Russian czar ruled the area as a single empire.",
      "An extensive single-crop agricultural system emerged.",
      "Neighbors who were more powerful could not invade the region."
    ],
    "answer": "Many different languages, religions, and customs developed."
  },
  {
    "id": 75,
    "question": "Which geographic factor was most important to the development of the early river valley civilizations?",
    "option": [
      "fertile soils",
      "high mountains",
      "vast deserts",
      "smooth coastlines"
    ],
    "answer": "fertile soils"
  },
  {
    "id": 76,
    "question": "Which factor contributes most to the recurring food shortages in Africa?",
    "option": [
      "poor distribution of agricultural products",
      "extensive river systems",
      "location between two major oceans",
      "rainforest environment"
    ],
    "answer": "poor distribution of agricultural products"
  },
  {
    "id": 77,
    "question": "Which condition is a major obstacle to economic development in the Middle East and Northern Africa",
    "option": [
      "use of strip mining to obtain minerals",
      "reliance on capitalist economic systems",
      "lack of access to world markets",
      "scarcity of water resources"
    ],
    "answer": "scarcity of water resources"
  },
  {
    "id": 78,
    "question": "Singapore and Hong Kong have become major economic powers by taking advantage of their",
    "option": [
      "abundant mineral resources",
      "imported cheap labor from Japan",
      "profits from agricultural surpluses",
      "favorable location on international trade routes"
    ],
    "answer": "favorable location on international trade routes"
  },
  {
    "id": 79,
    "question": "Throughout the 1800 s, Russia was interested in acquiring Turkey mainly because Russia wanted",
    "option": [
      "to maintain peace in the Middle East",
      "access to the Mediterranean Sea",
      "to reestablish the Byzantine Empire",
      "the rich farmland of the Anatolian Plateau"
    ],
    "answer": "access to the Mediterranean Sea"
  },
  {
    "id": 80,
    "question": "Which conclusion can be drawn from the information in the chart?",
    "option": [
      "Developing countries are instituting programs to limit the growth of their populations.",
      "Infant mortality is a greater problem in Africa than in Asia.",
      "The nations with relatively low birthrates have relatively high per capita incomes.",
      "The national birthrate is determined by many different factors."
    ],
    "answer": "The nations with relatively low birthrates have relatively high per capita incomes."
  },
  {
    "id": 81,
    "question": "A comparison of Japan s policies before 1945 with the policies in effect after 1945 indicates that",
    "option": [
      "reduction in spending on military goods leads to economic depression",
      "dependence on foreign trade usually leads to a weakened national economy",
      "territorial aggression is not necessary to secure national economic goals",
      "democratic institutions hinder economic growth"
    ],
    "answer": "territorial aggression is not necessary to secure national economic goals"
  },
  {
    "id": 82,
    "question": "A study of Japan s economy since World War II would lead to the conclusion that",
    "option": [
      "a. government support of technological advances can improve a nation s economic position",
      "a. imperialism is necessary form the economic development of a nation",
      "a. a communist system leads to economic prosperity",
      "a. the feudal system is more economically productive than the market system"
    ],
    "answer": "a. government support of technological advances can improve a nation s economic position"
  },
  {
    "id": 83,
    "question": "Which situation has contributed most to recent Japanese economic growth?",
    "option": [
      "The Japanese government has place limits on Japanese exports.",
      "Japanese industries spend very little on the research and development of new products.",
      "The Japanese government and Japanese businesses have cooperated with each other.",
      "Japanese citizens save less of their incomes than the citizens of other industrialized nation do."
    ],
    "answer": "The Japanese government and Japanese businesses have cooperated with each other."
  },
  {
    "id": 84,
    "question": "The emergence of Japan as a world economic power has been based mostly on Japan s",
    "option": [
      "development of nuclear power",
      "abundance of fossil fuels",
      "strong traditional of military rule",
      "business enterprise and organization"
    ],
    "answer": "business enterprise and organization"
  },
  {
    "id": 85,
    "question": "In recent years, which factor has been a major reason for the economic tensions between the United States and Japan?",
    "option": [
      "Japan s trade deficit with the United States was very high",
      "the United States refused to place quotas on Japanese goods",
      "the United States imported more from Japan than it exported to Japan",
      "Japan lowered tariffs on goods imported from the United States"
    ],
    "answer": "the United States imported more from Japan than it exported to Japan"
  },
  {
    "id": 86,
    "question": "Since World War II, people in both Africa and Latin America have moved from rural to urban areas.  The major cause of this movement has been the",
    "option": [
      "rejection of traditional custom",
      "expectation of improved economic opportunities",
      "guarantee of better housing",
      "fear of civil war"
    ],
    "answer": "expectation of improved economic opportunities"
  },
  {
    "id": 87,
    "question": "Which factor best accounts for the existence of cash-crop production as a major form of agriculture in many Central American nations today?",
    "option": [
      "demand of world markets for such crops",
      "lack of modern agricultural technology",
      "inadequate supply of water and other natural resources",
      "peasant ownership of most farmlands"
    ],
    "answer": "demand of world markets for such crops"
  },
  {
    "id": 88,
    "question": "Economic development in Japan after World War II and in Communist China since the 1980 s is similar in that both nations have sought to",
    "option": [
      "end foreign investment",
      "develop their vast natural resources to achieve economic growth",
      "utilize the concepts of capitalism to improve their economies",
      "nationalize most major industries and restrict competition"
    ],
    "answer": "nationalize most major industries and restrict competition"
  },
  {
    "id": 89,
    "question": "During the 1980 s and 1990 s, the economic policies of China, supported by Deng Xiaoping, have led directly to",
    "option": [
      "an expansion of China s colonial empire",
      "an increase in trade with the West",
      "a return to a strict command economy",
      "the success of the commune system"
    ],
    "answer": "an increase in trade with the West"
  },
  {
    "id": 90,
    "question": "Which statement best explains China s economic shift toward capitalism in the 1980 s and early 1990 s?",
    "option": [
      "China s economic policies were directly influenced by the success of the Soviet economic system",
      "the Tiananmen Square massacre resulted in major economic reforms in China",
      "the success of the Cultural Revolution resulted in the increased westernization of China",
      "communist economic policies were not meeting the needs of the society"
    ],
    "answer": "communist economic policies were not meeting the needs of the society"
  },
  {
    "id": 91,
    "question": "One principle in the theory of mercantilism is that colonies should be",
    "option": [
      "granted independence as soon as possible",
      "considered an economic burden for the colonial power",
      "encouraged to develop their own industries",
      "acquired as markets and sources of raw materials"
    ],
    "answer": "acquired as markets and sources of raw materials"
  },
  {
    "id": 92,
    "question": "Which statement best describes how a command economy functioned in the Soviet Union?",
    "option": [
      "The laws of supply and demand controlled the economy.",
      "Trade policies mandated that imports exceed exports.",
      "The success of the agricultural sector controlled the price of manufactured goods.",
      "A central authority determined the type and quantity of goods to be produced."
    ],
    "answer": "A central authority determined the type and quantity of goods to be produced."
  },
  {
    "id": 93,
    "question": "To maintain its economic position, Japan has often limited the number of cars or the quantity of farm products that the United States can sell in Japan. Japan has imposed these limits to develop",
    "option": [
      "an equality-of-trade position",
      "a favorable balance of trade",
      "a more open market",
      "a belief system"
    ],
    "answer": "a favorable balance of trade"
  },
  {
    "id": 94,
    "question": "The economic policy of mercantilism first developed during the",
    "option": [
      "Age of Exploration",
      "Enlightenment",
      "Cold War",
      "Green Revolution"
    ],
    "answer": "Age of Exploration"
  },
  {
    "id": 95,
    "question": "Statement A:   The might of a country consists of gaining surpluses of gold and silver.",
    "option": ["traditional", "feudal", "command", "mercantile"],
    "answer": "mercantile"
  },
  {
    "id": 96,
    "question": "Which generalization about democracy is most valid?",
    "option": [
      "democratic political systems require a highly industrialized society",
      "democratic governments first evolved in North America",
      "democratic governments prevent their citizens from traveling abroad",
      "democratic governments protect basic civil liberties"
    ],
    "answer": "democratic governments protect basic civil liberties"
  },
  {
    "id": 97,
    "question": "Which factor is necessary for the development of democratic institutions?",
    "option": [
      "strong military forces",
      "respect for individual rights",
      "a one-party system",
      "an agricultural economy"
    ],
    "answer": "respect for individual rights"
  },
  {
    "id": 98,
    "question": "Power tends to corrupt; absolute power corrupts absolutely.",
    "option": [
      "dictatorship",
      "absolute monarchy",
      "totalitarian state",
      "representative democracy"
    ],
    "answer": "representative democracy"
  },
  {
    "id": 99,
    "question": "Democracy in modern Japan resulted primarily from",
    "option": [
      "Shinto and Buddhist beliefs about equality and justice",
      "reforms imposed by the United States after World War II",
      "a history of imperial justice under the constitution of the Emperor",
      "the diffusion of ideas and practices from China and Korea"
    ],
    "answer": "reforms imposed by the United States after World War II"
  },
  {
    "id": 100,
    "question": "After the breakup of the Austro-Hungarian Empire and the Soviet Union, new nations were formed.  Which generalization accurately reflects the effect of the breakup on these new nations?",
    "option": [
      "new nations are generally too poor and weak to become active members of the United Nations",
      "new nations rarely use their limited resources to wage war",
      "national and ethnic differences often lead to instability and violence in new nations",
      "self-determination generally leads to democratic forms of government in new nations"
    ],
    "answer": "national and ethnic differences often lead to instability and violence in new nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 101,
    "question": "Which statement describes a characteristic of the British parliamentary system today?",
    "option": [
      "the Prime Minister is elected by the majority party in Parliament",
      "the monarch serves as a strong head of state",
      "the members of the House of Commons are appointed for life",
      "the minority party has no vote in the Parliament"
    ],
    "answer": "the Prime Minister is elected by the majority party in Parliament"
  },
  {
    "id": 102,
    "question": "Which political system is the basis of Japan s government today?",
    "option": [
      "parliamentary democracy",
      "military dictatorship",
      "absolute monarchy",
      "national socialism"
    ],
    "answer": "parliamentary democracy"
  },
  {
    "id": 103,
    "question": "A constitution? What for? The Koran is the oldest and most efficient constitution in the world.  --King Faisal of Saudi Arabia (1966)",
    "option": [
      "the laws of Islam can be used to govern a country",
      "every country needs elected leaders",
      "Muslims believe in a weak central government",
      "religion should be separated from government"
    ],
    "answer": "the laws of Islam can be used to govern a country"
  },
  {
    "id": 104,
    "question": "Cavour Provokes War Against Austria    Mazzini Establishes Young Italy",
    "option": ["nationalism", "isolationism", "imperialism", "totalitarianism"],
    "answer": "nationalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 105,
    "question": "What did Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels believe would be the result when communism finally emerged as the dominant political and economic system?",
    "option": [
      "Only two classes would exist in society.",
      "All the evils of industrial society would disappear.",
      "The Soviet Union would become the world s only superpower.",
      "Citizens would own their individual homes and farms."
    ],
    "answer": "All the evils of industrial society would disappear."
  },
  {
    "id": 106,
    "question": "A similarity of the rule of the ancient Mongols and the ancient Greeks is that both",
    "option": [
      "protected the human rights of the peoples they controlled",
      "destroyed the civilizations they defeated",
      "remained isolated and peaceful for centuries",
      "established vast empires and spread their cultures to the people they conquered"
    ],
    "answer": "established vast empires and spread their cultures to the people they conquered"
  },
  {
    "id": 107,
    "question": "The code of Hammurabi is an example of",
    "option": [
      "written rules for legal procedures",
      "the power of strong kings to control trade",
      "regulations on the way to conduct wars against neighboring nations",
      "the power of a legislature to veto laws passed by absolute monarchs"
    ],
    "answer": "written rules for legal procedures"
  },
  {
    "id": 108,
    "question": ". . . suspending laws . . . , by regal [royal] authority without consent of Parliament is illegal.",
    "option": [
      "limited monarchy",
      "dynastic rule",
      "totalitarian",
      "theocracy"
    ],
    "answer": "limited monarchy"
  },
  {
    "id": 109,
    "question": "The Magna Carta, the Glorious Revolution, and the writings of John Locke all contributed to Great Britain s development of",
    "option": [
      "absolute monarchy",
      "ethnic rivalries",
      "parliamentary democracy",
      "imperialist policies"
    ],
    "answer": "parliamentary democracy"
  },
  {
    "id": 110,
    "question": "In the Soviet Union, Joseph Stalin governed by means of secret police, censorship, and purges.",
    "option": ["democracy", "totalitarian", "limited monarchy", "theocracy"],
    "answer": "totalitarian"
  },
  {
    "id": 111,
    "question": "Speaker A:   The gods approached Vishnu, the lord of creatures, and said:  Indicate to us that one person among mortals who alone is worthy of the highest rank . . .  Vishnu reflected, and brought forth a glorious son who became the first king.",
    "option": ["A and D", "B and C", "A and C", "B and D"],
    "answer": "A and D"
  },
  {
    "id": 112,
    "question": "Which aspect of a nation s culture is most directly influenced by the physical geography of that nation?",
    "option": [
      "form of government",
      "religious beliefs",
      "population distribution",
      "social class system"
    ],
    "answer": "population distribution"
  },
  {
    "id": 113,
    "question": "One reason the cultures of North Africa developed differently from the cultures of the rest of Africa was that these areas of Africa were separated by the",
    "option": [
      "Congo River Basin",
      "Great Rift Valley",
      "Sahara Desert",
      "Arabian Sea"
    ],
    "answer": "Sahara Desert"
  },
  {
    "id": 114,
    "question": "In China, the development of ethnocentrism was most influenced by",
    "option": [
      "its historic reliance on foreign nations",
      "a long history of democratic government",
      "a strong belief in Christianity",
      "its geographic isolation"
    ],
    "answer": "its geographic isolation"
  },
  {
    "id": 115,
    "question": "In most societies, works of art and architecture generally serve to",
    "option": [
      "satisfy the needs of the leaders",
      "limit the influence of religion",
      "reflect the values of that society",
      "express opposition to the government in power"
    ],
    "answer": "reflect the values of that society"
  },
  {
    "id": 116,
    "question": "In modern African nations, the continued strength of the tribe or ethnic group is a reflection of the continuing influence of",
    "option": [
      "European imperialism",
      "urban growth",
      "the slave trade",
      "traditional cultures"
    ],
    "answer": "traditional cultures"
  },
  {
    "id": 117,
    "question": "Traditional African art has had the greatest influence on",
    "option": [
      "classical Roman mosaics and pottery",
      "Renaissance painting",
      "20th century sculpture and painting",
      "Medieval European architecture"
    ],
    "answer": "20th century sculpture and painting"
  },
  {
    "id": 118,
    "question": "Which generalization is characteristic of most traditional societies?",
    "option": [
      "people move from city to city seeking new jobs",
      "sons learn the same trades as their fathers",
      "a high degree of social mobility exists",
      "all people have the same economic opportunities"
    ],
    "answer": "sons learn the same trades as their fathers"
  },
  {
    "id": 119,
    "question": "Recent archeological studies suggest the theory that",
    "option": [
      "the earliest humans evolved in the Rift Valley in Africa",
      "farming societies developed before hunting and gathering societies",
      "all the continents were settled at about the same time",
      "the wheel was used by all ancient societies"
    ],
    "answer": "the earliest humans evolved in the Rift Valley in Africa"
  },
  {
    "id": 120,
    "question": "Which factor has contributed most to the social and cultural identity of the Middle East?",
    "option": [
      "political stability of the region",
      "ability of the region to export oil",
      "lack of foreign involvement in the region",
      "strong influence of Islam on the region"
    ],
    "answer": "strong influence of Islam on the region"
  },
  {
    "id": 121,
    "question": "The Chinese called their land  Middle Kingdom.   Europeans often used the term  backward  to refer to China.  These statements best illustrate",
    "option": [
      "the failure of geographers to establish a universal terminology",
      "the importance of East Asia in world history",
      "the adoption of policies of nonalignment",
      "attitudes of ethnocentrism in both cultures"
    ],
    "answer": "attitudes of ethnocentrism in both cultures"
  },
  {
    "id": 122,
    "question": "Geographic isolation of a people frequently reinforces",
    "option": [
      "a traditional way of life",
      "the development of scientific investigation",
      "the need for higher education",
      "a process of cultural diffusion"
    ],
    "answer": "a traditional way of life"
  },
  {
    "id": 123,
    "question": "In  most societies, urbanization has",
    "option": [
      "weakened traditional values and life patterns",
      "strengthened the influence of the extended family system",
      "discouraged economic growth",
      "promoted population growth"
    ],
    "answer": "weakened traditional values and life patterns"
  },
  {
    "id": 124,
    "question": "Which statement cites an example of cultural diffusion?",
    "option": [
      "Venezuela has large reserves of oil",
      "young people dance to rock music in Russia",
      "students in China learn calligraphy in school",
      "the Caste system is an important part of life in India"
    ],
    "answer": "young people dance to rock music in Russia"
  },
  {
    "id": 125,
    "question": "In most traditional societies, the teaching of values is mainly the responsibility of the",
    "option": ["judicial system", "government", "educational system", "family"],
    "answer": "family"
  },
  {
    "id": 126,
    "question": "The study of culture primarily involves",
    "option": [
      "observing the physical environment of people",
      "learning why various peoples live as they do",
      "understanding the technology of modern machinery",
      "analyzing the personalities of children in the same family"
    ],
    "answer": "learning why various peoples live as they do"
  },
  {
    "id": 127,
    "question": "Extended families and limited social mobility are characteristic of",
    "option": [
      "constitutional monarchies",
      "polytheistic religions",
      "traditional societies",
      "socialist economies"
    ],
    "answer": "traditional societies"
  },
  {
    "id": 128,
    "question": "People in both Japan and India eat very little meat.  A study of these cultures would show that",
    "option": [
      "although these cultures have similar practices, the reasons for these practices differ",
      "the raising of cattle in both nations is very difficult due to the extreme climate",
      "neither culture is concerned with health issues",
      "the governments of both nations enforce strict dietary laws"
    ],
    "answer": "although these cultures have similar practices, the reasons for these practices differ"
  },
  {
    "id": 129,
    "question": "The dominance of the Spanish language in Latin America and continued use of the French language in Senegal are examples of",
    "option": ["cultural diffusion", "social mobility", "humanism", "Marxism"],
    "answer": "cultural diffusion"
  },
  {
    "id": 130,
    "question": "Which activity is the best example of cultural diffusion in Africa?",
    "option": [
      "weaving kente cloth in Ghana",
      "using masks in traditional African ceremonies",
      "discovering bronze sculptures from Benin",
      "practicing of Islam in Nigeria"
    ],
    "answer": "practicing of Islam in Nigeria"
  },
  {
    "id": 131,
    "question": "Which statement about India is a fact rather than an opinion?",
    "option": [
      "most Indians are happy with the Hindu practice of arranged marriages",
      "India is fortunate to have a multiparty system of government",
      "The Mongols ruled India for more that 100 years",
      "the partition of British India in 1947 helped India prosper"
    ],
    "answer": "The Mongols ruled India for more that 100 years"
  },
  {
    "id": 132,
    "question": "Which reference would be used to find the most recent information about the gross domestic product (GDP) of a nation?",
    "option": ["historical atlas", "thesaurus", "world almanac", "dictionary"],
    "answer": "world almanac"
  },
  {
    "id": 133,
    "question": "Culture is sometimes referred to as  a blueprint for living  because it",
    "option": [
      "flourished best in traditional societies",
      "includes all the things that contribute to a society s development",
      "is determined by genetics",
      "determines the types of jobs offered to the members of a society"
    ],
    "answer": "includes all the things that contribute to a society s development"
  },
  {
    "id": 134,
    "question": "In many African nations, a major result of migration from rural to urban areas has been",
    "option": [
      "a strengthening of traditional values",
      "a decline in employment opportunities for educated Africans",
      "a weakening of ancestral lines and kinship bonds",
      "increased agricultural productivity"
    ],
    "answer": "a weakening of ancestral lines and kinship bonds"
  },
  {
    "id": 135,
    "question": "Which statement about Japan is a fact rather than an opinion?",
    "option": [
      "Japanese family values have declined with modernization",
      "many of Japan s cultural traditions were borrowed from China",
      "rapid industrialization has caused few problems for the Japanese people",
      "traditional farming techniques in Japan were better than modern ones"
    ],
    "answer": "many of Japan s cultural traditions were borrowed from China"
  },
  {
    "id": 136,
    "question": "One similarity between the culture of traditional China under dynastic rule and the culture of modern China under communism is that both stress",
    "option": [
      "a state-supported religion",
      "loyalty to the authority of leaders",
      "the importance of a matriarchal society",
      "limits on population growth"
    ],
    "answer": "loyalty to the authority of leaders"
  },
  {
    "id": 137,
    "question": "The ancient Chinese expression  Middle Kingdom  and the European terms  Near East  and  Far East  best reflect",
    "option": [
      "the impact of the Enlightenment on global thinking",
      "an improved knowledge of world geography",
      "an objective view of the world s cultures",
      "the influence of ethnocentrism on geographic perspective"
    ],
    "answer": "the influence of ethnocentrism on geographic perspective"
  },
  {
    "id": 138,
    "question": "The accusations of witchcraft in 17th century England and the practice of foot-binding in 19th century China are examples of the",
    "option": [
      "discrimination against women in various cultures",
      "negative aspects of a matriarchal society",
      "gradual improvement of women s rights around the world",
      "respect give to mothers in traditional cultures"
    ],
    "answer": "discrimination against women in various cultures"
  },
  {
    "id": 139,
    "question": "Buildings such as the Gothic cathedrals in Western Europe and the Parthenon in ancient Greece reflect each society s",
    "option": [
      "imperialistic attitudes",
      "cultural values",
      "belief in democracy",
      "rigid social structure"
    ],
    "answer": "cultural values"
  },
  {
    "id": 140,
    "question": "Before towns and cities can develop in a society, the society needs to establish",
    "option": [
      "an educational system",
      "an agricultural surplus",
      "a writing system",
      "a democratic government"
    ],
    "answer": "an agricultural surplus"
  },
  {
    "id": 141,
    "question": "Which statement best supports the idea that cultural diffusion has greatly affected Southeast Asia?",
    "option": [
      "the population of Southeast Asia is concentrated in rural areas",
      "monsoon climates affect food production in Indonesia",
      "a reliance on subsistence agriculture remains a problem for many Southeast Asian economies",
      "Buddhism, Hinduism, and Islam are practiced throughout Southeast Asia"
    ],
    "answer": "Buddhism, Hinduism, and Islam are practiced throughout Southeast Asia"
  },
  {
    "id": 142,
    "question": "In India, which aspect of society has been most heavily influenced by religious beliefs, tradition, and the division of labor?",
    "option": [
      "caste system",
      "policy of neutrality",
      "urbanization",
      "parliamentary government"
    ],
    "answer": "caste system"
  },
  {
    "id": 143,
    "question": "One similarity between the cultures of traditional China and traditional Japan was that",
    "option": [
      "the educated class was held in high esteem",
      "religion played a minor role in society",
      "social mobility was encouraged",
      "the people elected the political leaders"
    ],
    "answer": "the educated class was held in high esteem"
  },
  {
    "id": 144,
    "question": "The invention of writing systems and the growth of cities occurred only in civilizations that",
    "option": [
      "originated in south Asia",
      "developed matriarchal leadership",
      "developed complex institutions",
      "borrowed heavily from the Greeks and Romans"
    ],
    "answer": "developed complex institutions"
  },
  {
    "id": 145,
    "question": "A sociologist interested in Indian culture would most likely focus on the study of",
    "option": [
      "Hinduism and its influence on life in India",
      "India s development of nuclear weapons",
      "the parliamentary government of India",
      "the influence of agricultural production on India s Gross national Product (GNP)"
    ],
    "answer": "Hinduism and its influence on life in India"
  },
  {
    "id": 146,
    "question": "In India, the Caste System determined a person s occupation, personal associations, and marriage partner.  This situation shows that the Caste system",
    "option": [
      "has helped eliminate ethnic and religious rivalries",
      "has promoted social mobility within Indian society",
      "has been stronger in urban areas that in rural areas",
      "has been a way of life as well as an element of religion"
    ],
    "answer": "has been a way of life as well as an element of religion"
  },
  {
    "id": 147,
    "question": "During the centuries of dynastic rule, the Chinese rejected other cultures as inferior to their own.  This situation illustrates the concept of",
    "option": [
      "ethnocentrism",
      "imperialism",
      "social mobility",
      "cultural diffusion"
    ],
    "answer": "ethnocentrism"
  },
  {
    "id": 148,
    "question": "Which statement best describes the status of women in most traditional Asian societies?",
    "option": [
      "women were encouraged to obtain an education",
      "women were expected to run for political office",
      "women were expected to dedicate their lives to their families",
      "women were encouraged to work outside the home"
    ],
    "answer": "women were expected to dedicate their lives to their families"
  },
  {
    "id": 149,
    "question": "One result of the Neolithic Revolution was",
    "option": [
      "an increase in the number of nomadic tribes",
      "a reliance on hunting and gathering for food",
      "the establishment of villages and the rise of governments",
      "a decrease in trade between cultural groups"
    ],
    "answer": "the establishment of villages and the rise of governments"
  },
  {
    "id": 150,
    "question": "The Japanese feudal system and the Hindu caste system are similar in that both systems",
    "option": [
      "promoted social mobility",
      "developed a rigid class structure",
      "encouraged the people to take part in government",
      "resulted in economic opportunities for the lower classes"
    ],
    "answer": "developed a rigid class structure"
  },
  {
    "id": 151,
    "question": "Which situation best illustrates a traditional practice of women in Masai society?",
    "option": [
      "a young woman leaving her village to attend a university in the capital city",
      "an educated woman returning to her village to become leader of her tribe",
      "a young woman marrying and her husband giving cattle to her family as a wedding gift",
      "a young mother discouraging her children from practicing animism"
    ],
    "answer": "a young woman marrying and her husband giving cattle to her family as a wedding gift"
  },
  {
    "id": 152,
    "question": "The Japanese feudal system and the Hindu caste system are similar in that both systems",
    "option": [
      "promoted social mobility",
      "developed a rigid class structure",
      "encouraged the people to take part in government",
      "resulted in economic opportunities for the lower classes"
    ],
    "answer": "developed a rigid class structure"
  },
  {
    "id": 153,
    "question": "Which statement concerning modern Japan is most accurate?",
    "option": [
      "Japan has modernized while maintaining some elements of its traditional culture",
      "Japan has become a leader in global peacekeeping efforts",
      "Japan has shown little concern for its natural environment",
      "Japan has severed all traditional ties in favor of western values"
    ],
    "answer": "Japan has modernized while maintaining some elements of its traditional culture"
  },
  {
    "id": 154,
    "question": "The introduction of Buddhism into China and of Islam into Indonesia are examples of",
    "option": [
      "social mobility",
      "cultural diffusion",
      "ethnocentrism",
      "interdependence"
    ],
    "answer": "cultural diffusion"
  },
  {
    "id": 155,
    "question": "In a traditional society, the influence of an extended family decreases when that society is",
    "option": [
      "being governed by a council of elders",
      "experiencing rapid urbanization and industrialization",
      "faced with a decreasing population",
      "raising only enough crops to feed its people"
    ],
    "answer": "experiencing rapid urbanization and industrialization"
  },
  {
    "id": 156,
    "question": "Which factor has been most responsible for the common culture found in Japan?",
    "option": [
      "religious diversity",
      "success of democracy",
      "ethnic homogeneity",
      "political instability"
    ],
    "answer": "ethnic homogeneity"
  },
  {
    "id": 157,
    "question": "From a little spark may burst a mighty flame.   --Dante",
    "option": [
      "All cultures are concerned with transportation and conservation.",
      "In all cultures, people make excuses for their mistakes.",
      "Geography is important to the development of all cultures.",
      "People from different cultures often view situations in similar ways."
    ],
    "answer": "People from different cultures often view situations in similar ways."
  },
  {
    "id": 158,
    "question": "The Church of the Holy Sepulchre, the Dome of the Rock, and the Western (Wailing) Wall are religious sites in Jerusalem. These sites symbolize the",
    "option": [
      "Roman domination of the Mediterranean region in the 1st century",
      "cultural diversity of the Middle East",
      "limited architectural skills of builders in the Middle East",
      "geographic isolation of the city"
    ],
    "answer": "cultural diversity of the Middle East"
  },
  {
    "id": 159,
    "question": "Throughout much of history, both China and Japan held a common view that other nations were",
    "option": [
      "valued sources of worthwhile knowledge",
      "envoys of an advanced civilization",
      "barbarians not worthy of their attention",
      "sources of cheap labor and goods"
    ],
    "answer": "barbarians not worthy of their attention"
  },
  {
    "id": 160,
    "question": "Historians are interested in studying Maya ruins in Mexico, the haiku poetry of Japan, and the music of Chopin because such cultural and intellectual developments",
    "option": [
      "reflect the values of that society",
      "illustrate the economic status of individuals in that society",
      "help to explain the role of geography in that society",
      "reveal the political structure of that society"
    ],
    "answer": "reflect the values of that society"
  },
  {
    "id": 161,
    "question": "Which term is used to describe the spread of Buddhism from India through Southeast Asia?",
    "option": [
      "ethnocentrism",
      "isolation",
      "imperialism",
      "cultural diffusion"
    ],
    "answer": "cultural diffusion"
  },
  {
    "id": 162,
    "question": "One reason for the development of an early civilization in the Tigris-Euphrates river valleys was that",
    "option": [
      "the location protected the people from land invasion",
      "periodic flooding left rich soil, which was ideal for farming",
      "these rivers provided a direct trade route between Europe and Asia",
      "these rivers flowed into the Mediterranean Sea"
    ],
    "answer": "periodic flooding left rich soil, which was ideal for farming"
  },
  {
    "id": 163,
    "question": "Which characteristic did the early civilizations that developed along the Nile, the Tigris-Euphrates and the Huang He (Yellow River) have in common?",
    "option": [
      "each society s religious beliefs were based on monotheism",
      "urban communities were built using iron and steel tools",
      "the form of government in each community was based on male suffrage",
      "transportation and communication were promoted by a mild climate, fertile soil, and natural waterways"
    ],
    "answer": "transportation and communication were promoted by a mild climate, fertile soil, and natural waterways"
  },
  {
    "id": 164,
    "question": "The early civilizations of the Nile River Valley, Mesopotamia, and the Yellow River Valley were similar because they were",
    "option": [
      "industrialized societies",
      "monotheistic",
      "dependent on fertile land",
      "dependent on each other for trade"
    ],
    "answer": "dependent on fertile land"
  },
  {
    "id": 165,
    "question": "One way in which the civilizations of the Sumerians, the Phoenicians, and the Maya were similar is that each",
    "option": [
      "developed extensive writing systems",
      "emphasized equality in education",
      "established monotheistic religions",
      "encouraged democratic participation in government"
    ],
    "answer": "developed extensive writing systems"
  },
  {
    "id": 166,
    "question": "If a seignior (noble) has knocked out the tooth of a seignior of his own rank, they shall knock out his tooth.  But if he has knocked out a commoner s tooth, he shall pay one-third mina of silver.   -Code of Hammurabi",
    "option": [
      "all men were equal under the law",
      "fines were preferable to corporal punishment",
      "divisions existed between social classes",
      "violence was always punished with violence"
    ],
    "answer": "divisions existed between social classes"
  },
  {
    "id": 167,
    "question": "The ancient civilizations of Mesopotamia and Egypt were similar in that both cultures",
    "option": [
      "developed along rivers",
      "used the ziggurat form for their temples",
      "established trade routes to China",
      "used a hieroglyphic writing system"
    ],
    "answer": "developed along rivers"
  },
  {
    "id": 168,
    "question": "Notre Dame Cathedral in Paris, the Dome of the Rock in Jerusalem and the Great Pyramid in Egypt are examples of",
    "option": [
      "architectural accomplishments that reflect religious beliefs",
      "the influence of Buddhist architecture on conquered nations",
      "ancient architectural monuments no longer in use",
      "the influence of cultural diffusion on contemporary architecture"
    ],
    "answer": "architectural accomplishments that reflect religious beliefs"
  },
  {
    "id": 169,
    "question": "Judaism, Islam, and Christianity share a belief in",
    "option": [
      "the central authority of the Pope",
      "a prohibition of the consumption of port",
      "reincarnation and the Four Noble Truths",
      "monotheism and ethical conduct"
    ],
    "answer": "monotheism and ethical conduct"
  },
  {
    "id": 170,
    "question": "Which is a valid statement about the history of South Asia?",
    "option": [
      "Religious beliefs have both unified and divided the people of the region.",
      "Little cultural diffusion has occurred in this region.",
      "Urbanization has strengthened the traditional beliefs and lifestyles of the people of the region.",
      "Superpower involvement has brought peace and economic prosperity to the region."
    ],
    "answer": "Religious beliefs have both unified and divided the people of the region."
  },
  {
    "id": 171,
    "question": "When I go to the office, I put on my shirt and I take off my caste; when I come home, I take off my shirt and I put on my caste.",
    "option": [
      "the caste system continues to influence Indian society",
      "the caste system has been reflected by most Indians",
      "successful urban workers in India belong the same Caste",
      "the Indian government officially supports the Caste system"
    ],
    "answer": "the caste system continues to influence Indian society"
  },
  {
    "id": 172,
    "question": "According the teachings of Confucius, the key to the successful organization of society is that",
    "option": [
      "the ruler should be chosen democratically",
      "the evil in humans must be eliminated",
      "ancestor worship should be discontinued",
      "individuals should know and do what is expected of them"
    ],
    "answer": "individuals should know and do what is expected of them"
  },
  {
    "id": 173,
    "question": "In traditional Chinese culture, which philosophy had the greatest influence on the development of social order and political organization?",
    "option": ["Taoism", "Shintoism", "Confucianism", "Marxism"],
    "answer": "Confucianism"
  },
  {
    "id": 174,
    "question": "The teachings of Confucius encouraged people to",
    "option": [
      "put their own interests first",
      "reject government authority",
      "believe in reincarnation",
      "follow a code of moral conduct"
    ],
    "answer": "follow a code of moral conduct"
  },
  {
    "id": 175,
    "question": "In Japan, the martial arts, the tea ceremony, and flower arranging best reflect the influences of",
    "option": [
      "imperialism and militarism",
      "Buddhism and Shintoism",
      "capitalism",
      "mercantilism"
    ],
    "answer": "Buddhism and Shintoism"
  },
  {
    "id": 176,
    "question": "A person who practices the Shinto faith would be most likely to",
    "option": [
      "visit a shrine placed on the shore of a lake",
      "pray five times a day",
      "bathe in the Ganges River",
      "make a pilgrimage to Jerusalem"
    ],
    "answer": "visit a shrine placed on the shore of a lake"
  },
  {
    "id": 177,
    "question": "Taoism and Shintoism are similar in that both religions stress",
    "option": [
      "adhering to the five Confucian relationships",
      "following the Eightfold Path",
      "developing harmony between humans and nature",
      "believing in one God"
    ],
    "answer": "developing harmony between humans and nature"
  },
  {
    "id": 178,
    "question": "One similarity between the Five Pillars of Islam and the Ten Commandments is that both",
    "option": [
      "support a belief in reincarnation",
      "promote learning as a means to salvation",
      "encourage the use of statues to symbolize God",
      "provide a guide to proper ethical and moral behavior"
    ],
    "answer": "provide a guide to proper ethical and moral behavior"
  },
  {
    "id": 179,
    "question": "One way in which Eastern Orthodoxy, Roman Catholicism, and Protestantism are similar is that each",
    "option": [
      "accepts the supreme authority of the Pope",
      "rejects the Old Testament as part of the Bible",
      "is a branch of Christianity",
      "was once the official religion of the Byzantine Empire"
    ],
    "answer": "is a branch of Christianity"
  },
  {
    "id": 180,
    "question": "The Koran, jihad, and the hegira are most closely associated with the practice of",
    "option": ["Islam", "Judaism", "Shinto", "Buddhism"],
    "answer": "Islam"
  },
  {
    "id": 181,
    "question": "The Buddhist religion teaches that salvation is earned by",
    "option": [
      "following the Ten Commandments",
      "worshiping Allah as the one true god",
      "learning to give up selfish desire",
      "being baptized and confirmed"
    ],
    "answer": "learning to give up selfish desire"
  },
  {
    "id": 182,
    "question": "Confucianism in traditional China served to",
    "option": [
      "maintain social order",
      "create ethnic unrest",
      "emphasize material wealth",
      "support democratic government"
    ],
    "answer": "maintain social order"
  },
  {
    "id": 183,
    "question": "Traditional animistic beliefs in Africa, Asia, and Latin America are based on",
    "option": [
      "a desire for wealth",
      "a written tradition",
      "an appreciation for the forces of nature",
      "a willingness to accept Christianity"
    ],
    "answer": "an appreciation for the forces of nature"
  },
  {
    "id": 184,
    "question": "Jewish religions and cultural identity has been greatly influenced by",
    "option": [
      "Ramadan and the concept of reincarnation",
      "the Torah and the Diaspora",
      "the New Testament and the Four Noble Truths",
      "the Koran and the code of bushido"
    ],
    "answer": "the Torah and the Diaspora"
  },
  {
    "id": 185,
    "question": "In India, the Caste system determined a person s occupation, personal associations, and marriage partner.  This situation shows that the Caste system",
    "option": [
      "has helped eliminate ethnic and religious rivalries",
      "has promoted social mobility within Indian society",
      "has been stronger in urban areas that in rural areas",
      "has been a way of life as well as an element of religion"
    ],
    "answer": "has been a way of life as well as an element of religion"
  },
  {
    "id": 186,
    "question": "Mansa Musa s journey to Mecca in the 1300 s is evidence that",
    "option": [
      "the Crusades had a great influence on western Africa",
      "most African leaders were educated in the Middle East",
      "European culture was superior to the cultures of western Africa",
      "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire"
    ],
    "answer": "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire"
  },
  {
    "id": 187,
    "question": "From as early as I can remember, the Emperor was an important presence even in our remote home.  He was a descendant of the gods from thousands of years before, never to be looked at or listened to by mere mortals, a presence to be revered and protected and obeyed Finally , my family and neighbors gathered around the radio and listened in stunned silence to the voice that had never before been heard, saying he was only human after all.  Everyone was crying.  I was sad and confused",
    "option": ["Shintoism", "Christianity", "Islam", "Judaism"],
    "answer": "Shintoism"
  },
  {
    "id": 188,
    "question": "Beginning with childhood, all of man s study is centered on one aim alone   to emerge successfully from the three days  examination   and all he has in his mind is what success can bring to him in terms of power, influence, and prestige.",
    "option": [
      "civil service system",
      "social welfare system",
      "contemplation of nature",
      "religious practices"
    ],
    "answer": "civil service system"
  },
  {
    "id": 189,
    "question": "The Eightfold Path, the Four Noble Truths, and the concept of nirvana are associated with the religion of",
    "option": ["Islam", "Jainism", "Shinto", "Buddhism"],
    "answer": "Buddhism"
  },
  {
    "id": 190,
    "question": "One way in which the Vedas, the Bible, and the Koran are similar is that these religious books",
    "option": [
      "provide guidelines to govern the behavior of believers",
      "deny the existence of a supreme being who rules the universe",
      "encourage strife between segments of believers",
      "support political rebellions to overthrow existing governments"
    ],
    "answer": "provide guidelines to govern the behavior of believers"
  },
  {
    "id": 191,
    "question": "Which values are most closely associated with the fundamental principles of Buddhism?",
    "option": [
      "competition and financial success",
      "maintaining the caste system and providing education for all people",
      "practicing nonviolence and giving up worldly desires",
      "self-determination and democracy"
    ],
    "answer": "practicing nonviolence and giving up worldly desires"
  },
  {
    "id": 192,
    "question": "A belief of animism is that",
    "option": [
      "after death the soul is reborn in another human form",
      "holy wars must be fought to gain entry into heaven",
      "meditation leads followers to nirvana",
      "spirits of nature inhabit all living and nonliving objects"
    ],
    "answer": "spirits of nature inhabit all living and nonliving objects"
  },
  {
    "id": 193,
    "question": "The Analects :    In his [the leader] personal conduct, he was respectful.",
    "option": ["anarchy", "law", "trade", "architecture"],
    "answer": "law"
  },
  {
    "id": 194,
    "question": "A major impact of Ancient Greece and Rome on Western Civilization was that",
    "option": [
      "the Greeks and Romans succeeded in achieving a classless society, which was later copied in Western Europe",
      "Greek sculpture and Roman architecture were much admired and copied in the 18th and 19th centuries",
      "Greece and Rome transmitted Islamic philosophy to the areas they conquered",
      "Greek and Latin are still widely spoken in universities throughout the West"
    ],
    "answer": "Greek sculpture and Roman architecture were much admired and copied in the 18th and 19th centuries"
  },
  {
    "id": 195,
    "question": "The Ancient Romans  most significant contribution to Europe has been in the area of",
    "option": ["economics", "poetry", "drama", "law"],
    "answer": "law"
  },
  {
    "id": 196,
    "question": "An immediate result of the fall of the Roman Empire was",
    "option": [
      "a renewed interest in education and the arts",
      "a period of disorder and weak central government",
      "an increase in trade and manufacturing",
      "the growth of cities and dominance by the middle class"
    ],
    "answer": "a period of disorder and weak central government"
  },
  {
    "id": 197,
    "question": "The Ancient Athenians are credited with",
    "option": [
      "inventing and using the wheel",
      "eliminating slavery",
      "establishing governments that had democratic elements",
      "inventing the printing press"
    ],
    "answer": "establishing governments that had democratic elements"
  },
  {
    "id": 198,
    "question": "Both the Ancient Romans and the Ancient Chinese viewed foreigners as barbarians.  This is an example of",
    "option": [
      "cultural diffusion",
      "materialism",
      "imperialism",
      "ethnocentrism"
    ],
    "answer": "ethnocentrism"
  },
  {
    "id": 199,
    "question": "A major contribution of the Roman Republic to Western European culture was the",
    "option": [
      "concept of government by laws",
      "belief that political power should be controlled by the military",
      "establishment of agricultural communes",
      "rejection of the concept of slavery"
    ],
    "answer": "concept of government by laws"
  },
  {
    "id": 200,
    "question": "Which ancient civilization established the basis of western democracy?",
    "option": ["Phoenician", "Egyptian", "Sumerian", "Greek"],
    "answer": "Greek"
  },
  {
    "id": 201,
    "question": "The political system of the Ancient Roman Empire was characterized by",
    "option": [
      "a strong central government",
      "rule by a coalition of emperors and religious leaders",
      "universal suffrage in national elections",
      "a strict adherence to constitutional principles"
    ],
    "answer": "a strong central government"
  },
  {
    "id": 202,
    "question": "Which societal condition was basic to the development of Greek philosophy?",
    "option": [
      "rigid social classes",
      "emphasis on individualism",
      "religious uniformity",
      "mass education"
    ],
    "answer": "mass education"
  },
  {
    "id": 203,
    "question": "Important long-term contributions of Ancient Greek and Roman civilizations are primarily found in the area of",
    "option": [
      "military technology",
      "religious doctrine",
      "economic policy and planning",
      "government and law"
    ],
    "answer": "government and law"
  },
  {
    "id": 204,
    "question": "The Ancient Greek city-state of Sparta",
    "option": [
      "was primarily concerned with the health of their people",
      "was a powerful military state",
      "granted universal suffrage to their people",
      "placed great emphasis on literature and the arts"
    ],
    "answer": "was a powerful military state"
  },
  {
    "id": 205,
    "question": "An immediate result of the fall of the Roman Empire was",
    "option": [
      "a renewed interest in education and the arts",
      "a period of disorder and weak central government",
      "an increase in trade and manufacturing",
      "the growth of cities and dominance by the middle class"
    ],
    "answer": "a period of disorder and weak central government"
  },
  {
    "id": 206,
    "question": "Which societal condition was basic to the development of Greek philosophy and Renaissance art?",
    "option": [
      "rigid social classes",
      "emphasis on individualism",
      "religious uniformity",
      "mass education"
    ],
    "answer": "emphasis on individualism"
  },
  {
    "id": 207,
    "question": "An influence that spread from the Byzantine Empire to Early Russia was the",
    "option": [
      "Orthodox Christian religion",
      "use of the Latin alphabet",
      "beginning of democracy",
      "factory system"
    ],
    "answer": "Orthodox Christian religion"
  },
  {
    "id": 208,
    "question": "The adoption of the Eastern Orthodox religion and the Cyrillic alphabet by the Russian people occurred as a result of",
    "option": [
      "territorial expansion during the reign of Catherine the Great",
      "the westernization policies of Peter the Great",
      "contact with Byzantine culture in the 10th century",
      "the influence of the Crusaders during the Middle Ages"
    ],
    "answer": "contact with Byzantine culture in the 10th century"
  },
  {
    "id": 209,
    "question": "One similarity between Axum, Kush, and Nubia was that they were",
    "option": [
      "military leaders in the Neolithic Age",
      "rivers along which early trade developed",
      "writers of epic poems about Greek cities",
      "early civilizations in Africa"
    ],
    "answer": "early civilizations in Africa"
  },
  {
    "id": 210,
    "question": "One similarity between the decline of the Roman Empire and the fall of the Manchu Dynasty was that both initially led to",
    "option": [
      "improved economic conditions",
      "democratically elected governments",
      "political chaos and decentralization of government",
      "major accomplishments in art, science, and technology"
    ],
    "answer": "political chaos and decentralization of government"
  },
  {
    "id": 211,
    "question": "A major contribution of the Roman Empire to Western society was the development of",
    "option": [
      "gunpowder",
      "the principles of revolutionary socialism",
      "monotheism",
      "an effective legal system"
    ],
    "answer": "an effective legal system"
  },
  {
    "id": 212,
    "question": "After the fall of Rome, the eastern portion of the Roman Empire became known as the",
    "option": [
      "Persian Empire",
      "Byzantine Empire",
      "Mongol Empire",
      "Gupta Empire"
    ],
    "answer": "Byzantine Empire"
  },
  {
    "id": 213,
    "question": "Which conclusion can be drawn from a study of the early civilizations of Axum, Kush, Mali and Songhai?",
    "option": [
      "these African societies flourished at the same time",
      "farming was more extensive in the Nile River Valley than it was in the Fertile Crescent",
      "the Neolithic Revolution occurred in Africa",
      "these societies had a long and rich history before their first contact with Europeans"
    ],
    "answer": "these societies had a long and rich history before their first contact with Europeans"
  },
  {
    "id": 214,
    "question": "A major effect of the decline of the Roman Empire was that Western Europe",
    "option": [
      "came under the control of the Muslims",
      "was absorbed by the Byzantine Empire",
      "returned to a republican form of government",
      "entered a period of chaos and disorder"
    ],
    "answer": "entered a period of chaos and disorder"
  },
  {
    "id": 215,
    "question": "Which characteristic was common to the Golden Age of Greece and the Italian Renaissance?",
    "option": [
      "a strong military led to national unity",
      "written constitutions led to the establishment of democratic governments",
      "prosperity led to the creation of many works of art",
      "political instability led directly to the formation of unified nation-states"
    ],
    "answer": "prosperity led to the creation of many works of art"
  },
  {
    "id": 216,
    "question": "During the centuries of dynastic rule, the Chinese rejected other cultures as inferior to their own.  This situation illustrates the concept of",
    "option": [
      "ethnocentrism",
      "imperialism",
      "social mobility",
      "cultural diffusion"
    ],
    "answer": "ethnocentrism"
  },
  {
    "id": 217,
    "question": "Alexander the Great s conquests of Greece, Asia Minor, Egypt, and Persia led to the",
    "option": [
      "spread of Hellenic culture",
      "adoption of a feudal system",
      "establishment of representative democracy",
      "spread of Islamic culture throughout Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "spread of Hellenic culture"
  },
  {
    "id": 218,
    "question": "One similarity between the Ancient African kingdoms of Egypt, Ghana, Mali and Songhai is that all of these kingdoms were located",
    "option": [
      "in mountainous terrain",
      "in coastal areas",
      "on major trading routes",
      "in rain forest areas"
    ],
    "answer": "on major trading routes"
  },
  {
    "id": 219,
    "question": "One reason the ancient kingdoms in western Africa prospered was that they",
    "option": [
      "were located along the Tigris and Euphrates rivers",
      "had no contact with the rest of the world",
      "followed the Hindu beliefs of their rulers",
      "developed extensive trade in gold, ivory, and salt"
    ],
    "answer": "developed extensive trade in gold, ivory, and salt"
  },
  {
    "id": 220,
    "question": "Mansa Musa s journey to Mecca in the 1300 s is evidence that",
    "option": [
      "the Crusades had a great influence on western Africa",
      "most African leaders were educated in the Middle East",
      "European culture was superior to the cultures of western Africa",
      "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire"
    ],
    "answer": "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire"
  },
  {
    "id": 221,
    "question": "The contributions of the ancient civilizations of Ghana, Axum, Kush, and Mali demonstrate that",
    "option": [
      "industrial technology was needed for African civilizations to develop",
      "many African civilizations developed in southern Africa",
      "most of the African Continent was unified under a single political system",
      "advanced societies developed in Africa before Europeans colonized this region"
    ],
    "answer": "advanced societies developed in Africa before Europeans colonized this region"
  },
  {
    "id": 222,
    "question": "A similarity between the ancient western African kingdoms of Mali, Ghana, and Songhai is that these kingdoms",
    "option": [
      "limited the power of their rulers",
      "practiced Christianity",
      "established economies based on trade",
      "isolated themselves from contact with other cultures"
    ],
    "answer": "established economies based on trade"
  },
  {
    "id": 223,
    "question": "Western Europe owed a debt of gratitude to the Empire that for almost a thousand years ensured the survival of Christianity during a time when Europe was too weak to accomplish the task.",
    "option": ["Hellenistic", "Mongol", "Byzantine", "Ottoman"],
    "answer": "Byzantine"
  },
  {
    "id": 224,
    "question": "An influence that spread from the Byzantine Empire to Early Russia was the",
    "option": [
      "Orthodox Christian religion",
      "use of the Latin alphabet",
      "beginning of democracy",
      "factory system"
    ],
    "answer": "Orthodox Christian religion"
  },
  {
    "id": 225,
    "question": "Which empire introduced the Eastern Orthodox Church and the Cyrillic alphabet to Russia?",
    "option": ["Mongol", "Byzantine", "British", "Gupta"],
    "answer": "Byzantine"
  },
  {
    "id": 226,
    "question": "A major feature of the Golden Age of Moslem culture was the",
    "option": [
      "political and economic isolation of the Arab world",
      "development of the foundations of modern science and mathematics",
      "adoption of democratic government",
      "persecution of Jews and Christians"
    ],
    "answer": "development of the foundations of modern science and mathematics"
  },
  {
    "id": 227,
    "question": "Which factor helps explain the scientific and literary achievements of the Muslims during their Golden Age (A.D. 800-1300)?",
    "option": [
      "expansion of trans-Atlantic trade",
      "innovations introduced by the Europeans during the Renaissance",
      "cultural diversity accepted by many Islamic governments",
      "legal equality of all people in the Islamic empire"
    ],
    "answer": "cultural diversity accepted by many Islamic governments"
  },
  {
    "id": 228,
    "question": "Mansa Musa s journey to Mecca in the 1300 s is evidence that",
    "option": [
      "the Crusades had a great influence on western Africa",
      "most African leaders were educated in the Middle East",
      "European culture was superior to the cultures of western Africa",
      "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire"
    ],
    "answer": "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire"
  },
  {
    "id": 229,
    "question": "Which activity occurred during the Golden Age of Muslim culture?",
    "option": [
      "destruction of books containing Greek and Roman ideas",
      "beginning of pilgrimages to Mecca",
      "opposition to freedom of thought and to foreign ideas by rulers",
      "major discoveries in mathematics and science"
    ],
    "answer": "major discoveries in mathematics and science"
  },
  {
    "id": 230,
    "question": "The contributions of the Golden Age of Islamic civilization include",
    "option": [
      "advances in mathematics",
      "irrigation systems",
      "polytheistic beliefs",
      "gunpowder and guns"
    ],
    "answer": "advances in mathematics"
  },
  {
    "id": 231,
    "question": "In Europe during the Middle Ages, increases in trade and commerce resulted in",
    "option": [
      "lower living standards for industrial workers",
      "decreased economic rivalry between kings",
      "increased political power for the clergy",
      "development of towns and cities"
    ],
    "answer": "development of towns and cities"
  },
  {
    "id": 232,
    "question": "During the Middle Ages, Europeans did not eat potatoes or corn because these vegetables",
    "option": [
      "were forbidden by the Catholic Church for religious reasons",
      "had not yet been introduced to Europe from the New World",
      "were believed to be poisonous",
      "were too expensive to import from China"
    ],
    "answer": "had not yet been introduced to Europe from the New World"
  },
  {
    "id": 233,
    "question": "All things were under its domain...its power was such that no one could hope to escape its scrutiny.",
    "option": ["the Guild", "Knighthood", "the Church", "the nation-state"],
    "answer": "the Church"
  },
  {
    "id": 234,
    "question": "The Middle Ages in Western Europe was characterized by",
    "option": [
      "the manor system and the importance of land ownership",
      "absolute monarchies and strong central governments",
      "decreased emphasis on religion in daily life",
      "extensive trade with Asia and the Middle East"
    ],
    "answer": "the manor system and the importance of land ownership"
  },
  {
    "id": 235,
    "question": "Feudal societies are generally characterized by",
    "option": [
      "an emphasis on social order",
      "a representative government",
      "many economic opportunities",
      "the protection of political rights"
    ],
    "answer": "an emphasis on social order"
  },
  {
    "id": 236,
    "question": "In Europe, a long-term effect of the Crusades was",
    "option": [
      "the strengthening of the feudal system",
      "the adoption of Islamic religious practices",
      "an increased demand for goods from the East",
      "increased European isolation"
    ],
    "answer": "an increased demand for goods from the East"
  },
  {
    "id": 237,
    "question": "The art, music, and philosophy of the medieval period in Europe generally dealt with",
    "option": [
      "human scientific achievements",
      "religious themes",
      "materialism",
      "classic Greek and Roman subjects"
    ],
    "answer": "religious themes"
  },
  {
    "id": 238,
    "question": "Which statement best describes the result of the Crusades?",
    "option": [
      "Europeans maintained a lasting control over much of the Middle East",
      "Islamic influence dominated Europe",
      "Europeans developed tolerance of Non-Christian religions",
      "trade between Europe and the Middle East was expanded"
    ],
    "answer": "trade between Europe and the Middle East was expanded"
  },
  {
    "id": 239,
    "question": "What were two indirect results of the Crusades?",
    "option": [
      "trade and commerce increased and the feudal system was strengthened",
      "trade and commerce declined and the feudal system was strengthened",
      "trade and commerce increased and the feudal system was weakened",
      "trade and commerce declined and the feudal system was weakened"
    ],
    "answer": "trade and commerce increased and the feudal system was weakened"
  },
  {
    "id": 240,
    "question": "In Europe during the Middle Ages, the force that provided unification and stability was the",
    "option": [
      "central government in Rome",
      "military alliance between France and Germany",
      "federation of the craft guilds",
      "Roman Catholic Church"
    ],
    "answer": "Roman Catholic Church"
  },
  {
    "id": 241,
    "question": "Feudalism in Western Europe was similar to feudalism in Japan in that",
    "option": [
      "power was based on class relationships",
      "equality among the social classes",
      "direct democracy",
      "monotheism"
    ],
    "answer": "power was based on class relationships"
  },
  {
    "id": 242,
    "question": "Which is a characteristic of a feudal society?",
    "option": [
      "rapid social change",
      "high literacy rate",
      "industrial-based economy",
      "rigid class structure"
    ],
    "answer": "rigid class structure"
  },
  {
    "id": 243,
    "question": "In Europe, the Crusades resulted in",
    "option": [
      "greater isolation of the region from the world",
      "an increased demand for goods from the Middle East and Asia",
      "the adoption of Islam as the official religion of many European nations",
      "the strengthening of the feudal system"
    ],
    "answer": "an increased demand for goods from the Middle East and Asia"
  },
  {
    "id": 244,
    "question": "One important effect of the Crusades on Western Europe was that they",
    "option": [
      "led to a decline in the importance of the church in Western Europe",
      "furthered cultural diffusion throughout Western Europe",
      "introduced the Industrial Revolution to Western Europe",
      "ended the western European quest for an overseas empire"
    ],
    "answer": "furthered cultural diffusion throughout Western Europe"
  },
  {
    "id": 245,
    "question": "In European feudal society, an individual s social status was generally determined by",
    "option": [
      "birth",
      "education and training",
      "individual abilities",
      "marriage"
    ],
    "answer": "birth"
  },
  {
    "id": 246,
    "question": "Which economic system existed in Europe during the early Middle Ages?",
    "option": ["free market", "socialism", "manorialism", "command"],
    "answer": "manorialism"
  },
  {
    "id": 247,
    "question": "One major result of the Crusades was the",
    "option": [
      "permanent occupation of the Holy Land by the Europeans",
      "long-term decrease in European trade",
      "conversion of most Muslims to Christianity",
      "spread of Middle Eastern culture and technology to Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "spread of Middle Eastern culture and technology to Europe"
  },
  {
    "id": 248,
    "question": "The growth of feudalism in Europe during the Middle Ages was primarily caused by the",
    "option": [
      "rivalry between the colonial empires",
      "suppression of internationalism",
      "decline of the Roman Catholic Church",
      "collapse of a strong central government"
    ],
    "answer": "collapse of a strong central government"
  },
  {
    "id": 249,
    "question": "The Crusades have been called  history s most successful failures.     Which statement best explains this expression?",
    "option": [
      "The Crusades did not achieve their original goals, but they brought about many desirable changes in Europe.",
      "Although the Crusaders captured the Holy Land, they were unable to bring about democratic reforms.",
      "The Crusades helped bring about the fall of the Roman Empire",
      "The Crusaders prevented the Turks from capturing Constantinople for many centuries"
    ],
    "answer": "The Crusades did not achieve their original goals, but they brought about many desirable changes in Europe."
  },
  {
    "id": 250,
    "question": "The Roman Catholic Church during the Middle Ages in Europe can best be described as a church that",
    "option": [
      "favored separation from secular governments",
      "avoided involvement in social and educational matters",
      "was a strong force that divided many people",
      "was a stabilizing influence during a period of weak central governments"
    ],
    "answer": "was a stabilizing influence during a period of weak central governments"
  },
  {
    "id": 251,
    "question": "A major goal of the Christian Church during the Crusades (1096 1291) was to",
    "option": [
      "establish Christianity in western Europe",
      "capture the Holy Land from Islamic rulers",
      "unite warring Arab peoples",
      "strengthen English dominance in the Arab world"
    ],
    "answer": "capture the Holy Land from Islamic rulers"
  },
  {
    "id": 252,
    "question": "Korea greatly influenced the development of early Japan by",
    "option": [
      "acting as a bridge for ideas from China",
      "providing Japan with the technology for industrialization",
      "serving as a barrier against Chinese aggression",
      "protecting Japan from early European exploration"
    ],
    "answer": "acting as a bridge for ideas from China"
  },
  {
    "id": 253,
    "question": "In Japan between 1603 and 1868, the most notable action taken by the Tokugawa Shogunate was the",
    "option": [
      "military conquest of China",
      "development of extensive trade with the Americas",
      "formation of cultural links with Europe",
      "virtual isolation of the country from the outside world"
    ],
    "answer": "virtual isolation of the country from the outside world"
  },
  {
    "id": 254,
    "question": "The code of bushido of the Japanese samurai is most similar to",
    "option": [
      "belief in reincarnation and karma of Hindus",
      "practice of chivalry by European knights",
      "teachings of Judaism",
      "theory of natural rights of the Enlightenment writers"
    ],
    "answer": "practice of chivalry by European knights"
  },
  {
    "id": 255,
    "question": "Feudal societies are generally characterized by",
    "option": [
      "an emphasis on social order",
      "a representative government",
      "many economic opportunities",
      "the protection of political rights"
    ],
    "answer": "an emphasis on social order"
  },
  {
    "id": 256,
    "question": "Feudalism in Western Europe was similar to feudalism in Japan in that",
    "option": [
      "power was based on class relationships",
      "equality among the social classes",
      "direct democracy",
      "monotheism"
    ],
    "answer": "power was based on class relationships"
  },
  {
    "id": 257,
    "question": "Which is a characteristic of a feudal society?",
    "option": [
      "rapid social change",
      "high literacy rate",
      "industrial-based economy",
      "rigid class structure"
    ],
    "answer": "rigid class structure"
  },
  {
    "id": 258,
    "question": "The diagram illustrates the social structure of feudal Japan.",
    "option": [
      "a classless society",
      "a growing middle class",
      "high social mobility",
      "a well-defined class system"
    ],
    "answer": "a well-defined class system"
  },
  {
    "id": 259,
    "question": "A valid generalization about early Japanese culture is that Japan",
    "option": [
      "had a strong influence on the development of culture in Korea",
      "spread Shinto throughout Asia",
      "maintained a uniquely individual culture while borrowing much from other cultures",
      "imported almost all of its cultural ideas from China, resulting in nearly identical cultures"
    ],
    "answer": "maintained a uniquely individual culture while borrowing much from other cultures"
  },
  {
    "id": 260,
    "question": "The Mongols played a significant role in Russian history by",
    "option": [
      "supporting Czar Nicholas II during the Russian Revolution",
      "supporting the rule of Ivan the Terrible",
      "ending the reign of Catherine the Great",
      "isolating Russia from Western Europe during the early Renaissance"
    ],
    "answer": "isolating Russia from Western Europe during the early Renaissance"
  },
  {
    "id": 261,
    "question": "In Europe, a major characteristic of humanism was",
    "option": [
      "a belief in the supremacy of the state in relation to individual rights",
      "a rejection of ancient civilizations and their cultures",
      "an emphasis on social control and obedience to national rulers",
      "an appreciation for the basic worth of individual achievement"
    ],
    "answer": "an appreciation for the basic worth of individual achievement"
  },
  {
    "id": 262,
    "question": "Which statement best describes a characteristic of the Renaissance in Europe?",
    "option": [
      "the social structure became very rigid",
      "creativity in the arts was encouraged",
      "the political structure was similar to that of the Roman Empire",
      "humanism decreased in importance"
    ],
    "answer": "creativity in the arts was encouraged"
  },
  {
    "id": 263,
    "question": "Europe is waking out of a long, deep sleep time was when learning was only found in the religious orders learning has passed to secular princes and peers.",
    "option": [
      "Renaissance",
      "decline of the Roman Empire",
      "Crusades",
      "rise of Christianity"
    ],
    "answer": "Renaissance"
  },
  {
    "id": 264,
    "question": "Which was a major characteristic of the Renaissance?",
    "option": ["conformity", "humanism", "mysticism", "obedience"],
    "answer": "humanism"
  },
  {
    "id": 265,
    "question": "Which statement describes a direct effect of the Renaissance on Western Europe?",
    "option": [
      "the philosophy of humanism brought about a decrease in the power of the Roman Catholic Church",
      "art began to reflect an increased emphasis on religious themes",
      "nationalistic movements among the minority ethnic groups in the region declines",
      "the feudal system was developed to provide stability in a decentralized political structure"
    ],
    "answer": "the philosophy of humanism brought about a decrease in the power of the Roman Catholic Church"
  },
  {
    "id": 266,
    "question": "The Renaissance and the Protestant Reformation were similar in that both were",
    "option": [
      "stimulated by a spirit of inquiry",
      "supported by the working class",
      "limited to Italy, France, and Germany",
      "encouraged by the successes of the French Revolution"
    ],
    "answer": "stimulated by a spirit of inquiry"
  },
  {
    "id": 267,
    "question": "Which statement best describes a change that occurred during both the Renaissance and the Enlightenment?",
    "option": [
      "feudalism became the dominant political system",
      "the use of reason and logic were discouraged",
      "technology and science were considered unimportant",
      "a new questioning spirit and attitude emerged"
    ],
    "answer": "a new questioning spirit and attitude emerged"
  },
  {
    "id": 268,
    "question": "One factor that enabled the Renaissance to flourish in Northern Italy was that the region had",
    "option": [
      "a wealthy class that invested in the arts",
      "a socialist for of government",
      "limited contact with the Byzantine Empire",
      "a shrinking middle class"
    ],
    "answer": "a wealthy class that invested in the arts"
  },
  {
    "id": 269,
    "question": "European society during the Renaissance differed from European society during the Middle Ages in that during the Renaissance",
    "option": [
      "the Church was no longer influential",
      "the emphasis on individual worth increased",
      "economic activity declined",
      "art no longer contained religious themes"
    ],
    "answer": "the emphasis on individual worth increased"
  },
  {
    "id": 270,
    "question": "Which societal condition was basic to the development of Greek philosophy and Renaissance art?",
    "option": [
      "rigid social classes",
      "emphasis on individualism",
      "religious uniformity",
      "mass education"
    ],
    "answer": "emphasis on individualism"
  },
  {
    "id": 271,
    "question": "The humanists of the Renaissance differed from the traditional medieval philosophers in the humanists",
    "option": [
      "interest in the spiritual life of people",
      "lack of interest in Ancient Greek and Roman culture",
      "rejection of Christian principles",
      "emphasis on the importance of the individual"
    ],
    "answer": "emphasis on the importance of the individual"
  },
  {
    "id": 272,
    "question": "Which characteristic was common to the Golden Age of Greece and the Italian Renaissance?",
    "option": [
      "a strong military led to national unity",
      "written constitutions led to the establishment of democratic governments",
      "prosperity led to the creation of many works of art",
      "political instability led directly to the formation of unified nation-states"
    ],
    "answer": "prosperity led to the creation of many works of art"
  },
  {
    "id": 273,
    "question": "Which idea about leadership would Niccolo Machiavelli most likely support?",
    "option": [
      "leaders should do whatever is necessary to achieve their goals",
      "leaders should fight against discrimination and intolerance",
      "leaders should listen to the desires of the people",
      "elected leaders should be fair and good"
    ],
    "answer": "leaders should do whatever is necessary to achieve their goals"
  },
  {
    "id": 274,
    "question": "In the Renaissance period, which factor was emphasized by the philosophy of humanism?",
    "option": [
      "superiority of medieval thought",
      "devotion to religion",
      "value of the individual",
      "obedience to government officials"
    ],
    "answer": "value of the individual"
  },
  {
    "id": 275,
    "question": "Which statement concerning the Renaissance in Europe is based on opinion rather than on fact?",
    "option": [
      "Literature began to appear in languages other than Latin.",
      "The art of the Northern Renaissance was superior to that of the Italian Renaissance.",
      "Art reflected the ideas of humanism and individualism.",
      "Art produced during the Renaissance had religious as well as secular themes."
    ],
    "answer": "The art of the Northern Renaissance was superior to that of the Italian Renaissance."
  },
  {
    "id": 276,
    "question": "Martin Luther s Ninety-Five Theses were a call for",
    "option": [
      "religious revolt against the German princes",
      "reforms within the Roman Catholic Church",
      "greater papal authority",
      "crusades to spread Christianity"
    ],
    "answer": "reforms within the Roman Catholic Church"
  },
  {
    "id": 277,
    "question": "In Western Europe, a major immediate effect of the Reformation was a",
    "option": [
      "renewed domination of the Catholic Church over the German states",
      "greater tolerance of religions other than Christianity",
      "decrease in educational opportunities for the middle class",
      "decline in religious unity and in the power of the Catholic Church"
    ],
    "answer": "decline in religious unity and in the power of the Catholic Church"
  },
  {
    "id": 278,
    "question": "During the Renaissance, which development contributed most to the Protestant Reformation?",
    "option": [
      "interest in Ancient Greece and Rome",
      "advances in mathematics and science",
      "questioning of traditional authority",
      "attention to realism and detail"
    ],
    "answer": "questioning of traditional authority"
  },
  {
    "id": 279,
    "question": "Which was a result of the Protestant Reformation in Europe?",
    "option": [
      "the Catholic Church accepted the dominance of the new Protestant religions in Italy, France, and Germany",
      "Spain became a predominately Protestant nation",
      "Catholic Church leaders refused to make any changes in church practices",
      "the power of the Catholic Church in Europe was weakened"
    ],
    "answer": "the power of the Catholic Church in Europe was weakened"
  },
  {
    "id": 280,
    "question": "Which was a major result of the Reformation?",
    "option": [
      "new Christian denominations emerged",
      "religious teachings were no longer allowed in the universities",
      "the Crusades were organized",
      "the power of the Pope was strengthened"
    ],
    "answer": "new Christian denominations emerged"
  },
  {
    "id": 281,
    "question": "Which factor helped most to bring about the Protestant Reformation?",
    "option": [
      "the Catholic clergy had lost faith in their religion",
      "Islam was attracting many converts in Western Europe",
      "kings and princes in Northern Europe resented the power of the Catholic Church",
      "the exploration of the Americas led to the introduction of new religious ideas"
    ],
    "answer": "kings and princes in Northern Europe resented the power of the Catholic Church"
  },
  {
    "id": 282,
    "question": "The Protestant Reformation and the European Renaissance were similar in that both",
    "option": [
      "discouraged the growth of strong monarchs",
      "encouraged people to question tradition",
      "were led by the military",
      "supported the return of the Roman Empire"
    ],
    "answer": "encouraged people to question tradition"
  },
  {
    "id": 283,
    "question": "The Protestant Reformation represents a turning point in European history because it",
    "option": [
      "allowed religious reformers to escape persecution",
      "standardized all religious writings",
      "ended religious unity in Western Europe",
      "forced most of Europe s monarchs to become Protestants"
    ],
    "answer": "ended religious unity in Western Europe"
  },
  {
    "id": 284,
    "question": "Christians should be taught that he who gives to a poor man or lends to a needy man does better than if he used the money to buy an indulgence.",
    "option": [
      "Commercial Revolution",
      "Industrial Revolution",
      "Renaissance",
      "Protestant Reformation"
    ],
    "answer": "Protestant Reformation"
  },
  {
    "id": 285,
    "question": "The Renaissance and the Protestant Reformation were similar in that both were",
    "option": [
      "stimulated by a spirit of inquiry",
      "supported by the working class",
      "limited to Italy, France, and Germany",
      "encouraged by the successes of the French Revolution"
    ],
    "answer": "stimulated by a spirit of inquiry"
  },
  {
    "id": 286,
    "question": "One major influence the Renaissance had on the Protestant Reformation was that the philosophers of the Renaissance",
    "option": [
      "supported democratic forms of government",
      "encouraged a questioning attitude",
      "stressed the importance of life after death",
      "denied the existence of God"
    ],
    "answer": "encouraged a questioning attitude"
  },
  {
    "id": 287,
    "question": "Unless I am convinced by Scripture and plain reason... my conscience is captive to the Word of God. I cannot and I will hot recant anything, for to go against conscience is neither right nor safe. Here I stand, I cannot do otherwise.    Martin Luther, Diet of Worms (1517)",
    "option": [
      "the supremacy of the Bible over Church policies",
      "imprisoning those who disagreed with Church teachings",
      "maintaining the unity of the Church",
      "the need for nepotism"
    ],
    "answer": "the supremacy of the Bible over Church policies"
  },
  {
    "id": 288,
    "question": "Martin Luther s posting of the Ninety-Five Theses is considered by many to be a turning point in history because",
    "option": [
      "the Pope s right to sell indulgences was strengthened",
      "Luther soon became the leader of Germany",
      "the power of the Roman Catholic Church was lessened and royal power grew",
      "the Roman Catholic Church unified the German states"
    ],
    "answer": "the power of the Roman Catholic Church was lessened and royal power grew"
  },
  {
    "id": 289,
    "question": "In Spain, an effect of the Inquisition during the 16th century was to",
    "option": [
      "prevent the introduction of Protestant religions",
      "reintroduce Moorish culture to the Iberian Peninsula",
      "encourage the development of the Industrial Revolution",
      "implement the ideas of the Renaissance in major cities"
    ],
    "answer": "prevent the introduction of Protestant religions"
  },
  {
    "id": 290,
    "question": "In Latin America, the Maya and the Aztec civilizations were similar in that they",
    "option": [
      "showed little evidence of urbanization",
      "lacked a strong central government",
      "developed complex mathematical and calendar systems",
      "used military weapons superior to those of Europeans"
    ],
    "answer": "developed complex mathematical and calendar systems"
  },
  {
    "id": 291,
    "question": "A study of Mayas, Aztecs, and Incas would show that these ancient American civilizations",
    "option": [
      "produced few cultural achievements",
      "lived at peace with their neighbors",
      "welcomed the new technology brought by European explorers",
      "rivaled the accomplishments of early Middle Eastern cultures"
    ],
    "answer": "rivaled the accomplishments of early Middle Eastern cultures"
  },
  {
    "id": 292,
    "question": "A study of the Maya, Aztec, and Inca civilizations of Latin America would show that these civilizations",
    "option": [
      "developed advanced and complex societies before the arrival of the Europeans",
      "established extensive trade with Pacific Rim nations",
      "were strongly influenced by their contact with Asian and African civilizations",
      "were relatively large, but not well organized"
    ],
    "answer": "developed advanced and complex societies before the arrival of the Europeans"
  },
  {
    "id": 293,
    "question": "Which was a result of the Commercial Revolution",
    "option": [
      "decline in population growth in Europe",
      "shift of power from Western Europe to Eastern Europe",
      "spread of feudalism throughout Western Europe",
      "expansion of European influence overseas"
    ],
    "answer": "expansion of European influence overseas"
  },
  {
    "id": 294,
    "question": "Which was an immediate result of the European Age of Exploration?",
    "option": [
      "Islamic culture spread across Africa and Asia",
      "European influence spread to the Western hemisphere",
      "independence movements developed in Asia and Africa",
      "military dictatorships were established throughout Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "European influence spread to the Western hemisphere"
  },
  {
    "id": 295,
    "question": "A major result of the Age of Exploration was",
    "option": [
      "a long period of peace and prosperity for the nations of Western Europe",
      "extensive migration of people from the Western Hemisphere to Europe and Asia",
      "the fall of European national monarchies and the end of the power of the Catholic Church",
      "the end of regional isolation and the beginning of a period of European global domination"
    ],
    "answer": "the end of regional isolation and the beginning of a period of European global domination"
  },
  {
    "id": 296,
    "question": "The Commercial Revolution in Western Europe led directly to the",
    "option": [
      "development of a socialist economy",
      "establishment of the Guild System",
      "weakening of the power of the middle class",
      "expansion of world trade"
    ],
    "answer": "expansion of world trade"
  },
  {
    "id": 297,
    "question": "Which system developed as a result of the Commercial Revolution",
    "option": ["manorialism", "communism", "bartering", "market economy"],
    "answer": "market economy"
  },
  {
    "id": 298,
    "question": "Which of these events during the Age of Exploration was a cause of the other three?",
    "option": [
      "Europeans brought food, animals, and ideas from one continent to another",
      "European diseases had an adverse effect on the native populations of new territories",
      "warfare increased as European nations competed for land and power",
      "advances in learning and technology made long ocean voyages possible"
    ],
    "answer": "advances in learning and technology made long ocean voyages possible"
  },
  {
    "id": 299,
    "question": "The Native American population of Mexico in 1492 has been estimated at 25 million; the population in 1608 has been estimated at 1.7 million.  This decrease in population was mainly a result of",
    "option": [
      "crop failures brought on by poor weather conditions",
      "emigration of Native Americans to Europe and Africa",
      "wars between various native groups",
      "diseases introduced by the Spanish"
    ],
    "answer": "diseases introduced by the Spanish"
  },
  {
    "id": 300,
    "question": "In Latin America during the early period of Spanish colonialism, the deaths of large numbers of the native people led to",
    "option": [
      "a decline in Spanish immigration to the Americas",
      "the removal of most Spanish troops from the Americas",
      "the importation of slaves from Africa",
      "improved health care in the colonies"
    ],
    "answer": "the importation of slaves from Africa"
  },
  {
    "id": 301,
    "question": "Both Japan and China decided to limit trade with Europe during much of the 16th and 17th centuries because the Japanese and the Chinese",
    "option": [
      "had few products to sell to the Europeans",
      "held religious beliefs that prohibited contact with foreigners",
      "thought European technology would hinder any effort to modernize",
      "believed they would receive no benefit from increased contact with the Europeans"
    ],
    "answer": "believed they would receive no benefit from increased contact with the Europeans"
  },
  {
    "id": 302,
    "question": "One reason the Spanish conquistadors were able to conquer the Aztec and Inca Empires rapid is that",
    "option": [
      "these empires had no standing armies",
      "the Spanish had better weapons than the Aztecs and Incas did",
      "the Spanish greatly outnumbered the Aztecs and Incas",
      "the Aztecs and Incas joined together to fight the Spanish"
    ],
    "answer": "the Spanish had better weapons than the Aztecs and Incas did"
  },
  {
    "id": 303,
    "question": "Which conclusion can be drawn from a study of the early civilizations of Axum, Kush, Mali and Songhai?",
    "option": [
      "these African societies flourished at the same time",
      "farming was more extensive in the Nile River Valley than it was in the Fertile Crescent",
      "the Neolithic Revolution occurred in Africa",
      "these societies had a long and rich history before their first contact with Europeans"
    ],
    "answer": "these societies had a long and rich history before their first contact with Europeans"
  },
  {
    "id": 304,
    "question": "Which was a characteristic of the policy of mercantilism followed by Spanish colonial rulers in Latin America?",
    "option": [
      "the colonies were forced to develop local industries to support themselves",
      "Spain sought trade agreements between its colonies and the English colonies in North America",
      "the colonies were required to provide raw materials to Spain and to purchase Spanish manufactured goods",
      "Spain encouraged the colonies to develop new political systems to meet colonial needs"
    ],
    "answer": "the colonies were required to provide raw materials to Spain and to purchase Spanish manufactured goods"
  },
  {
    "id": 305,
    "question": "Which statement best describes a result of the scarcity of native Indian labor in Latin America during the colonial period?",
    "option": [
      "unskilled laborers were imported from Asia",
      "many people from Spain and Portugal immigrated to the region",
      "Native American Indians from the British colonies went south to work",
      "large numbers of African slaves were imported"
    ],
    "answer": "large numbers of African slaves were imported"
  },
  {
    "id": 306,
    "question": "The influence of African culture on some areas of Latin America was largely a result of the",
    "option": [
      "American Revolution",
      "building of the Panama Canal",
      "success of Communist Revolutions",
      "Atlantic slave trade"
    ],
    "answer": "Atlantic slave trade"
  },
  {
    "id": 307,
    "question": "In many Latin American nations, a major effect of colonial rule has been the",
    "option": [
      "concentration of power in a small group of landowners",
      "minor political role of the military",
      "equal distribution of wealth among social classes",
      "economic control held by the Indian population"
    ],
    "answer": "concentration of power in a small group of landowners"
  },
  {
    "id": 308,
    "question": "Spain s colonial policy of mercantilism affected the development of Latin American nations by promoting",
    "option": [
      "the production of raw material and cash crops",
      "free and rapid trade with Asia and Africa",
      "respect for the rights of indigenous people",
      "isolationism as a response to international political issues"
    ],
    "answer": "the production of raw material and cash crops"
  },
  {
    "id": 309,
    "question": "One result of the European conquest of Latin America was that in Latin America",
    "option": [
      "Spanish became the major spoken language",
      "Native American cultures flourished",
      "the Aztec religion spread",
      "many parliamentary democracies were established"
    ],
    "answer": "Spanish became the major spoken language"
  },
  {
    "id": 310,
    "question": "In colonial Latin America, the main purpose of the encomienda system was to",
    "option": [
      "insure that the Indians were humanely treated",
      "provide a steady labor supply for early colonists",
      "prevent slaver in Spain s New World colonies",
      "build and maintain forts to repel foreign invaders"
    ],
    "answer": "provide a steady labor supply for early colonists"
  },
  {
    "id": 311,
    "question": "According to the theory of mercantilism, colonies should be",
    "option": [
      "acquired as markets and sources of raw materials",
      "considered an economic burden for the colonial power",
      "grated independence as soon as possible",
      "encouraged to develop their own industries"
    ],
    "answer": "acquired as markets and sources of raw materials"
  },
  {
    "id": 312,
    "question": "He once sent fifty horsemen with pikes (spears) to destroy an entire province.  Not a single human being survived that massacre, neither women nor children nor aged infirm This terrible massacre was punishment for a trifling offense: some Indians had not responded to a summons promptly enough when the tyrant had commanded that they bring him a load of maize (corn) , or else had asked for more Indians to be assigned to serve him or his comrades.  And there was no place where the Indians could take refuge",
    "option": [
      "encourage the colonial government to change its policies toward native peoples",
      "explain the problems associated with using native laborers",
      "justify the need for the harsh treatment of the native people",
      "show support for the governor s policy toward native peoples"
    ],
    "answer": "encourage the colonial government to change its policies toward native peoples"
  },
  {
    "id": 313,
    "question": "The Treaty of Tordesillas (1494), concerning Latin America, and the Berlin Conference (1884-1885), concerning Africa, were similar in that each agreement",
    "option": [
      "provided for self-government by the native peoples",
      "declared that in these areas monarchs rule by divine right",
      "divided each area into European-controlled segments",
      "suppressed revolts by native peoples against European imperialists"
    ],
    "answer": "divided each area into European-controlled segments"
  },
  {
    "id": 314,
    "question": "Which statement best illustrates the contradictory actions of the Catholic Church in colonial Latin America?",
    "option": [
      "the Jesuits destroyed the temples of the Native Americans, but allowed them to continue their religious rituals",
      "the Church expressed concern over the mistreatment of Native Americans, but supported the encomienda system",
      "the Church moved many Native Americas from Spanish territory to Portuguese territory, but encouraged the importation of African slaves",
      "the Pope endorsed the Treaty of Tordesillas, but outlawed further exploration"
    ],
    "answer": "the Church expressed concern over the mistreatment of Native Americans, but supported the encomienda system"
  },
  {
    "id": 315,
    "question": "The Crusades indirectly contributed to the discovery of the New World by",
    "option": [
      "forcing the religious conversion of the Muslim population",
      "forcing the Turks to flee from Constantinople",
      "stimulating European demand for goods from the East",
      "increasing the power of the feudal lords"
    ],
    "answer": "stimulating European demand for goods from the East"
  },
  {
    "id": 316,
    "question": "In the 1600 s, the interest of Europeans in Africa was based mainly on Europe s need to",
    "option": [
      "market its surplus agricultural products",
      "obtain workers for its colonies in the Americas",
      "establish collective security arrangements",
      "settle its surplus population on new lands"
    ],
    "answer": "obtain workers for its colonies in the Americas"
  },
  {
    "id": 317,
    "question": "The printing press, the astrolabe, and the Mercator projection were technological advances that contributed to the",
    "option": [
      "exploration and overseas expansion of the colonial empires",
      "unification of Germany and Italy in the late 1800 s",
      "growth of industry in Latin America during the late 1900 s",
      "spread of Islam in the 700 s and 800 s"
    ],
    "answer": "exploration and overseas expansion of the colonial empires"
  },
  {
    "id": 318,
    "question": "Peter the Great and Catherine the Great changed Russia by",
    "option": [
      "abolishing all social class distinctions",
      "becoming constitutional monarchs",
      "preventing wars with neighboring nations",
      "introducing western ideas and customs"
    ],
    "answer": "introducing western ideas and customs"
  },
  {
    "id": 319,
    "question": "Changes in Russia under Peter the Great were most similar to changes that occurred in",
    "option": [
      "China before the Opium War",
      "Japan during the Meiji Restoration",
      "Iran after the fall of Shah Pahlevi",
      "France during the feudal period"
    ],
    "answer": "Japan during the Meiji Restoration"
  },
  {
    "id": 320,
    "question": "Westernization in Russia came about largely through the",
    "option": [
      "efforts of Peter the Great and his successors",
      "invasion of Russia by Sweden",
      "desire of the United States to seek new markets",
      "acceptance of the policies of the Eastern Orthodox Church"
    ],
    "answer": "efforts of Peter the Great and his successors"
  },
  {
    "id": 321,
    "question": "God hath power to create or destroy, make or unmake, at his pleasure; to give life or send death; to judge and to be judged (by) none And the like power have kings;",
    "option": [
      "theory of divine right",
      "enlightened despotism",
      "Social Darwinism",
      "constitutional monarchy"
    ],
    "answer": "theory of divine right"
  },
  {
    "id": 322,
    "question": "Which type of government is shown in the cartoon?",
    "option": [
      "a socialist republic",
      "an absolute monarchy",
      "a communist dictatorship",
      "a democracy"
    ],
    "answer": "an absolute monarchy"
  },
  {
    "id": 323,
    "question": ". . .The person of the King is sacred, and to attack him in any way is an attack on religion itself. Kings represent the divine majesty and have been appointed by Him to carry out His purposes. Serving God and respecting kings are bound together.    Bishop Jacques Bossuet",
    "option": [
      "existed during the",
      "Age of Absolutism",
      "Renaissance",
      "Industrial Revolution"
    ],
    "answer": "Age of Absolutism"
  },
  {
    "id": 324,
    "question": ". . .The person of the King is sacred, and to attack him in any way is an attack on religion itself. Kings represent the divine majesty and have been appointed by Him to carry out His purposes. Serving God and respecting kings are bound together.    Bishop Jacques Bossuet",
    "option": ["John Locke", "Karl Marx", "Elizabeth II", "Louis XIV"],
    "answer": "Louis XIV"
  },
  {
    "id": 325,
    "question": "Francis Bacon, Galileo, and Isaac Newton promoted the idea that knowledge should be based on",
    "option": [
      "the experiences of past civilizations",
      "experimentation and observation",
      "emotions and feelings",
      "the teachings of the Catholic Church"
    ],
    "answer": "experimentation and observation"
  },
  {
    "id": 326,
    "question": "During the Scientific Revolution and the Enlightenment, one similarity in the work of many scientists and philosophers was that they",
    "option": [
      "relied heavily on the ideas of medieval thinkers",
      "favored an absolute monarchy as a way of improving economic conditions",
      "received support from the Catholic Church",
      "examined natural laws governing the universe"
    ],
    "answer": "examined natural laws governing the universe"
  },
  {
    "id": 327,
    "question": "Which statement best describes the effects of the works of Nicolaus Copernicus, Galileo Galilei, Sir",
    "option": [
      "The acceptance of traditional authority was strengthened.",
      "The scientific method was used to solve problems.",
      "Funding to education was increased by the English government.",
      "Interest in Greek and Roman drama was renewed."
    ],
    "answer": "The scientific method was used to solve problems."
  },
  {
    "id": 328,
    "question": "Speaker A  : Good government stresses the importance of the nation and accepts the rights of the individual only if the interests of the individual are the same as those of the nation.",
    "option": ["A", "B", "C", "D"],
    "answer": "C"
  },
  {
    "id": 329,
    "question": "Speaker A  :  The story of history is the story of class struggles.  Revolution is necessary to overthrow the ruling class and eventually create a classless society in which no one will be exploited.",
    "option": ["A", "B", "C", "D"],
    "answer": "D"
  },
  {
    "id": 330,
    "question": "One important result of the French Revolution was that",
    "option": [
      "France enjoyed a lengthy period of peace and prosperity",
      "the church was restored to its former role and power in the French government",
      "political power shifted to the bourgeoisie",
      "France lost its spirit of nationalism"
    ],
    "answer": "political power shifted to the bourgeoisie"
  },
  {
    "id": 331,
    "question": "Which statement is a valid generalization about the immediate results of the French Revolution of 1789?",
    "option": [
      "the Roman Catholic Church increased its power and wealth",
      "the revolution achieved its goal of establishing peace, democracy, and justice for all",
      "the revolution had little impact outside France",
      "the French middle class gained more power"
    ],
    "answer": "the French middle class gained more power"
  },
  {
    "id": 332,
    "question": "In France, which was a major result of the French Revolution?",
    "option": [
      "the king was restored to unlimited power",
      "the clergy dominated government",
      "the middle class gained political influence",
      "the tax burden was carried by the lower class"
    ],
    "answer": "the middle class gained political influence"
  },
  {
    "id": 333,
    "question": "A study of revolutions would most likely lead to the conclusion that pre-Revolutionary governments",
    "option": [
      "are more concerned about human rights than the governments that replace them",
      "refuse to modernize their armed forces with advanced technology",
      "attempt to bring about the separation of government from religion",
      "fail to meet the political and economic needs of their people"
    ],
    "answer": "fail to meet the political and economic needs of their people"
  },
  {
    "id": 334,
    "question": "Congress of Vienna Restores Monarchy to France    Czar Nicholas I Limits Freedom of the Russian Press",
    "option": [
      "reactions to the French Revolution",
      "movements to unify all of western Europe",
      "efforts to improve the conditions of factory workers",
      "attempts to promote trade between European nations"
    ],
    "answer": "reactions to the French Revolution"
  },
  {
    "id": 335,
    "question": "The French people supported Napoleon Bonaparte because they hoped he would",
    "option": [
      "adopt the ideas of the Protestant Reformation",
      "restore Louis XVI to power",
      "provide stability for the nation",
      "end British control of France"
    ],
    "answer": "provide stability for the nation"
  },
  {
    "id": 336,
    "question": "Simon Bolivar and Miguel Hidalgo, leaders of Latin American independence movements, were inspired by successful revolutions in",
    "option": [
      "the Untied States and France",
      "the Soviet Union and China",
      "Cuba and Costa Rica",
      "Egypt and Kenya"
    ],
    "answer": "the Untied States and France"
  },
  {
    "id": 337,
    "question": "During the early 1800 s, which was a major influence on the struggle for political independence in Latin America?",
    "option": [
      "poor conditions in urban centers in Latin America",
      "the American and French Revolutions",
      "the desire of the Roman Catholic Church in Latin America to escape European control",
      "demands by Latin American workers to own their own factories"
    ],
    "answer": "the American and French Revolutions"
  },
  {
    "id": 338,
    "question": "One similarity in the leadership of Latin Americas Jose de San Martin, Toussaint l Ouverture, Bernanrdo O Higgins, and Pedro I was that each leader",
    "option": [
      "opposed United States intervention in Haiti",
      "led a struggle to gain freedom for the people of his nation",
      "opposed membership of his nation in the League of Nations",
      "established an absolute monarchy in his nation"
    ],
    "answer": "led a struggle to gain freedom for the people of his nation"
  },
  {
    "id": 339,
    "question": "I will never allow my hands to be idle nor my soul to rest until I have broken the chains laid upon us by Spain.",
    "option": [
      "a Latin American nationalist",
      "a Portuguese explorer",
      "a Roman Catholic bishop",
      "a Spanish conquistador"
    ],
    "answer": "a Latin American nationalist"
  },
  {
    "id": 340,
    "question": "Which of these situations was the direct result of the other three?",
    "option": [
      "nations of Latin America won independence",
      "revolutions occurred in North America and France",
      "the Napoleonic wars weakened Spain s power",
      "creoles and mestizos became discontented with Spanish rule"
    ],
    "answer": "nations of Latin America won independence"
  },
  {
    "id": 341,
    "question": "The 19th-century independence movements in Latin America were influenced by",
    "option": [
      "Marxist ideology",
      "the Aztec wars against Hernando Cortez",
      "liberation theology",
      "the American and the French Revolutions"
    ],
    "answer": "the American and the French Revolutions"
  },
  {
    "id": 342,
    "question": "Simon Bolivar, Toussaint L Overture, and Bernardo O Higgins were Latin American leaders of",
    "option": [
      "economic development",
      "educational reforms",
      "independence movements",
      "colonial expansion"
    ],
    "answer": "independence movements"
  },
  {
    "id": 343,
    "question": "In which region of the world did the American Revolution and the French Revolution have the greatest influence during the 1800 s?",
    "option": [
      "Southeast Asia",
      "Latin America",
      "South Asia",
      "sub-Saharan Africa"
    ],
    "answer": "Latin America"
  },
  {
    "id": 344,
    "question": "Sim n Bol var, Jos  de San Mart n, and Toussaint l Ouverture are important in Latin American history because they were",
    "option": [
      "20th-century caudillos",
      "leaders of liberation movements",
      "members of the Organization of American States (OAS)",
      "winners of the Nobel Peace Prize"
    ],
    "answer": "leaders of liberation movements"
  },
  {
    "id": 345,
    "question": "A country is not merely a geographic territory.  A country is also the idea given birth by the geographic territory.  A country is a sense of love that unites, as one, all the sons and daughters of that geographic territory",
    "option": [
      "totalitarian rule",
      "absolute monarchy",
      "mercantilism",
      "nationalism"
    ],
    "answer": "nationalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 346,
    "question": "In a number of European countries in the 1800 s, which situation occurred as a result of the influence of the French Revolution?",
    "option": [
      "increase in religious conflict",
      "rise of nationalistic movements",
      "decentralization of governmental power",
      "economic depression"
    ],
    "answer": "rise of nationalistic movements"
  },
  {
    "id": 347,
    "question": "Which quotation best reflects a feeling of nationalism?",
    "option": [
      " An eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth",
      " A person s greatest social obligation is loyalty to the family",
      " For God, King, and Country",
      " Opposition to evil is as much a duty as is cooperation with good"
    ],
    "answer": " For God, King, and Country"
  },
  {
    "id": 348,
    "question": "Nationalism is most likely to develop in an area that has",
    "option": [
      "land suited to agriculture",
      "adequate industry to supply consumer demands",
      "a moderate climate with rivers for irrigation",
      "common customs, language, and history"
    ],
    "answer": "common customs, language, and history"
  },
  {
    "id": 349,
    "question": "Nationalism is best defined as",
    "option": [
      "the achievement of world peace and global understanding",
      "the desire to take over other societies by force",
      "a method of solving basic economic problems of the society",
      "the loyalty of a people to their values, traditions, and a geographic region"
    ],
    "answer": "the loyalty of a people to their values, traditions, and a geographic region"
  },
  {
    "id": 350,
    "question": "The best example of the success of nationalism in Europe is the",
    "option": [
      "development of socialism in France",
      "Industrial Revolution in Great Britain",
      "establishment of the Common Market",
      "unification of Germany"
    ],
    "answer": "unification of Germany"
  },
  {
    "id": 351,
    "question": "Which condition is most necessary to the process of industrialization in a society?",
    "option": [
      "dependence on subsistence agriculture",
      "creation of a one-crop economy",
      "availability of investment capital",
      "capture of foreign lands"
    ],
    "answer": "availability of investment capital"
  },
  {
    "id": 352,
    "question": "According to Karl Marx, history is the record of the",
    "option": [
      "granting of more political liberties to all people",
      "struggle between classes in society",
      "wars and conflicts between national leaders",
      "increasing prosperity brought about by industrialization"
    ],
    "answer": "struggle between classes in society"
  },
  {
    "id": 353,
    "question": "A main idea of Karl Marx and Friedrich Engles  Communist Manifesto is that the proletariat",
    "option": [
      "would need foreign help to achieve its revolutionary ends",
      "had to cooperate with the capitalists to gain economic rewards",
      "should allow the capitalists to control the means of production",
      "must unite to overthrow the capitalist class"
    ],
    "answer": "must unite to overthrow the capitalist class"
  },
  {
    "id": 354,
    "question": "Revolution will occur more and more frequently in the industrialized nations as the proletariat struggles to overcome the abuses of the capitalist system.",
    "option": [
      "Charles Darwin",
      "Karl Marx",
      "Niccolo Machiavelli",
      "John Locke"
    ],
    "answer": "Karl Marx"
  },
  {
    "id": 355,
    "question": "The proletarians have nothing to lose but their chains Workers of the world, unite!",
    "option": [
      "Protestant Reformation",
      "Counter-Reformation",
      "Commercial Revolution",
      "Industrial Revolution"
    ],
    "answer": "Industrial Revolution"
  },
  {
    "id": 356,
    "question": "Before a nation can begin to industrialize, that nation must first develop",
    "option": [
      "a democratic government",
      "a rigid class structure",
      "a strong religious foundation",
      "an adequate food supply"
    ],
    "answer": "an adequate food supply"
  },
  {
    "id": 357,
    "question": "A major result of the Industrial Revolution was the",
    "option": [
      "concentration of workers in urban areas",
      "increased desire of the wealthy class to share its power",
      "formation of powerful craft guilds",
      "control of agricultural production by governments"
    ],
    "answer": "concentration of workers in urban areas"
  },
  {
    "id": 358,
    "question": "According to the theories of Karl Marx, history can be viewed as a",
    "option": [
      "succession of famines that result in the destruction of civilizations",
      "repeating cycle of imperialism and colonialism",
      "listing of the accomplishments of the ruling classes",
      "continuous struggle between economic classes"
    ],
    "answer": "continuous struggle between economic classes"
  },
  {
    "id": 359,
    "question": "-Europeans sought new markets for their goods.  -Many Europeans migrated to the cities in search of jobs.",
    "option": [
      "Industrial Revolution",
      "rise of feudalism",
      "Congress of Vienna",
      "French Revolution"
    ],
    "answer": "Industrial Revolution"
  },
  {
    "id": 360,
    "question": "Which revolution inspired Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels to express their ideas in The Communist Manifesto?",
    "option": ["Industrial", "Scientific", "Glorious", "Neolithic"],
    "answer": "Industrial"
  },
  {
    "id": 361,
    "question": "Before Commodore Matthew Perry s expedition to Japan in 1853, Japan was most influenced by",
    "option": [
      "Russia s need for warm water ports",
      "the introduction of advanced technology from the United States",
      "France s quest for new colonies",
      "China s religion, art, and writing"
    ],
    "answer": "China s religion, art, and writing"
  },
  {
    "id": 362,
    "question": "In Japan, the Meiji Restoration resulted in the",
    "option": [
      "division of the nation between the European powers",
      "modernization of the nation s industry",
      "abolition of the position of emperor",
      "government being controlled by the samurai"
    ],
    "answer": "modernization of the nation s industry"
  },
  {
    "id": 363,
    "question": "An immediate result of Commodore Matthew Perry s visit to Japan in 1853 was",
    "option": [
      "an alliance between Japan and Russia",
      "the development of trade between Japan and the West",
      "a war between Japan and the United States",
      "the continued isolation of Japan"
    ],
    "answer": "the development of trade between Japan and the West"
  },
  {
    "id": 364,
    "question": "The arrival of Commodore Matthew Perry in Japan in 1853 signaled the end of Japanese",
    "option": [
      "cultural contacts with the West",
      "policies of isolationism",
      "militarism in Southeast Asia",
      "trade relations with the United States"
    ],
    "answer": "policies of isolationism"
  },
  {
    "id": 365,
    "question": "A major goal of the Meiji government in Japan was to",
    "option": [
      "isolate Japan from other nations",
      "achieve political union with China",
      "establish Japan as an industrial power",
      "encourage colonization of Asia by Western nations"
    ],
    "answer": "establish Japan as an industrial power"
  },
  {
    "id": 366,
    "question": "The modernization of Japan during the Meiji Restoration resulted in",
    "option": [
      "a return to a feudal system of government",
      "the rise of Japan as an imperialistic nation",
      "an alliance between China, Korea, Russia, and Japan",
      "a strengthening of Japan s isolationist policies"
    ],
    "answer": "the rise of Japan as an imperialistic nation"
  },
  {
    "id": 367,
    "question": "Which statement best describes events in Japan during the period of the Meiji Restoration?",
    "option": [
      "Japan sought to isolate itself from world affairs.",
      "Rapid industrialization and economic growth occurred.",
      "Local lords increased their power over the Japanese emperor.",
      "Agriculture was taken over by the government."
    ],
    "answer": "Rapid industrialization and economic growth occurred."
  },
  {
    "id": 368,
    "question": "A primary purpose for building the Suez Canal was to",
    "option": [
      "encourage Jewish settlement in nearby Palestine",
      "increase trade between the Middle East, Europe and Asia",
      "reduce the time needed for travel between the Atlantic Ocean and the Caribbean Sea",
      "allow Indian merchants to reach the east coast of Africa"
    ],
    "answer": "increase trade between the Middle East, Europe and Asia"
  },
  {
    "id": 369,
    "question": "Which is an accurate statement about the partitioning of Africa by European imperialist nations during the 1800 s?",
    "option": [
      "new nations were based on old tribal boundaries",
      "the cultural and ethnic diversity of the African people was disregarded",
      "the continent was divided equally among the colonial powers",
      "African unity was encouraged"
    ],
    "answer": "the cultural and ethnic diversity of the African people was disregarded"
  },
  {
    "id": 370,
    "question": "After 1880, European nations sought colonies in Africa primarily because the Europeans were",
    "option": [
      "in need of land for their surplus populations",
      "competing of raw materials and markets",
      "determined to bring Christianity to the Moslem world",
      "interested in completing their geographic knowledge of the world"
    ],
    "answer": "competing of raw materials and markets"
  },
  {
    "id": 371,
    "question": "The 19th century term  White Man s Burden  reflects the idea that",
    "option": [
      "Asians and Africans were equal to Europeans",
      "Asians and Africans would be grateful for European help",
      "imperialism was opposed by most Europeans",
      "Europeans had a responsibility to improve the lives of the colonial peoples"
    ],
    "answer": "Europeans had a responsibility to improve the lives of the colonial peoples"
  },
  {
    "id": 372,
    "question": "The Sepoy Mutiny in India, the Boxer Rebellion in China, and the Islamic Revolution in Iran were similar in that they",
    "option": [
      "restored power to the hereditary monarchies",
      "attempted to reject the traditional cultures in these countries",
      "resisted foreign influence in these countries",
      "reestablished the power of religious leaders"
    ],
    "answer": "resisted foreign influence in these countries"
  },
  {
    "id": 373,
    "question": "During the 19th century, Europeans were able to divide China in Spheres of Influence mainly because the",
    "option": [
      "Chinese were eager to adopt western culture",
      "Europeans had technologically superior military forces",
      "Europeans were willing to adopt Chinese customs",
      "Chinese lacked raw materials and resources"
    ],
    "answer": "Europeans had technologically superior military forces"
  },
  {
    "id": 374,
    "question": "The Boxer Rebellion of the early 20th century was an attempt to",
    "option": [
      "eliminate poverty among the Chinese peasants",
      "bring western-style democracy to China",
      "restore trade between China and European nations",
      "remove foreign influences from China"
    ],
    "answer": "remove foreign influences from China"
  },
  {
    "id": 375,
    "question": "Yesterday, your ambassador petitioned my ministers regarding your trade with China our Celestial Empire possesses all things in great abundance and lacks no product within its own borders.  There is, therefore, no need to import any product manufactured by outside barbarians in exchange for our own goods.",
    "option": [
      "maintaining economic isolation",
      "expanding foreign trade",
      "increasing international interdependence",
      "developing into a colonial power"
    ],
    "answer": "maintaining economic isolation"
  },
  {
    "id": 376,
    "question": "British control over South Africa, French control over Indochina, and Spanish control over Mexico are examples of",
    "option": ["isolationism", "appeasement", "nonalignment", "imperialism"],
    "answer": "imperialism"
  },
  {
    "id": 377,
    "question": "In the past, European nations have conquered other lands, made them into colonies, and controlled their economies.",
    "option": ["socialism", "isolationism", "imperialism", "monotheism"],
    "answer": "imperialism"
  },
  {
    "id": 378,
    "question": "In the past, European nations have conquered other lands, made them into colonies, and controlled their economies.",
    "option": [
      "industrialization of Europe and the need for raw materials",
      "desire of Europeans to spread communism throughout the world",
      "European belief in human rights for all people",
      "requests of developing nations for modern machines and technology"
    ],
    "answer": "industrialization of Europe and the need for raw materials"
  },
  {
    "id": 379,
    "question": "During the 1840 s, China signed  unequal treaties  with Western nations mainly because",
    "option": [
      "China had won the Opium War",
      "Western nations had superior military technology",
      "leaders in China favored expansion",
      "China had requested economic assistance from the West"
    ],
    "answer": "Western nations had superior military technology"
  },
  {
    "id": 380,
    "question": "Throughout the 1800 s, an increased need for both raw materials and new markets for manufactured goods led various European nations to pursue policies of",
    "option": ["imperialism", "socialism", "isolationism", "communism"],
    "answer": "imperialism"
  },
  {
    "id": 381,
    "question": "During the 18th and 19th centuries, increased contact between European and the continents of Africa, Asia, and South America resulted in",
    "option": [
      "closer cultural cooperation between Europe and these continents",
      "the exploitation of the labor and resources of these continents",
      "a return to the political and economic systems of feudal Europe",
      "preservation of the rights of the indigenous peoples"
    ],
    "answer": "the exploitation of the labor and resources of these continents"
  },
  {
    "id": 382,
    "question": "Take up the White Man s burden",
    "option": [
      "negative attitude of Europeans toward peoples of the non-Western world",
      "advantages Europeans would gain by colonizing Africa, Asia, and Latin America",
      "positive role of the Roman Catholic Church in Africa and Asia",
      "challenges non-Europeans faced when trading with the Europeans"
    ],
    "answer": "negative attitude of Europeans toward peoples of the non-Western world"
  },
  {
    "id": 383,
    "question": "Both the French and the British were interested in controlling Egypt in the mid-19th century because Egypt had",
    "option": [
      "control of the spice trade",
      "an industrial-based economy",
      "vital mineral resources",
      "a strategic location"
    ],
    "answer": "a strategic location"
  },
  {
    "id": 384,
    "question": ", you, Africa, suffered like a beast  Your ashes strewn to the wind that roams the desert,",
    "option": ["imperialism", "communism", "nationalism", "regionalism"],
    "answer": "imperialism"
  },
  {
    "id": 385,
    "question": "The results of the Opium War (1839-1842) indicate that China was",
    "option": [
      "still a major military power",
      "not strong enough to resist Western demands",
      "rapidly building a modern industrial economy",
      "accepting Western nations as equal trading partners"
    ],
    "answer": "not strong enough to resist Western demands"
  },
  {
    "id": 386,
    "question": "During the 18th and 19th centuries, Europeans improved roads and bridges and built railroads in their colonies primarily to",
    "option": [
      "provide jobs for the colonists",
      "obtain raw materials needed for industrialization",
      "impress the colonists with their technological knowledge",
      "help missionaries spread Christianity"
    ],
    "answer": "obtain raw materials needed for industrialization"
  },
  {
    "id": 387,
    "question": "Compared to other peoples of the world we have the greatest (largest) population and our civilization is four thousand years old Today we are the poorest and weakest nation in the world and occupy the lowest position in international affairs.  Other men are the carving knife and serving dish, we are the fish and the meat.  As a consequence we are being transformed everywhere into a colony of the foreign powers.",
    "option": [
      "Opium War and Boxer Rebellion",
      "Mau Mau uprising and adoption of apartheid",
      "Sepoy Mutiny and the Salt March",
      "Haitian Revolution and Cortes  march on Mexico City"
    ],
    "answer": "Opium War and Boxer Rebellion"
  },
  {
    "id": 388,
    "question": "One result of British colonialism in India was that India",
    "option": [
      "adopted a parliamentary system of government",
      "developed religious unity",
      "supported Western foreign policies in the United Nations",
      "created programs to increase its population"
    ],
    "answer": "adopted a parliamentary system of government"
  },
  {
    "id": 389,
    "question": "The Ashanti and Ijebu... strongly resisted missionary incursion [interference]-for a time at least . . . Both groups grudgingly [reluctantly] accepted missionaries and their schools only after military defeat by imperial forces.       Edward H. Berman",
    "option": [
      "opposed giving up their religious and cultural heritage",
      "returned to the worship of their traditional gods after the defeat of the missionaries",
      "cooperated with the missionaries for economic gain",
      "feared that missionaries would refuse to teach their children"
    ],
    "answer": "opposed giving up their religious and cultural heritage"
  },
  {
    "id": 390,
    "question": "In 19th-century China, the Opium War resulted in",
    "option": [
      "the control of Hong Kong being returned to China",
      "the removal of all British naval forces from China",
      "an increase in European spheres of influence in China",
      "the rejection of Buddhism by the Chinese people"
    ],
    "answer": "an increase in European spheres of influence in China"
  },
  {
    "id": 391,
    "question": "The borders that were established for many African nations during the late 1800 s were based primarily on",
    "option": [
      "natural geographic barriers",
      "easy access to natural resources",
      "territorial claims of colonial rulers",
      "cultural differences between ethnic groups"
    ],
    "answer": "territorial claims of colonial rulers"
  },
  {
    "id": 392,
    "question": "An analysis of the Russo-Japanese War and the Boer War shows that one reason nations go to war is to",
    "option": [
      "assist oppressed people",
      "spread religious beliefs",
      "satisfy imperialist goals",
      "honor provisions of a treaty"
    ],
    "answer": "satisfy imperialist goals"
  },
  {
    "id": 393,
    "question": "Which statement best expresses the motive for 19th-century European imperialism?",
    "option": [
      "Living space was needed for the excess population in western Europe.",
      "European leaders believed imperialism was an effective method of reducing the number of wars.",
      "European nations would benefit from some aspects of the conquered nation s culture.",
      "Imperialism would benefit the economies of the colonial powers."
    ],
    "answer": "Imperialism would benefit the economies of the colonial powers."
  },
  {
    "id": 394,
    "question": "In 1917, Bolshevik leaders in Russia sought peace with Germany because the new Russian government",
    "option": [
      "decided to join forces with Germany and the Central Powers",
      "needed to concentrate its troops and resources on its war with Turkey",
      "wanted to retain power and avoid German occupation",
      "needed to control the Baltic Sea and wanted a warm water port"
    ],
    "answer": "wanted to retain power and avoid German occupation"
  },
  {
    "id": 395,
    "question": "In Eastern Europe after World War I, the greatest obstacle to national unity in many nation-states was the",
    "option": [
      "great ethnic diversity found in the region",
      "economic dependence of Eastern Europe on Japan",
      "acceptance of democratic traditions by most Eastern Europeans",
      "expansion of United States influence in the region"
    ],
    "answer": "great ethnic diversity found in the region"
  },
  {
    "id": 396,
    "question": "Which statement best describes the relationship between World War I and the Russian Revolution?",
    "option": [
      "World War I created conditions within Russia that helped trigger a revolution",
      "World War I postponed the Russian Revolution by restoring confidence in the Czar",
      "the Russian Revolution inspired the Russian people to win World War I",
      "World War I gave the Czar s army the needed experience to suppress the Russian Revolution"
    ],
    "answer": "World War I created conditions within Russia that helped trigger a revolution"
  },
  {
    "id": 397,
    "question": "A major cause of World War I was",
    "option": [
      "a decline in the policy of imperialism",
      "the existence of opposing alliances",
      "an increase in acts of aggression by England",
      "the spread of communism throughout Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "the existence of opposing alliances"
  },
  {
    "id": 398,
    "question": "Why was the Balkan region referred to as the  Powder Keg of Europe  prior to World War I?",
    "option": [
      "The aggression of the Ottoman Empire was disrupting the balance of power.",
      "Yugoslavia was invading its neighboring countries.",
      "Nationalistic and imperialistic rivalries were increasing.",
      "The area was the leading supplier of military equipment to the rest of the world."
    ],
    "answer": "Nationalistic and imperialistic rivalries were increasing."
  },
  {
    "id": 399,
    "question": "The major impact of the Treaty of Versailles on Germany was that the treaty led to",
    "option": [
      "an era of peace and international good will in Germany",
      "a stable Germany that was both democratic and strong",
      "an increase in Germany s desire to regain its power and prestige",
      "a leadership position for Germany in the League of Nations"
    ],
    "answer": "an increase in Germany s desire to regain its power and prestige"
  },
  {
    "id": 400,
    "question": "Archduke Franz Ferdinand Assassinated!    Germany Declares War on Russia and France!",
    "option": ["Franco-Prussian War", "Crimean War", "World War I", "Cold War"],
    "answer": "World War I"
  },
  {
    "id": 401,
    "question": "Which is generally a characteristic of a communist economy?",
    "option": [
      "investment is encouraged by the promise of large profits",
      "the role of government in the economy is restricted by law",
      "government agencies are involved in production planning",
      "entrepreneurs sell shares in their companies to the government"
    ],
    "answer": "government agencies are involved in production planning"
  },
  {
    "id": 402,
    "question": "A group of planners makes all economic decisions. The group assigns natural, human, and capital resources to the production of those goods and services it wants. The group decides how to produce them and to whom to distribute them",
    "option": [
      "manorial economy of feudal Europe",
      "mercantile economy of 18th century Europe",
      "command economy of the Soviet Union",
      "market economy of the United States"
    ],
    "answer": "command economy of the Soviet Union"
  },
  {
    "id": 403,
    "question": "Which situation resulted from the Russo-Japanese War of 1905?",
    "option": [
      "Japan lost its status as a world power",
      "the Japanese Emperor encouraged reforms in Russia",
      "dissident groups challenged the power of the Russian Czar",
      "Russia gained control of China and Japan"
    ],
    "answer": "dissident groups challenged the power of the Russian Czar"
  },
  {
    "id": 404,
    "question": "Stalin s Five-Year Plans and his decision to form collectives are examples of",
    "option": [
      "strategies to modernize the economy of the Soviet Union through forced communism",
      "a more friendly foreign policy toward China",
      "methods of dealing with the United States during the Cold War",
      "programs to westernize, educate, and enlighten the population"
    ],
    "answer": "strategies to modernize the economy of the Soviet Union through forced communism"
  },
  {
    "id": 405,
    "question": "A major cause of the Russian Revolution of 1917 was the",
    "option": [
      "defeat of Germany in the Russian campaign",
      "marriage of Czar Nicholas II to a German princess",
      "existence of sharp economic differences between social classes",
      "appeal of Marxism to the Russian nobility"
    ],
    "answer": "existence of sharp economic differences between social classes"
  },
  {
    "id": 406,
    "question": "Which is an accurate statement about the Soviet economy under the leadership of Joseph Stalin?",
    "option": [
      "a large selection of consumer goods became available",
      "the Soviet Union increased its industrial output by developing heavy industry",
      "private farmers were encouraged to sell their surplus produce in an open market",
      "the government reduced its role in planning industrial production"
    ],
    "answer": "the Soviet Union increased its industrial output by developing heavy industry"
  },
  {
    "id": 407,
    "question": "A major effect of Josef Stalin s policy of Collectivization on Soviet agriculture was",
    "option": [
      "a widespread food shortage throughout the nation",
      "an increase in the export of agricultural products",
      "a surplus of agricultural goods",
      "the immediate creation of many small private farms"
    ],
    "answer": "a widespread food shortage throughout the nation"
  },
  {
    "id": 408,
    "question": "One action taken by both V.I. Lenin and Joseph Stalin was",
    "option": [
      "attempting to bring democracy to Russia",
      "jailing or murdering potential opponents",
      "supporting the Russian Orthodox Church",
      "providing economic aid to Japan after World War I and World War II"
    ],
    "answer": "jailing or murdering potential opponents"
  },
  {
    "id": 409,
    "question": "The Russian peasants supported the Bolsheviks in the 1917 Revolutions mainly because the Bolsheviks promised to",
    "option": [
      "establish collective farms",
      "maintain the agricultural price-support system",
      "bring modern technology to Russian farms",
      "redistribute the land owned by the nobility"
    ],
    "answer": "redistribute the land owned by the nobility"
  },
  {
    "id": 410,
    "question": "Which statement best describes the political situation in the Soviet Union immediately after Lenin s death in 1924?",
    "option": [
      "the nation adopted a constitutional monarchy",
      "Trotsky and his followers assumed full control of the Communist Party",
      "popular elections were held to choose a new general secretary",
      "a power struggle developed among Communist Party leaders"
    ],
    "answer": "a power struggle developed among Communist Party leaders"
  },
  {
    "id": 411,
    "question": "The term that best describes the position of Jews in Czarist Russia is",
    "option": [
      "political elite",
      "persecuted minority",
      "landed gentry",
      "military leaders"
    ],
    "answer": "persecuted minority"
  },
  {
    "id": 412,
    "question": "the organizations of the revolutionaries must consist first, foremost, and mainly of people who make revolutionary activity their profession such an organization must of necessity be not too extensive and as secret as possible",
    "option": [
      "defeat Germany in World War I",
      "establish democracy in Russia",
      "maintain communist power in Western Europe",
      "overthrow the Russian government"
    ],
    "answer": "overthrow the Russian government"
  },
  {
    "id": 413,
    "question": "The 1917 victory of the communists in Russia was a contradiction of Marxist theory because Russia was",
    "option": [
      "already ruled by a socialist government",
      "involved in World War I",
      "mainly an agricultural society",
      "not considered to be a military power"
    ],
    "answer": "mainly an agricultural society"
  },
  {
    "id": 414,
    "question": "Josef Stalin s leadership of the Soviet Union can best be characterized as a period of",
    "option": [
      "democratic reform and nationalism",
      "humanism and democracy",
      "religious freedom and tolerance",
      "censorship and terror"
    ],
    "answer": "censorship and terror"
  },
  {
    "id": 415,
    "question": "The political reorganization of Russia after the Communist Revolution of 1917 resulted in",
    "option": [
      "the establishment of a two-party political system",
      "increased political power for ethnic minorities",
      "a limited monarchy with the czar as a figurehead",
      "a federation of socialist republics"
    ],
    "answer": "a federation of socialist republics"
  },
  {
    "id": 416,
    "question": "Under Josef Stalin, the Soviet Union emphasized centralized economic planning and Five-Year Plans primarily to",
    "option": [
      "produce more consumer goods",
      "expand exports",
      "create a demand for high-quality imports",
      "develop heavy industry"
    ],
    "answer": "develop heavy industry"
  },
  {
    "id": 417,
    "question": "Which characteristic was common to both Russia under the Czars and the Soviet Union under Josef Stalin?",
    "option": [
      "a lack of concern about territorial expansion",
      "support of artistic and literary freedom",
      "encouragement of free enterprise",
      "persecution of political dissenters"
    ],
    "answer": "persecution of political dissenters"
  },
  {
    "id": 418,
    "question": "Under Joseph Stalin, life in the Soviet Union was characterized by",
    "option": [
      "an abundance of consumer goods",
      "political instability and numerous civil wars",
      "support for small family-run farms",
      "the use of censorship and the secret police"
    ],
    "answer": "the use of censorship and the secret police"
  },
  {
    "id": 419,
    "question": "Which slogan expressed the ideals of the Bolshevik Revolution of 1917?",
    "option": [
      "Liberty, Equality, and Fraternity",
      "Bread, Land, and Peace",
      "Land and Liberty",
      "Nationalism, Democracy, and the People s Livelihood"
    ],
    "answer": "Bread, Land, and Peace"
  },
  {
    "id": 420,
    "question": "Russian peasants supported the Bolsheviks in 1917 primarily because the Bolsheviks pledged to",
    "option": [
      "establish and maintain collective farms",
      "redistribute land and make peace",
      "keep crop yields low",
      "limit the income of the nobility"
    ],
    "answer": "redistribute land and make peace"
  },
  {
    "id": 421,
    "question": "Which statement best describes a relationship between World War I and the Bolshevik Revolution?",
    "option": [
      "World War I created conditions in Russia that helped trigger a revolution.",
      "World War I postponed the revolution in Russia by restoring confidence in the Czar.",
      "Opposing Russian forces cooperated to fight the foreign invaders.",
      "World War I gave the Czar s army the needed experience to suppress the revolution."
    ],
    "answer": "World War I created conditions in Russia that helped trigger a revolution."
  },
  {
    "id": 422,
    "question": "The Kirghiz with whom we stopped was very well off. . . . After some tea our host asked me,  Where is the Ak Padsha now, the White Tsar Nikolai?    He and all his family, the Tsaritsa, their daughters and son, have been killed by the Bolsheviks,  I answered.",
    "option": [
      "during the Napoleonic Wars",
      "after Mao Zedong came to power",
      "after the Russian Revolution",
      "during World War II"
    ],
    "answer": "after the Russian Revolution"
  },
  {
    "id": 423,
    "question": "In the 1920 s and 1930 s, the rise of totalitarian governments in Germany, Italy, and Spain was largely the result of",
    "option": [
      "the success of the Communists in establishing a command economy in the Soviet Union",
      "severe economic and social problems that arose in Europe after World War I",
      "the active support of the United States",
      "movements demanding the return of the old monarchies"
    ],
    "answer": "severe economic and social problems that arose in Europe after World War I"
  },
  {
    "id": 424,
    "question": "The harsh conditions imposed by the Treaty of Versailles after World War I helped lay the foundation for the",
    "option": [
      "rise of fascism Germany",
      "uprisings during the French Revolution",
      "division of Korea along the 38th parallel",
      "Bolshevik Revolution in Russia"
    ],
    "answer": "rise of fascism Germany"
  },
  {
    "id": 425,
    "question": "Between the Meiji Restoration and World War II, Japan tried to solve the problem of its scarcity of natural resources by",
    "option": [
      "exporting agricultural products in exchange for new technology",
      "establishing a policy of imperialism",
      "building nuclear power plants",
      "cooperating with the Soviet Union to gain needed resources"
    ],
    "answer": "establishing a policy of imperialism"
  },
  {
    "id": 426,
    "question": "Which idea was included in the provisions of the Treaty of Versailles to show the intent of the Allies to punish the Central Powers for their role in World War II?",
    "option": [
      "all nations shall maintain open covenants of peace",
      "freedom of the seas will be maintained",
      "Germany will accept full responsibility for causing the war",
      "territorial settlements shall be made along clearly recognizable lines of nationality"
    ],
    "answer": "Germany will accept full responsibility for causing the war"
  },
  {
    "id": 427,
    "question": "Fascism in Europe during the 1920 s and 1930 s is best described as a",
    "option": [
      "demonstration of laissez-faire capitalism that promoted free enterprise",
      "form of totalitarianism that glorified the state above the individual",
      "type of economic system that stressed a classless society",
      "set of humanist ideas that emphasized the dignity and worth of the individual"
    ],
    "answer": "form of totalitarianism that glorified the state above the individual"
  },
  {
    "id": 428,
    "question": "Censorship, mass arrests, and a secret police force are most characteristic of",
    "option": [
      "parliamentary democracies",
      "republics",
      "totalitarian regimes",
      "constitutional monarchies"
    ],
    "answer": "totalitarian regimes"
  },
  {
    "id": 429,
    "question": "After World War I, Japan attempted to solve some of its economic problems by",
    "option": [
      "establishing extensive trade with the Soviet Union",
      "expanding its influence in Asia",
      "practicing the principles of Marxism",
      "refusing to rely on Western technology"
    ],
    "answer": "expanding its influence in Asia"
  },
  {
    "id": 430,
    "question": "Which policy shows that appeasement does not always prevent war?",
    "option": [
      "British policy toward Germany in Munich during the 1930 s",
      "French policy in Indochina in the 1950 s",
      "United States policy toward Cuba in the early 1960 s",
      "Iraqi policy toward Iran in the 1980 s"
    ],
    "answer": "British policy toward Germany in Munich during the 1930 s"
  },
  {
    "id": 431,
    "question": "In the 1930 s, the Japanese government followed a policy of imperialism primarily to",
    "option": [
      "acquire new sources of raw materials",
      "spread Zen Buddhism throughout Asia",
      "sell more consumer goods to European nations",
      "spread the ideas of bushido"
    ],
    "answer": "acquire new sources of raw materials"
  },
  {
    "id": 432,
    "question": "What was one reason the Nazi programs and policies of the early 1930 s appealed to many people in Germany?",
    "option": [
      "the people were frustrated with their current economic and political situation",
      "Germany had been denied membership in the United Nations",
      "a coup d etat had forced communism on the German people",
      "the German people feared that the French of the British would soon gain control of the Polish corridor"
    ],
    "answer": "the people were frustrated with their current economic and political situation"
  },
  {
    "id": 433,
    "question": "The imperialist policies followed by Japan after World War I were based on a desire to",
    "option": [
      "convert people to Shinto",
      "acquire markets for its oil industry",
      "compete with Chinese trade policies",
      "obtain natural resources for manufacturing"
    ],
    "answer": "obtain natural resources for manufacturing"
  },
  {
    "id": 434,
    "question": "During the mid-1930 s, which characteristic was common to Fascist Italy, Nazi Germany, and Communist Russia?",
    "option": [
      "government ownership of the means of production and distribution",
      "one-party system that denied basic human rights",
      "encouragement of individual freedom of expression in the arts",
      "emphasis on consumer goods rather than on weapons"
    ],
    "answer": "one-party system that denied basic human rights"
  },
  {
    "id": 435,
    "question": "One reason the Fascist governments of Benito Mussolini and Adolf Hitler came to power in Italy",
    "option": [
      "were threatened by the United States",
      "supported civil liberties for all",
      "failed to join the League of Nations",
      "faced economic and political difficulties"
    ],
    "answer": "faced economic and political difficulties"
  },
  {
    "id": 436,
    "question": "Which was a characteristic of Germany under Adolf Hitler and the Soviet Union under Josef Stalin?",
    "option": [
      "an official foreign policy of isolationism",
      "governmental control of the media",
      "public ownership of business and industry",
      "the absence of a written constitution"
    ],
    "answer": "governmental control of the media"
  },
  {
    "id": 437,
    "question": "World War II is often considered to be a turning point in history because",
    "option": [
      "the League of nations demonstrated that an international organization could maintain world peace",
      "the war brought an end to dictatorships as a form of government",
      "European domination of the world began to weaken as nationalism in colonies increased",
      "religious and ethnic differences were no longer a source of conflict between nations"
    ],
    "answer": "European domination of the world began to weaken as nationalism in colonies increased"
  },
  {
    "id": 438,
    "question": "From as early as I can remember, the Emperor was an important presence even in our remote home.  He was a descendant of the gods from thousands of years before, never to be looked at or listened to by mere mortals, a presence to be revered and protected and obeyed Finally , my family and neighbors gathered around the radio and listened in stunned silence to the voice that had never before been heard, saying he was only human after all.  Everyone was crying.  I was sad and confused",
    "option": [
      "his overthrow by communist forces",
      "defeat of the Japanese in World War II",
      "signing of the Versailles Treaty",
      "conclusion of the Russo-Japanese War"
    ],
    "answer": "defeat of the Japanese in World War II"
  },
  {
    "id": 439,
    "question": "Which reform took place in Japan after World War II?",
    "option": [
      "Japan s industrial capability was greatly reduced",
      "the Emperor s position was abolished",
      "Japan became a representative democracy",
      "labor unions were declared illegal"
    ],
    "answer": "Japan became a representative democracy"
  },
  {
    "id": 440,
    "question": "A major factor in the economic recoveries of Japan and West Germany after World War II was their",
    "option": [
      "desire to avoid an invasion from China",
      "acceptance into the United Nations",
      "ability to produce nuclear weapons",
      "need to replace destroyed factories"
    ],
    "answer": "need to replace destroyed factories"
  },
  {
    "id": 441,
    "question": "Which factor most enabled Japan to rebuild and modernize rapidly after World War II?",
    "option": [
      "vast mineral reserves",
      "large amounts of fertile land",
      "a strong military",
      "a well-trained workforce"
    ],
    "answer": "a well-trained workforce"
  },
  {
    "id": 442,
    "question": "Which is one major reason the Holocaust is considered a unique event in modern European history?",
    "option": [
      "Jews of Europe have seldom been victims of persecution.",
      "Civilians rarely were killed during air raids on Great Britain.",
      "Adolf Hitler concealed his anti-Jewish feelings until after he came to power.",
      "The genocide was planned in great detail and required the cooperation of many people."
    ],
    "answer": "The genocide was planned in great detail and required the cooperation of many people."
  },
  {
    "id": 443,
    "question": "The economic policies of the Soviet Union traditionally emphasized the production of",
    "option": [
      "automobiles for export",
      "building materials for luxury housing",
      "consumer goods",
      "heavy industrial goods"
    ],
    "answer": "heavy industrial goods"
  },
  {
    "id": 444,
    "question": "Which is generally a characteristic of a communist economy?",
    "option": [
      "investment is encouraged by the promise of large profits",
      "the role of government in the economy is restricted by law",
      "government agencies are involved in production planning",
      "entrepreneurs sell shares in their companies to the government"
    ],
    "answer": "government agencies are involved in production planning"
  },
  {
    "id": 445,
    "question": "One reason the Soviet Union formed the Warsaw Pact was to",
    "option": [
      "ease the transition to democracy",
      "help institute capitalism in Eastern Europe",
      "limit the threat of invasion from Western Europe",
      "challenge the economic successes of the Common Market"
    ],
    "answer": "limit the threat of invasion from Western Europe"
  },
  {
    "id": 446,
    "question": "Which statement best describes most Eastern European countries immediately after World War II?  They",
    "option": [
      "adopted democratic reforms in their political systems",
      "became satellite states of the Soviet Union",
      "became dependent on aid provided by the Marshall Plan",
      "emerged as world economic powers"
    ],
    "answer": "became satellite states of the Soviet Union"
  },
  {
    "id": 447,
    "question": "Communist governments were established in most nations of Eastern Europe shortly after World War II because",
    "option": [
      "the region had a long tradition of strong communist parties",
      "communist governments were able to significantly increase agricultural productivity",
      "the Soviet Union used military and diplomatic pressures to install their governments",
      "members of the Communist party won free elections in these nations"
    ],
    "answer": "the Soviet Union used military and diplomatic pressures to install their governments"
  },
  {
    "id": 448,
    "question": "During the Cold War Era (1945-1990), the United States and the Soviet Union were reluctant to become involved in direct military conflict mainly because of",
    "option": [
      "the peacekeeping role of the United Nations",
      "pressure from nonaligned nations",
      "the potential for global nuclear destruction",
      "increased tensions in the Middle East"
    ],
    "answer": "the potential for global nuclear destruction"
  },
  {
    "id": 449,
    "question": "After World War II, the Soviet Union established satellites in Eastern Europe to",
    "option": [
      "support the remaining Fascist governments in Eastern Europe",
      "preserve capitalism in Eastern Europe",
      "establish democratic governments in Eastern European nations",
      "expand its power and control over Eastern Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "expand its power and control over Eastern Europe"
  },
  {
    "id": 450,
    "question": "In the Soviet Union, a negative aspect of the Cold War Era was the",
    "option": [
      "attempt to preserve democratic ideals",
      "development of peaceful uses for modern technology",
      "development of effective means of international cooperation",
      "high cost of maintaining the arms race"
    ],
    "answer": "high cost of maintaining the arms race"
  },
  {
    "id": 451,
    "question": "From Stetin in the Baltic to Trieste in the Adriatic, an Iron Curtain has descended across the continent. Behind that line lie all the capitals of the ancient states of Central and Eastern Europe. Warsaw, Berlin, Prague, Vienna, Budapest, Belgrade, Bucharest and Sofia, all these famous cities and the populations around them lie in what I might call the Soviet Sphere, and all are subject, in one form or another, not only to Soviet influence, but to very high, and in some cases increasing measure of control from Moscow.\"",
    "option": [
      "The Soviet Union has expanded its influence throughout Eastern Europe",
      "The Soviet Union has helped the nations of Eastern Europe improve their standard of living",
      "The democratic nations of Western Europe have stopped the expansion of Soviet influence in the world",
      "The Soviet Union will support communist revolutions in Southeast Asia"
    ],
    "answer": "The Soviet Union has expanded its influence throughout Eastern Europe"
  },
  {
    "id": 452,
    "question": "Prior to the 1980 s, the emphasis of the Five-Year Plans in the Soviet Union was on heavy industry.  One result was the",
    "option": [
      "scarcity of consumer goods",
      "abundance of manufactured goods",
      "rejection of agricultural planning",
      "decline in military spending"
    ],
    "answer": "scarcity of consumer goods"
  },
  {
    "id": 453,
    "question": "The Soviet Union s reaction to the 1968 revolt in Czechoslovakia was to",
    "option": [
      "permit limited political and economic reforms in Czechoslovakia",
      "withdraw Soviet troops from Eastern Europe",
      "send Soviet troops to occupy Czechoslovakia",
      "bring the matter to the attention of the United Nations"
    ],
    "answer": "send Soviet troops to occupy Czechoslovakia"
  },
  {
    "id": 454,
    "question": "Which was a major reason for the success of Soviet domination in Eastern Europe after World War II?",
    "option": [
      "Eastern Europeans accepted the doctrine of Pan-Slavism",
      "the democracies of Western Europe needed greater security",
      "the Soviet Union had military forces in Eastern Europe as a result of World War II",
      "Western Europeans feared that Nazism would be rekindled in Eastern Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "the Soviet Union had military forces in Eastern Europe as a result of World War II"
  },
  {
    "id": 455,
    "question": "The events that took place in Hungary in the 1950 s and in Czechoslovakia in the 1960 s demonstrated the Soviet Union s",
    "option": [
      "support of nationalism among satellite nations",
      "influence on the economies of developing nations",
      "determination to maintain political control over Eastern Europe at that time",
      "attempts to promote its artistic and literary achievements in Western Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "determination to maintain political control over Eastern Europe at that time"
  },
  {
    "id": 456,
    "question": "The expansion of communism into Eastern Europe was a direct result of",
    "option": [
      "the Crimean war",
      "the Napoleonic Wars",
      "World War I",
      "World War II"
    ],
    "answer": "World War II"
  },
  {
    "id": 457,
    "question": "United States involvement in the Vietnam War and the Soviet Union s involvement in Afghanistan were motivated mainly by a desire to",
    "option": [
      "exploit the mineral resources of the regions",
      "support governments that would remain strong allies",
      "stop the expansion of Japan into the Middle East",
      "establish independent nation-states in the regions"
    ],
    "answer": "support governments that would remain strong allies"
  },
  {
    "id": 458,
    "question": "Warsaw Pact Tanks Invade Budapest\"",
    "option": [
      "Mikhail Gorbachev s introduction of the policy of Glasnost",
      "Adolf Hitler s efforts to promote national socialism",
      "the Soviet Union s acceptance of capitalism",
      "attempts by the Soviet Union to strengthen communist control"
    ],
    "answer": "attempts by the Soviet Union to strengthen communist control"
  },
  {
    "id": 459,
    "question": "The invasion of Hungary in 1956 by the Soviet Union and the building of the Berlin Wall in 1961 are examples of",
    "option": [
      "United Nations Security Council resolutions",
      "Truman Doctrine failures",
      "Marshall Plan effects",
      "Cold War Era conflicts"
    ],
    "answer": "Truman Doctrine failures"
  },
  {
    "id": 460,
    "question": "During the Cold War Era, many Asian and African nations followed a policy of nonalignment because they",
    "option": [
      "had the same goals and needs as the Soviet Union",
      "needed the natural resources of Western European nations",
      "wished to receive aid from the Soviet Union and the United States",
      "were afraid of losing their vote in the United Nations"
    ],
    "answer": "wished to receive aid from the Soviet Union and the United States"
  },
  {
    "id": 461,
    "question": "We believe in nonaggression and noninterference by one country in the affairs of another and the growth of tolerance between them and the capacity for peaceful coexistence.  We, therefore, endeavor to maintain friendly relations with all countries, even though we may disagree with them in their policies.",
    "option": ["imperialism", "mercantilism", "isolationism", "nonalignment"],
    "answer": "nonalignment"
  },
  {
    "id": 462,
    "question": "Which is a major reason Cuban and Nicaraguan revolutionary movements were attracted to communism?",
    "option": [
      "communist groups promised economic reform and better living standards",
      "business owners and the military were supported by communist groups",
      "the goal of communism was to encourage religion",
      "communist leaders promised to reduce Spanish colonialism in the Western Hemisphere"
    ],
    "answer": "communist groups promised economic reform and better living standards"
  },
  {
    "id": 463,
    "question": "The main reason the United Nations sent troops to Korea in 1950 was to",
    "option": [
      "ensure that food reached areas of the Korean Peninsula affected by famine",
      "prevent North Korea from conquering the people of South Korea",
      "force the inspection of nuclear weapons plants in North Korea",
      "restore peace between warring factions of Buddhism and Shinto"
    ],
    "answer": "prevent North Korea from conquering the people of South Korea"
  },
  {
    "id": 464,
    "question": "The conflict between Israel and the Arab nations since 1948 was often considered part of the Cold War primarily because",
    "option": [
      "the policy of detente evolved from this conflict",
      "communist governments were established in many Arab nations",
      "the leadership of Joseph Stalin strongly influenced the policies of Saddam Hussein",
      "the United States supported Israel and the Soviet Union supported several Arab nations"
    ],
    "answer": "the United States supported Israel and the Soviet Union supported several Arab nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 465,
    "question": "-Berlin Blockade (1948-1949)",
    "option": [
      "throughout the period, the United States and the Soviet Union were reluctant to solve conflicts",
      "the level of tension between the United States and the Soviet Union varied",
      "economics played a key role in causing conflict between the United States and the Soviet Union",
      "the United Nations was instrumental in reducing tensions between the United States and the Soviet Union"
    ],
    "answer": "the level of tension between the United States and the Soviet Union varied"
  },
  {
    "id": 466,
    "question": "Which statement would be consistent with the views of Fidel Castro?",
    "option": [
      "The spread of communism is the greatest danger facing Latin America",
      "An American military presence is the key to the defense of Latin America",
      "Progress and justice in Latin America can only be achieved through revolutionary socialism",
      "Introducing a free-market system will improve the economies of Latin American nations"
    ],
    "answer": "Progress and justice in Latin America can only be achieved through revolutionary socialism"
  },
  {
    "id": 467,
    "question": "From the perspective of the North Vietnamese, the war in Vietnam in the 1960 s was a battle between",
    "option": [
      "fascism and liberalism",
      "nationalism and imperialism",
      "republicanism and totalitarianism",
      "theocracy and monarchy"
    ],
    "answer": "nationalism and imperialism"
  },
  {
    "id": 468,
    "question": "Which headline concerning the Soviet Union refers to a Cold War event?",
    "option": [
      " Yeltsin Assumes Power",
      " Trotsky Forms Red Army",
      " Germany Invades USSR",
      " Warsaw Pact Formed"
    ],
    "answer": " Warsaw Pact Formed"
  },
  {
    "id": 469,
    "question": "A major development in relations between the Soviet Union and the United States occurred in the late 1980 s when the two nations agreed to",
    "option": [
      "purchase all their oil from Mexico",
      "withdraw from the United Nations",
      "eliminate a group of nuclear missiles",
      "ban arms sales to developing nations"
    ],
    "answer": "eliminate a group of nuclear missiles"
  },
  {
    "id": 470,
    "question": "During the 1980 s, the Soviet Union experimented with modifications of its command economy by",
    "option": [
      "eliminating central planning",
      "allowing private ownership of major industries",
      "introducing some market economy strategies",
      "legalizing independent trade unions"
    ],
    "answer": "introducing some market economy strategies"
  },
  {
    "id": 471,
    "question": "In the 30 years after World War II, which area was most influenced by the Soviet Union?",
    "option": [
      "Southeast Asia",
      "North Africa",
      "Eastern Europe",
      "Central America"
    ],
    "answer": "Eastern Europe"
  },
  {
    "id": 472,
    "question": "Which statement best describes the political situation in Eastern Europe during the 1980 s?",
    "option": [
      "nationalism has often been a strong force for change",
      "communist governments have gained power through democratic elections",
      "ethnic rivalries have been eliminated throughout the region",
      "United States influence has been used to keep communist governments in power"
    ],
    "answer": "nationalism has often been a strong force for change"
  },
  {
    "id": 473,
    "question": "The withdrawal of France from Indochina, the involvement of the Soviet Union in Cuba, and the United States support of the Contras in Nicaragua illustrate that nations",
    "option": [
      "consistently discard traditional foreign policy goals after changes in administration",
      "tend to base foreign policy decisions on what they believe to be their self-interests",
      "no longer use warfare as a means to resolve international conflict",
      "tend to refer foreign policy conflicts to the United Nations"
    ],
    "answer": "tend to base foreign policy decisions on what they believe to be their self-interests"
  },
  {
    "id": 474,
    "question": "Which is a valid statement about the Soviet Union from the time of the Bolshevik Revolution through 1991?",
    "option": [
      "Education has been limited to the communist party elite",
      "Demand for consumer goods has exceeded production",
      "Military expenditures have been low",
      "Industrialization has not occurred"
    ],
    "answer": "Demand for consumer goods has exceeded production"
  },
  {
    "id": 475,
    "question": "In the Soviet Union, Vladimir Lenin s New Economic Policy (NEP) and Mikhail Gorbachev s policy of Perestroika both sought to",
    "option": [
      "increase spending of nuclear weapons",
      "strengthen central planning",
      "increase production through individual enterprise",
      "reduce the influence of middle-class farmers"
    ],
    "answer": "increase production through individual enterprise"
  },
  {
    "id": 476,
    "question": "During the 1980 s in the Soviet Union, a major element of the economic policy of Perestroika was",
    "option": [
      "increased collectivization of farms",
      "more reliance on local and regional decision making",
      "the expanded use of national Five-Year plans",
      "an emphasis on the redistribution of wealth"
    ],
    "answer": "more reliance on local and regional decision making"
  },
  {
    "id": 477,
    "question": "Blockade of Berlin    Operation of the Berlin Airlift",
    "option": [
      "efforts to prevent military conflict between the superpowers",
      "situations that increased tensions between communist and democratic nations in Europe",
      "attempts to weaken the Soviet Union s control of its Eastern European allies",
      "policies of peaceful coexistence and d tente"
    ],
    "answer": "situations that increased tensions between communist and democratic nations in Europe"
  },
  {
    "id": 478,
    "question": "In Eastern Europe during the 1950 s and 1960 s, the Soviet Union responded to challenges to its control by",
    "option": [
      "allowing free elections, when necessary",
      "imposing prompt and severe repression",
      "obtaining United Nations assistance",
      "granting independence to its satellite nations"
    ],
    "answer": "imposing prompt and severe repression"
  },
  {
    "id": 479,
    "question": "In the People s Republic of China, which factor best reflects Marxism?",
    "option": [
      "communal work teams on farms",
      "ownership of small farms by individuals",
      "small family-owned businesses in villages",
      "foreign influence on the economy"
    ],
    "answer": "communal work teams on farms"
  },
  {
    "id": 480,
    "question": "The Great Leap Forward in China and the five-year plans in the Soviet Union were attempts to increase",
    "option": [
      "private capital investment",
      "religious tolerance",
      "individual ownership of land",
      "industrial productivity"
    ],
    "answer": "industrial productivity"
  },
  {
    "id": 481,
    "question": "In China and the former Soviet Union, the communist governments discouraged organized religion because religions",
    "option": [
      "compete for the loyalties of the people",
      "support the principles of laissez-faire",
      "favor anarchy over organized government",
      "stress economic rather than political values"
    ],
    "answer": "compete for the loyalties of the people"
  },
  {
    "id": 482,
    "question": "A major goal of the Cultural Revolution in China during the 1960 s was to",
    "option": [
      "restore China to the glory of the Han Dynasty",
      "reemphasize Confucian traditional values",
      "weaken communist ideas",
      "eliminate opposition to Mao Zedong"
    ],
    "answer": "eliminate opposition to Mao Zedong"
  },
  {
    "id": 483,
    "question": "After World War II, the Chinese Communists were successful in their revolution mainly because the",
    "option": [
      "United States refused to support the Nationalists",
      "communists had the support of the peasants",
      "communists had more technologically advanced weapons",
      "nationalist had been defeated by Japan"
    ],
    "answer": "communists had the support of the peasants"
  },
  {
    "id": 484,
    "question": "An immediate result of the Cultural Revolution in China was that it",
    "option": [
      "helped to establish democracy in urban centers in China",
      "led to economic cooperation with Japan and South Korea",
      "disrupted China s economic and educational systems",
      "strengthened political ties with the United States"
    ],
    "answer": "disrupted China s economic and educational systems"
  },
  {
    "id": 485,
    "question": "The main reason the Chinese Communists gained control of mainland China in 1949 was that",
    "option": [
      "they were supported by many warlords and upper class Chinese",
      "the United States had supported the Chinese Communist Party during World War II",
      "the dynamic leadership of Mao Zedong had the support of the peasant class",
      "they had superior financial resources and were supported by Japan"
    ],
    "answer": "the dynamic leadership of Mao Zedong had the support of the peasant class"
  },
  {
    "id": 486,
    "question": "In China, the Great Leap Forward was an attempt to",
    "option": [
      "promote democratic reform",
      "end the private ownership of land",
      "strengthen economic ties with Europe",
      "increase agricultural and industrial production"
    ],
    "answer": "increase agricultural and industrial production"
  },
  {
    "id": 487,
    "question": "Deng Xioaping s economic reforms in China differ from the previous economic policies of Mao Zedong in that Deng s reforms",
    "option": [
      "discourage private ownership of businesses",
      "promote further collectivization",
      "include elements of capitalism",
      "decrease trade with the United States"
    ],
    "answer": "include elements of capitalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 488,
    "question": "The Confucian view of government and the Chinese Communist view of government were similar in that both stressed",
    "option": [
      "loyalty to the government",
      "the need for filial piety",
      "a civil service system",
      "equality of men and women"
    ],
    "answer": "loyalty to the government"
  },
  {
    "id": 489,
    "question": "A major reason for the success of the Communist revolution in China was that the Communists",
    "option": [
      "stressed Buddhism in their military training",
      "included important businessmen in their ranks",
      "promised land and power to the peasant class",
      "fought successfully against the United States during World War II"
    ],
    "answer": "promised land and power to the peasant class"
  },
  {
    "id": 490,
    "question": "In China, the Great Leap Forward and the Cultural Revolution promoted by Mao Zedong were similar in that both plans",
    "option": [
      "ended dynastic rule",
      "disrupted industrial development",
      "encouraged capitalism",
      "guaranteed human rights"
    ],
    "answer": "disrupted industrial development"
  },
  {
    "id": 491,
    "question": "During the 1980 s, the Chinese government adopted policies designed to",
    "option": [
      "increase industrial productivity",
      "reestablish Confucian traditions and values",
      "gain colonies throughout East Asia",
      "maintain its isolation from world events"
    ],
    "answer": "increase industrial productivity"
  },
  {
    "id": 492,
    "question": "Which statement about the economy of China in the 1980 s is most accurate?",
    "option": [
      "China surpassed the Soviet Union in steel production",
      "China s economy slowed down because of a lack of natural resources",
      "China increased its industrial capacity and foreign trade",
      "China s economy suffered from overproduction of consumer goods"
    ],
    "answer": "China increased its industrial capacity and foreign trade"
  },
  {
    "id": 493,
    "question": "Sun Yat-sen s  Three Principles of the People  (1911) and the demonstrations in Tiananmen Square (1989) were similar in that they both demanded that the Chinese government",
    "option": [
      "achieve global interdependence",
      "restore dynastic rule",
      "introduce democratic reforms",
      "end foreign influences in China"
    ],
    "answer": "introduce democratic reforms"
  },
  {
    "id": 494,
    "question": "The goal of Mao Zedong s policy known as the Great Leap Forward was to",
    "option": [
      "develop foreign export industries in China s coastal urban centers",
      "eliminate state-owned industries in rural China",
      "modernize China s economic system by dividing China into communes",
      "introduce capitalism to the Chinese economy"
    ],
    "answer": "modernize China s economic system by dividing China into communes"
  },
  {
    "id": 495,
    "question": "Which statement about reforms in China during the 1980 s and 1990 s is most accurate?",
    "option": [
      "Political reforms resulted in the overthrow of communism.",
      "Economic reforms were more successful than political reforms.",
      "Political reforms increased individual rights.",
      "Economic reforms forced China to return to a policy of isolationism."
    ],
    "answer": "Economic reforms were more successful than political reforms."
  },
  {
    "id": 496,
    "question": "A wind has been blowing from the West; now it will begin to blow from the East.   \tMao Zedong, 1949",
    "option": [
      "The monsoons will soon shift and bring destruction to the mainland of Asia.",
      "Chinese culture will no longer influence the people of Asia.",
      "European power will decline as a new center of power emerges in Asia.",
      "The Asian people have much to learn from the Western Europeans."
    ],
    "answer": "European power will decline as a new center of power emerges in Asia."
  },
  {
    "id": 497,
    "question": "When I go to the office, I put on my shirt and I take off my Caste; when I come home, I take off my shirt and I put on my Caste.",
    "option": [
      "the Caste system continues to influence Indian society",
      "the Caste system has been reflected by most Indians",
      "successful urban workers in India belong the same Caste",
      "the Indian government officially supports the Caste system"
    ],
    "answer": "the Caste system continues to influence Indian society"
  },
  {
    "id": 498,
    "question": "Which factor most limited the development of African nationalism?",
    "option": [
      "European support of an educational system based on local traditions and language",
      "the prior experience of Africans with economic self-sufficiency",
      "political boundaries imposed by Europeans that had little relationship to African tribal boundaries",
      "the European practice of making decisions based on local customs"
    ],
    "answer": "political boundaries imposed by Europeans that had little relationship to African tribal boundaries"
  },
  {
    "id": 499,
    "question": "One way in which Kwame Nkurmah, Jomo Kenyatta, and Kenneth Kaunda are similar is that they all",
    "option": [
      "supported the United Nations military action in the Persian Gulf War",
      "played a major role in independence movements in Africa",
      "rejected financial aid from the World Bank",
      "opposed the Pan-African movement"
    ],
    "answer": "played a major role in independence movements in Africa"
  },
  {
    "id": 500,
    "question": "Which statement best describes the political situation in Africa after World War II?",
    "option": [
      "increased nationalism led to independence for many African nations",
      "France and West Germany sought to establish colonies in Africa",
      "European nations increased their control over their African colonies",
      "the United Nations opposed the idea of self-determination for African nations"
    ],
    "answer": "increased nationalism led to independence for many African nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 501,
    "question": "If we are to remain free, if we are to enjoy the full benefits of Africa s enormous wealth, we must unite to plan for the full exploitation of our human and material resources in the interest of all our people",
    "option": ["colonialism", "Pan-Africanism", "imperialism", "urbanization"],
    "answer": "Pan-Africanism"
  },
  {
    "id": 502,
    "question": "After World War II, which action was taken by many African territories?",
    "option": [
      "demanding independence from their colonial rulers",
      "refusing to join international organizations",
      "rejecting most of the technology offered by western nations",
      "creating a strong, united Africa"
    ],
    "answer": "demanding independence from their colonial rulers"
  },
  {
    "id": 503,
    "question": "Mohandas Gandhi is best known for his",
    "option": [
      "use of passive resistance to achieve Indian independence",
      "desire to establish and Islamic nations",
      "opposition to Hindus holding political office",
      "encouragement of violence to end British rule"
    ],
    "answer": "use of passive resistance to achieve Indian independence"
  },
  {
    "id": 504,
    "question": "The primary goal of the Indian National Congress (1855-1947) was to",
    "option": [
      "reform the Hindu religion",
      "partition India between Muslims and Hindus",
      "create a socialist economy",
      "gain independence from Great Britain"
    ],
    "answer": "gain independence from Great Britain"
  },
  {
    "id": 505,
    "question": "The rise of independent states in Asia and Africa after World War II demonstrates the",
    "option": [
      "failure of nationalist movements",
      "influence of socialism",
      "success of United Nations peacekeeping forces",
      "decline of European colonial empires"
    ],
    "answer": "decline of European colonial empires"
  },
  {
    "id": 506,
    "question": "Which action best illustrates Mohandas Gandhi s concept of civil disobedience?",
    "option": [
      "a British army outpost was bombed as a protest against the British presence in Northern Ireland",
      "citizens in the United States went to jail for violation segregation laws",
      "French citizens wrote letters to their government to oppose arms sale to Iraq",
      "supporters of Ferdinand Marcos attempted a coup d etat against the Philippine government"
    ],
    "answer": "citizens in the United States went to jail for violation segregation laws"
  },
  {
    "id": 507,
    "question": "Which has been a characteristic of many Southeast Asian countries since World War II?",
    "option": [
      "internal struggles for power that lead to political instability",
      "isolation from the influence of the superpowers",
      "democratic governments based on the principles of the French Revolution",
      "fundamentalist Islamic governments supported by Iran"
    ],
    "answer": "internal struggles for power that lead to political instability"
  },
  {
    "id": 508,
    "question": "Which event was used by Mohandas Gandhi to bring world attention to the injustices of British colonialism?",
    "option": [
      "salt march",
      "partition of India",
      "Sepoy Mutiny",
      "formation of the Indian parliament"
    ],
    "answer": "salt march"
  },
  {
    "id": 509,
    "question": "Since the 1950 s, India has experienced conflict with both Pakistan and China over",
    "option": [
      "United Nations peacekeeping efforts in the region",
      "India s increasing trade with Korea",
      "borders and related territorial issues",
      "the interpretation of common religious works"
    ],
    "answer": "borders and related territorial issues"
  },
  {
    "id": 510,
    "question": "Which statement best reflects a belief of Mohandas Gandhi?",
    "option": [
      "Muslims and Hindus must be separated if true peace is to come to India",
      "India must adopt the British factory system",
      "The caste system must remain an important cornerstone of Hindu society",
      "India must achieve independence, but not at the expense of further dividing the Indian people"
    ],
    "answer": "India must achieve independence, but not at the expense of further dividing the Indian people"
  },
  {
    "id": 511,
    "question": "Since India s independence in 1947, the government has had the greatest success in",
    "option": [
      "increasing overall food production",
      "reducing the population",
      "eliminating religious conflict",
      "controlling industrial pollution"
    ],
    "answer": "increasing overall food production"
  },
  {
    "id": 512,
    "question": "The Canal was dug by Egypt s sons and 120,000 of them died while working.  The Suez Canal Company in Paris is an imposter company.  It usurped our concessions  Therefore, I have signed today the following law which has been approved by the Cabinet: Article 1 of the decree reads,  The Universal Company of the Suez Maritime Canal Egyptian Joint-Stock Company   is hereby nationalized. All its assets, rights and obligations are hereby transferred to the Nation.",
    "option": [
      "end trade with Mediterranean countries",
      "stop building canals",
      "take control of the Suez Canal",
      "sell the Suez Canal to France"
    ],
    "answer": "take control of the Suez Canal"
  },
  {
    "id": 513,
    "question": "One reason India gained its independence from Great Britain in 1947 was that",
    "option": [
      "Great Britain was defeated in World War II",
      "the Treaty of Versailles required Great Britain to give up its colonies",
      "Great Britain did not have the resources to maintain an empire after World War II",
      "India had supported the Axis Powers during World War II"
    ],
    "answer": "Great Britain did not have the resources to maintain an empire after World War II"
  },
  {
    "id": 514,
    "question": "One important similarity between Indira Gandhi of India and Benazir Bhutto of Pakistan is that both",
    "option": [
      "are Hindu leaders of Islamic nations",
      "became important national leaders in nations in which women have not traditionally had equal opportunities",
      "came into power as a result of the breakup of the Soviet Union",
      "became leaders of the Asian bloc of nations at the United Nations"
    ],
    "answer": "became important national leaders in nations in which women have not traditionally had equal opportunities"
  },
  {
    "id": 515,
    "question": "One similarity between the Sepoys in India, the Boxers in China, and the Mau Mau in Kenya is that these groups",
    "option": [
      "tried to drive Europeans out of their countries",
      "depended on Western support for their success",
      "adopted Marxist economic and political principles",
      "sought independence through nonviolence"
    ],
    "answer": "tried to drive Europeans out of their countries"
  },
  {
    "id": 516,
    "question": "The  homespun movement  and the Salt March promoted by Mohandas Gandhi in India are examples of his policy of",
    "option": [
      "industrialization",
      "isolationism",
      "nonalignment",
      "nonviolent protest"
    ],
    "answer": "nonviolent protest"
  },
  {
    "id": 517,
    "question": "Which statement best explains why India was partitioned in 1947?",
    "option": [
      "the British feared a united India",
      "one region wanted to remain under British control",
      "religious differences led to political division",
      "communist supporters wanted a separate state"
    ],
    "answer": "religious differences led to political division"
  },
  {
    "id": 518,
    "question": "During India s independence movement, Mohandas Gandhi s boycott of British-made products was effective because the British considered India a major",
    "option": [
      "shipping center",
      "industrial center",
      "market for manufactured goods",
      "source of mineral resources"
    ],
    "answer": "market for manufactured goods"
  },
  {
    "id": 519,
    "question": "The stability of many African nations continues to be threatened by the",
    "option": [
      "spread of Animism among the people",
      "ethnic and tribal loyalties of the people",
      "use of command economies",
      "establishment of labor unions"
    ],
    "answer": "ethnic and tribal loyalties of the people"
  },
  {
    "id": 520,
    "question": "The war between India and Pakistan in Kashmir in 1965, the sending of Indian troops to Sir Lanka in 1987, and the assassination of Rajiv Gandhi in 1991 all demonstrate that in South Asia",
    "option": [
      "a. the Shino religion is a significant force",
      "a. United Nations peacekeeping forces are ineffective",
      "b. regional and ethnic rivalries remain strong",
      "c. nations are vulnerable to a communist takeover"
    ],
    "answer": "b. regional and ethnic rivalries remain strong"
  },
  {
    "id": 521,
    "question": "In India today, the continued discrimination based on caste illustrates",
    "option": [
      "a. a commitment to a capitalist economic system",
      "b. the gap between law and tradition",
      "c. the influence of the Cold War on India",
      "c. the declining role of religion in modern society"
    ],
    "answer": "b. the gap between law and tradition"
  },
  {
    "id": 522,
    "question": "India has developed a mixed economy that",
    "option": [
      "a. guarantees government control over the economy",
      "b. provides open competition without government interference",
      "c. blends free enterprise with socialism",
      "d. relies on the traditional barter system"
    ],
    "answer": "c. blends free enterprise with socialism"
  },
  {
    "id": 523,
    "question": "During the 1980 s, national unity in India was hindered by",
    "option": [
      "a. a foreign policy of nonalignment",
      "b. continued fear of attack from the Soviet Union",
      "c. political interference from China",
      "c. conflicts between Sikhs, Hindus, and Muslims"
    ],
    "answer": "c. conflicts between Sikhs, Hindus, and Muslims"
  },
  {
    "id": 524,
    "question": "With which nation are Pol Pot, the Khmer Rouge, and genocide associated?",
    "option": ["Korea", "Japan", "Myanmar (Burma)", "Cambodia (Kampuchea)"],
    "answer": "Cambodia (Kampuchea)"
  },
  {
    "id": 525,
    "question": "--Rebellion in the Congo during the 1960 s  --Civil war in Nigeria from 1967 to 1970",
    "option": [
      "poor food distribution systems",
      "communist interference",
      "demands for land reform",
      "ethnic rivalries"
    ],
    "answer": "ethnic rivalries"
  },
  {
    "id": 526,
    "question": "In some African nations today, ethnic rivalries erupt when",
    "option": [
      "political differences are motivated by ancient resentments",
      "trading companies hire nonunion workers",
      "scarce funds halt the exploration for mineral resources",
      "groups share a common heritage"
    ],
    "answer": "political differences are motivated by ancient resentments"
  },
  {
    "id": 527,
    "question": "Which statement is most accurate about many African societies today?",
    "option": [
      "modern medicines have been ineffective in decreasing infant mortality throughout Africa",
      "new attitudes and values often clash with traditional tribal practices",
      "agriculture is no longer the most important economic activity in Africa",
      "European influence no longer exists in the former colonial territories"
    ],
    "answer": "new attitudes and values often clash with traditional tribal practices"
  },
  {
    "id": 528,
    "question": "Which situation would best encourage economic development in most African nations today?",
    "option": [
      "a. increasing the population growth rate",
      "b. attracting investment capital",
      "c. reducing the number of skilled workers",
      "d. depleting their natural resources"
    ],
    "answer": "b. attracting investment capital"
  },
  {
    "id": 529,
    "question": "The caste system is still practiced in India today primarily because it is",
    "option": [
      "encouraged by village customs and traditions",
      "enforced by the military",
      "supported by Christian and Muslim teachings",
      "mandated by law"
    ],
    "answer": "encouraged by village customs and traditions"
  },
  {
    "id": 530,
    "question": "In 1991, Pakistan amended its constitution and made the Koran the basis of all its laws.  Which group was responsible for this action?",
    "option": [
      "Kashmir separatists",
      "Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO)",
      "Buddhist monks",
      "Islamic fundamentalists"
    ],
    "answer": "Islamic fundamentalists"
  },
  {
    "id": 531,
    "question": "In India, the people have resisted changing their attitudes toward the caste system because",
    "option": [
      "national Muslim leaders have supported the caste system",
      "the government is unwilling to end the caste system",
      "continued religious conflict prevents changes in the caste system",
      "the Hindu beliefs of karma and dharma reinforce the caste system"
    ],
    "answer": "the Hindu beliefs of karma and dharma reinforce the caste system"
  },
  {
    "id": 532,
    "question": "Today you won t find a single African head of state who stands on a podium and declares:  I am a Marxist.  Instead all the talk is about currency, private enterprise, and getting hold of capital.    --Tei Mante of Ghana",
    "option": [
      "African nations remain heavily dependent on China and North Korea for trade, capital, and food",
      "African nations are more concerned with obtaining investment capital than with discussing political philosophies",
      "African nations realize they must cooperate",
      "the failure of capitalism in Africa has helped the communists grow in strength"
    ],
    "answer": "African nations are more concerned with obtaining investment capital than with discussing political philosophies"
  },
  {
    "id": 533,
    "question": "The actions of Jomo Kenyatta, Kwame Nkrumah, Leopold Senghor, and Julius Nyerere were most closely associated with",
    "option": [
      "a rise in nationalism in several African countries",
      "the end of apartheid in South Africa",
      "a resurgence of colonialism in east Africa",
      "the revival of Islam in northern Africa"
    ],
    "answer": "a rise in nationalism in several African countries"
  },
  {
    "id": 534,
    "question": "The wars that took place in the Democratic Republic of the Congo and Nigeria in the 1960 s and in Rwanda and Somalia in the early 1990 s are similar in that these wars were caused in part by disputes",
    "option": [
      "over water sources",
      "over oil and mineral rights",
      "between ethnic groups",
      "between communist and noncommunist forces"
    ],
    "answer": "between ethnic groups"
  },
  {
    "id": 535,
    "question": "Indian National Congress Refuses To Support British War Effort    Indians Answer Call for the Production of Homespun Cloth",
    "option": [
      "attempts by the native people to gain Indian independence",
      "political reorganization in the British colonia empire",
      "programs to increase India s standard of living",
      "the benefits of economic interdependence between Britain and India"
    ],
    "answer": "attempts by the native people to gain Indian independence"
  },
  {
    "id": 536,
    "question": "After World War II, the conflict between Hindus and Muslims in India resulted in the",
    "option": [
      "near genocide of the Hindu population",
      "creation of the Muslim state of Pakistan",
      "forced removal of most Hindus from northern and western India",
      "decision of Mohandas Gandhi to seek election as Prime Minister of India"
    ],
    "answer": "creation of the Muslim state of Pakistan"
  },
  {
    "id": 537,
    "question": "Which statement is valid about the history of Southeast Asia?",
    "option": [
      "Industrialization has strengthened the traditional beliefs and lifestyles of the people.",
      "The area has experienced little European contact.",
      "Superpower influence has brought peace and prosperity to the region.",
      "Religious beliefs have both unified and divided the people of the region."
    ],
    "answer": "Religious beliefs have both unified and divided the people of the region."
  },
  {
    "id": 538,
    "question": "Since Nigeria s independence in 1960, its government has frequently shifted between democracy and military dictatorship. This situation suggests that",
    "option": [
      "some Nigerians support British colonialism",
      "international problems are more easily solved by military governments",
      "democracy is often difficult to establish in nations where little democratic tradition exists",
      "economic prosperity is frequently achieved by military governments"
    ],
    "answer": "democracy is often difficult to establish in nations where little democratic tradition exists"
  },
  {
    "id": 539,
    "question": "The desire for self-determination in African nations became a powerful force for change immediately after",
    "option": [
      "World War II",
      "the Boer War",
      "revolutions in Russia and France",
      "the end of the Cold War"
    ],
    "answer": "World War II"
  },
  {
    "id": 540,
    "question": "Rhodesia Becomes Zimbabwe    Gold Coast Becomes Ghana",
    "option": [
      "avoid military overthrow",
      "reflect traditional cultures",
      "reinforce colonial influences",
      "increase foreign investments"
    ],
    "answer": "reflect traditional cultures"
  },
  {
    "id": 541,
    "question": "In India today, a major reason the caste system remains strongest in rural areas is that",
    "option": [
      "economic change occurs rapidly in villages",
      "village laws have resulted in immediate social change",
      "tradition remains a strong influence in small villages",
      "Islam is the dominant religion"
    ],
    "answer": "tradition remains a strong influence in small villages"
  },
  {
    "id": 542,
    "question": "During the Cold War period, India s foreign policy was committed to",
    "option": [
      "supporting communism in Asia",
      "rejecting democracy in Pakistan",
      "nonalignment with the world powers",
      "isolationism in international commerce"
    ],
    "answer": "nonalignment with the world powers"
  },
  {
    "id": 543,
    "question": "Since the end of World War II, military rearmament in Japan has been limited by",
    "option": [
      "specific restrictions in Japan s constitution",
      "Japan s refusal to sign a nuclear nonproliferation treaty",
      "the United Nations refusal to sell weapons to the Japanese",
      "a scarcity of technology and resources in Japan"
    ],
    "answer": "specific restrictions in Japan s constitution"
  },
  {
    "id": 544,
    "question": "A sense of national unity has been difficult to maintain in India because of",
    "option": [
      "its reliance on foreign aid",
      "the emergence of a mixed economic system",
      "the continuing influence of militarism",
      "the desire of religious groups for greater autonomy"
    ],
    "answer": "the desire of religious groups for greater autonomy"
  },
  {
    "id": 545,
    "question": "Which statement about the problems of Indian independence is a fact rather than an opinion?",
    "option": [
      "Stronger government leadership would have prevented bloodshed.",
      "Control of India by Great Britain brought more benefits than difficulties.",
      "Muslim leaders wanted their own separate Muslim state.",
      "India would have been more prosperous if it had remained a colony."
    ],
    "answer": "Muslim leaders wanted their own separate Muslim state."
  },
  {
    "id": 546,
    "question": "East Africa is changing. . . . When my children go . . . with us to visit my parents",
    "option": [
      "political problems of developing nations",
      "ethnic conflicts",
      "conflict between tradition and modernization",
      "prejudice against elderly family members"
    ],
    "answer": "conflict between tradition and modernization"
  },
  {
    "id": 547,
    "question": "The main course of the Arab-Israeli conflicts from 1948 to 1973 was the clash between",
    "option": [
      "Islamic Fundamentalism and Orthodox Judaism",
      "Arab socialism and Israeli capitalism",
      "Arab nationalism and Jewish nationalism",
      "Israeli technology and Saudi Arabian economic goals"
    ],
    "answer": "Arab nationalism and Jewish nationalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 548,
    "question": "In Iran, the Revolution of 1979 and the rise of Islamic fundamentalism resulted in",
    "option": [
      "an increase in woman s rights",
      "the westernization and modernization of the nation",
      "a return to many traditional customs",
      "the introduction of a democratic form of government"
    ],
    "answer": "a return to many traditional customs"
  },
  {
    "id": 549,
    "question": "Who were David Ben-Gurion, Golda Meir, and Menachem Begin?",
    "option": [
      "leaders of the modern state of Israel",
      "scientist who developed better methods of discovering oil",
      "clergy who supported Islamic Fundamentalism",
      "Egyptian presidents who encouraged peace with Israel"
    ],
    "answer": "leaders of the modern state of Israel"
  },
  {
    "id": 550,
    "question": "During the late 1980 s and early 1990 s the greatest threat to the stability of the nations of Egypt, Algeria, and Morocco was the",
    "option": [
      "rising standard of living of their citizens",
      "economic reforms taking place in Eastern Europe",
      "rise of Islamic Fundamentalism",
      "lack of financial aid from the United States"
    ],
    "answer": "rise of Islamic Fundamentalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 551,
    "question": "Israel is a country that has",
    "option": [
      "an abundance of oil",
      "a democratically elected government",
      "Islam as its official religion",
      "friendly ties to Jordan"
    ],
    "answer": "a democratically elected government"
  },
  {
    "id": 552,
    "question": "In 1979, the signing of the Camp David Accords by Egypt and Israel indicated that",
    "option": [
      "nationalism was no longer a force in middle Eastern politics",
      "the differences between Shi ite and Sunni Moslems had been settled",
      "former enemies were able to negotiate",
      "the Soviet Union dominated Middle Eastern affairs"
    ],
    "answer": "former enemies were able to negotiate"
  },
  {
    "id": 553,
    "question": "During the 1980 s, the economic development of Iran and Iraq was disrupted because of",
    "option": [
      "increased emphasis on agricultural production for export",
      "the war fought between these nations",
      "communist revolutionary movements in these nations",
      "severe drought and famine in the area"
    ],
    "answer": "the war fought between these nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 554,
    "question": "A major factor that continues to contribute to terrorist activities in the Middle East is",
    "option": [
      "a decrease in crude oil prices on the world market",
      "the Palestinian effort to establish a homeland",
      "the presence of United Nations forces in Syria",
      "the worldwide rejection of violence as a means to end conflict"
    ],
    "answer": "the Palestinian effort to establish a homeland"
  },
  {
    "id": 555,
    "question": "The 1979 Islamic Revolution in Iran was a reaction to the failure of Shah Reza Pahlavi to",
    "option": [
      "modernize the nation s economy",
      "meet the social and political needs of the people",
      "establish political ties with western nations",
      "supply the military with advanced weapons technology"
    ],
    "answer": "meet the social and political needs of the people"
  },
  {
    "id": 556,
    "question": "During the 1980 s the governments of Libya and Iran were similar in that both were linked to",
    "option": [
      "efforts to separate religion and politics",
      "advocates of judicial reform",
      "incidents of international terrorism",
      "promotion of democratic principles in third world nations"
    ],
    "answer": "incidents of international terrorism"
  },
  {
    "id": 557,
    "question": "The actions of most Islamic fundamentalists show that they support",
    "option": [
      "a Zionist movement",
      "equal rights for women",
      "traditional Muslim teachings",
      "a renewed attempt at modernization"
    ],
    "answer": "traditional Muslim teachings"
  },
  {
    "id": 558,
    "question": "In most of the nations of the Middle East, a major long-term economic concern will be the need for",
    "option": [
      "unskilled labor",
      "imported oil",
      "diversified industry",
      "herds of camels"
    ],
    "answer": "diversified industry"
  },
  {
    "id": 559,
    "question": "Which type of government did Ayatollah Khomeini establish as a result of the Iranian Revolution in 1979?",
    "option": [
      "constitutional monarchy",
      "fundamentalist Islamic state",
      "democratic republic",
      "radical Marxist regime"
    ],
    "answer": "fundamentalist Islamic state"
  },
  {
    "id": 560,
    "question": "One similarity in the leadership of Kemal Ataturk, Gamal Nasser, and Shah Reza Pahlavi is that all these leaders",
    "option": [
      "sought to modernize their nations",
      "came to power as a result of democratic elections",
      "encouraged their people to convert to Hinduism",
      "led invasions into Israel"
    ],
    "answer": "sought to modernize their nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 561,
    "question": "As a peace process continues in the Middle East, a major stumbling block to a settlement of the Arab-Israeli conflict is the question of",
    "option": [
      "ownership and operation of the Suez Canal",
      "control of the Arabian Peninsula",
      "representation of Palestinian Arabs and Israelis",
      "land and civil rights for Palestinian Arabs"
    ],
    "answer": "land and civil rights for Palestinian Arabs"
  },
  {
    "id": 562,
    "question": "The Middle Eastern leaders Kemal Ataturk, David Ben-Gurion, and Yasir Arafat are best known for their support of",
    "option": ["nationalism", "fascism", "colonialism", "communism"],
    "answer": "nationalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 563,
    "question": "The time has come for you to go  Live where you like, but not among us...",
    "option": ["socialism", "absolutism", "humanitarianism", "nationalism"],
    "answer": "nationalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 564,
    "question": "In the 1990 s, the action by the Israeli Government that has most divided Israeli society has been the decision to",
    "option": [
      "grant control of part of the West Bank and Gaza Strip to the Palestinians",
      "support the United States led Allied Coalition during the Persian Gulf War",
      "support the Camp David accords",
      "oppose Islamic fundamentalist rule in Iran"
    ],
    "answer": "grant control of part of the West Bank and Gaza Strip to the Palestinians"
  },
  {
    "id": 565,
    "question": "The response of the international community to Iraq s invasion of Kuwait in 1990 best illustrates the",
    "option": [
      "lack of cooperation between the major world powers",
      "global acceptance of imperialism",
      "effect of oil on world politics",
      "ineffectiveness of United Nations peacekeeping forces"
    ],
    "answer": "effect of oil on world politics"
  },
  {
    "id": 566,
    "question": "The statements below refer to changes in Afghanistan in the 1990 s.     The Taliban controls the government.",
    "option": [
      "Marxist ideology",
      "liberation theology",
      "constitutional reforms",
      "Islamic fundamentalism"
    ],
    "answer": "Islamic fundamentalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 567,
    "question": "Which conclusion is best supported by this cartoon?",
    "option": [
      "Imprisonment of political dissidents rarely ends opposition to the government.",
      "The United Nations supports punishment for acts of civil disobedience.",
      "Better media coverage would prevent the imprisonment of protesters.",
      "Mistreatment of political prisoners often results in their acceptance of government policies."
    ],
    "answer": "Imprisonment of political dissidents rarely ends opposition to the government."
  },
  {
    "id": 568,
    "question": "In the Republic of South Africa, the primary goal of the African National Congress (ANC) has been to",
    "option": [
      "eliminate communist influence",
      "rule as the majority political party",
      "create a united Africa",
      "promote homeland areas for Blacks"
    ],
    "answer": "rule as the majority political party"
  },
  {
    "id": 569,
    "question": "In the 1980 s, global concern for Blacks in the Republic of South Africa led many nations to",
    "option": [
      "impose economic sanctions on South Africa",
      "demand that Whites return to their European homelands",
      "sent troops to South Africa",
      "support policies of Apartheid"
    ],
    "answer": "impose economic sanctions on South Africa"
  },
  {
    "id": 570,
    "question": "The Very First Thing You Should Know About South African Stocks and Bonds     Two Leading Financial Institutions Show You Around South Africa s Banking World",
    "option": [
      "a continuation of the international trade sanctions imposed on South Africa in 1985",
      "a renewed interest in investing in South Africa s economy",
      "the hazards associated with overseas economic investment",
      "a belief that the banks and the bond market in South Africa are inferior to those in Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "a renewed interest in investing in South Africa s economy"
  },
  {
    "id": 571,
    "question": "In which way has the end of apartheid had a positive economic effect on South Africa?",
    "option": [
      "Black South African managers have increased industrial productivity throughout the nation",
      "the introduction of communism has led to a more equal distribution of income",
      "many foreign companies have resumed trading and investing in South Africa",
      "all profits of South Africa s industries are now reinvested out of the country"
    ],
    "answer": "many foreign companies have resumed trading and investing in South Africa"
  },
  {
    "id": 572,
    "question": "Which statement best characterizes the period of apartheid in South Africa?",
    "option": [
      "the majority of the population had the right to vote",
      "the Boers attempted to conquer Nigeria",
      "many racist ideas of the ruling minority were adopted into laws",
      "French was declared the official language of the nation"
    ],
    "answer": "many racist ideas of the ruling minority were adopted into laws"
  },
  {
    "id": 573,
    "question": "In the Republic of South Africa, the slogans  Freedom in Our Lifetime  and  New South Africa  changed from promises to reality after",
    "option": [
      "Frederik W. de Klerk took over the radical white police force",
      "Untied Nations troops occupied the Transvaal",
      "Nelson Mandela was elected President",
      "the majority of white South Africans returned to Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "Nelson Mandela was elected President"
  },
  {
    "id": 574,
    "question": "A major problem currently facing the Republic of South Africa is the",
    "option": [
      "continuation of attacks from neighboring Zimbabwe",
      "move toward the creation of a theocratic state",
      "struggle for power between different groups within South Africa s black majority",
      "continued international economic embargo against South Africa"
    ],
    "answer": "struggle for power between different groups within South Africa s black majority"
  },
  {
    "id": 575,
    "question": "Since the end of apartheid in South Africa, what has been one of the major challenges to the current government?",
    "option": [
      "establishing diplomatic relations with Europe",
      "resolving regional and ethnic rivalries",
      "guaranteeing religious freedom for all groups",
      "improving transportation throughout the country"
    ],
    "answer": "resolving regional and ethnic rivalries"
  },
  {
    "id": 576,
    "question": "What is the main idea of this 1991 cartoon?",
    "option": [
      "The unification of Germany has been hurt by poor leadership in the country.",
      "The economic differences between East and West Germany have limited the growth of the total German economy.",
      "East Germany's strong economy has strengthened a united Germany.",
      "Both East Germany and West Germany have contributed equally to the new economy of a reunified Germany."
    ],
    "answer": "The economic differences between East and West Germany have limited the growth of the total German economy."
  },
  {
    "id": 577,
    "question": "During the late 1980 s, the Soviet Union experienced internal unrest mainly as a result of",
    "option": [
      "widespread protests against involvement in Afghanistan",
      "a lack of raw materials and natural resources",
      "a failure to use modern technology in the military",
      "increased demands of minority ethnic groups"
    ],
    "answer": "increased demands of minority ethnic groups"
  },
  {
    "id": 578,
    "question": "During the presidency of Mikhail Gorbachev, which problem faced the Soviet Union?",
    "option": [
      "ethnic minorities demanded the right of self-determination",
      "agricultural production grew faster than food consumption",
      "the nations of Eastern Europe insisted that the Soviet Union keep troops in Eastern Europe",
      "Western European nations refused to trade with the Soviet Union"
    ],
    "answer": "ethnic minorities demanded the right of self-determination"
  },
  {
    "id": 579,
    "question": "Article 50 in accordance with the interests of the people and in order to strengthen and develop the socialist system, citizens of the USSR are guaranteed freedom of speech of the press, and of assembly, meetings, street processions and demonstrations.   Exercise of these political freedoms is ensured by putting public buildings, streets and squares at the disposal of the working people and their organizations, by broad dissemination of information, and by the opportunity to use the press, television, and radio.",
    "option": [
      "constitutional rights guarantee a free society",
      "a national constitution always guarantees human rights",
      "a constitutional guarantee must be very specific in order to be effective",
      "a constitutional guarantee may be limited by government actions"
    ],
    "answer": "a constitutional guarantee may be limited by government actions"
  },
  {
    "id": 580,
    "question": "During the 1980 s, Mikhail Gorbachev introduced Perestroika in the Soviet Union to",
    "option": [
      "improve the economy and decentralize decision making",
      "abandon arms treaties with the United States and Western Europe",
      "tighten government controls over the communication media",
      "suppress the growing nationalist movements in Eastern Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "improve the economy and decentralize decision making"
  },
  {
    "id": 581,
    "question": "The revolt in Hungary (1956), the demonstrations in Czechoslovakia (1968), and the formation of solidarity in Poland (1980 s) are similar in that they",
    "option": [
      "were movements in restore the power of the aristocracy",
      "were tolerated by the communist leaders, who accepted the need for change",
      "represented a challenge to communist leadership",
      "represented attempts to rid these countries of western ideas and influence"
    ],
    "answer": "represented a challenge to communist leadership"
  },
  {
    "id": 582,
    "question": "One result of the collapse of the Soviet Union has been that",
    "option": [
      "some former republics have reorganized the Warsaw Pact",
      "ethnic violence has broken out in some regions",
      "an era of peace and stability has emerged in most of the former republics",
      "the republics have made an east transition to a market economy"
    ],
    "answer": "ethnic violence has broken out in some regions"
  },
  {
    "id": 583,
    "question": "Polish Communist Party Fails in Election Bid    Romanians Depose Communist Dictator",
    "option": [
      "military buildups are continuing in Eastern Europe",
      "planned economies in Eastern Europe have become increasingly successful",
      "demands for democracy ended many totalitarian governments in Eastern Europe",
      "the Soviet Union stopped independence efforts in Eastern Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "demands for democracy ended many totalitarian governments in Eastern Europe"
  },
  {
    "id": 584,
    "question": "The Soviet Union Splits into 15 Republics    Yugoslavia Experiences Internal Conflict",
    "option": [
      "communism remains an important force in Europe",
      "many Western European nations are experiencing civil war",
      "international sanctions strengthen a nation s ability to govern",
      "the forces of nationalism can either divide of unite a nation"
    ],
    "answer": "the forces of nationalism can either divide of unite a nation"
  },
  {
    "id": 585,
    "question": "The initial reaction of the Russian government to the fighting that broke out in Chechnya in the 1990 s demonstrated that Russia",
    "option": [
      "is unwilling to grant independence to dissenting ethnic groups",
      "has little control over its arsenal of nuclear weapons",
      "will defend its remaining republics against foreign invasion",
      "favors reestablishing communism"
    ],
    "answer": "is unwilling to grant independence to dissenting ethnic groups"
  },
  {
    "id": 586,
    "question": "In many Latin American nations, the leadership roles assumed by the military and by the Roman Catholic Church evolved from",
    "option": [
      "Native American beliefs",
      "the development of the triangular trade",
      "the effects of matriarchal societies",
      "Spanish colonial rule"
    ],
    "answer": "Spanish colonial rule"
  },
  {
    "id": 587,
    "question": "In many Latin American nations, which group has most resisted social and economic changes since the end of World War II?",
    "option": [
      "poor farmers",
      "the military",
      "union leaders",
      "the middle class"
    ],
    "answer": "the military"
  },
  {
    "id": 588,
    "question": "The main purpose of the Organization of American States (OAS) is to",
    "option": [
      "integrate the economies of Latin American nations",
      "encourage United States military involvement in the region",
      "destroy the power of Colombian drug lords",
      "provide a way to resolve regional problems peacefully"
    ],
    "answer": "provide a way to resolve regional problems peacefully"
  },
  {
    "id": 589,
    "question": "During the last ten years, what has occurred in many of the nations of Latin America?",
    "option": [
      "successful communist revolutions",
      "an increase in the number of popularly elected leaders",
      "a growing dependence on Cuba for economic support",
      "a return to their former colonial status"
    ],
    "answer": "an increase in the number of popularly elected leaders"
  },
  {
    "id": 590,
    "question": "Which group has been a major force in calling for the protection of human rights in Central America during the 1980 s and 1990 s?",
    "option": [
      "Caudillos",
      "military generals",
      "Landowners",
      "liberation theology clergy"
    ],
    "answer": "liberation theology clergy"
  },
  {
    "id": 591,
    "question": "Brazil s establishment of an equal partnership with foreign investors and Venezuela s control of its highly profitable oil industry are examples of",
    "option": [
      "Neocolonialism",
      "new imperialism",
      "economic nationalism",
      "Fascism"
    ],
    "answer": "economic nationalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 592,
    "question": "At the present time, which is a major economic problem for many Latin American governments?",
    "option": [
      "increased settlement in rural areas",
      "low rates of inflation",
      "inability to pay foreign debts",
      "lack of a chief executive"
    ],
    "answer": "inability to pay foreign debts"
  },
  {
    "id": 593,
    "question": "Which major economic problem has been faced by many Latin American nations throughout their histories?",
    "option": [
      "lack of capital for industrial development",
      "declining birthrate",
      "widespread acceptance of Marxist economic policies",
      "lack of labor for factories"
    ],
    "answer": "lack of capital for industrial development"
  },
  {
    "id": 594,
    "question": "During the 20th century, a major course of political problems in Latin American has been",
    "option": [
      "a decrease in population",
      "the declining importance of international trade",
      "widespread poverty",
      "increasing social mobility"
    ],
    "answer": "widespread poverty"
  },
  {
    "id": 595,
    "question": "Which has been an important factor that has discouraged investment in the economic developments of many Latin American nations?",
    "option": [
      "lack of natural resources",
      "history of colonial dependence",
      "declining birthrate",
      "political instability"
    ],
    "answer": "political instability"
  },
  {
    "id": 596,
    "question": "Which statement best describes the Roman Catholic Church in most Latin American countries in the 1980 s?",
    "option": [
      "the activities of the church are controlled by the national governments",
      "the church has confined its activities to religious issues",
      "the church has become active in social and human rights issues",
      "most people see the church as having little influence in daily life"
    ],
    "answer": "the church has become active in social and human rights issues"
  },
  {
    "id": 597,
    "question": "Which type of government has resulted from the changing political trends in much of Latin America during the 1990 s?",
    "option": ["monarchy", "military juntas", "democracy", "fascism"],
    "answer": "democracy"
  },
  {
    "id": 598,
    "question": "A major problem facing many Central American nations is that their nation s wealth is",
    "option": [
      "generally invested in consumer industries",
      "controlled by a small group of landed elite",
      "distributed throughout the large middle class",
      "held mainly by government agencies"
    ],
    "answer": "controlled by a small group of landed elite"
  },
  {
    "id": 599,
    "question": "In the 20th century, an economic weakness of many Central American nations has been",
    "option": [
      "a reliance on monsoons for water to irrigate crops",
      "an overdependence on one or two cash crops for export",
      "chronic labor shortages caused by slow population growth",
      "excessive investment in foreign manufacturing industries"
    ],
    "answer": "an overdependence on one or two cash crops for export"
  },
  {
    "id": 600,
    "question": "Since World War II, what action have many Latin American nations taken to improve their economies?",
    "option": [
      "reinforcing traditional farming methods",
      "encouraging citizens to emigrate to other nations",
      "adopting protectionist policies",
      "encouraging industrial development"
    ],
    "answer": "encouraging industrial development"
  },
  {
    "id": 601,
    "question": "In Latin America during the 1960 s and 1970 s, which group became increasingly active in promoting human rights?",
    "option": [
      "wealthy landholders",
      "Roman Catholic clergy",
      "successful industrialists",
      "military leaders"
    ],
    "answer": "Roman Catholic clergy"
  },
  {
    "id": 602,
    "question": "Which political trend exists in present-day Latin America?",
    "option": [
      "Most countries are becoming military juntas.",
      "Communism is spreading throughout the region.",
      "Democracy is replacing dictatorship.",
      "Religious leaders are making government policy."
    ],
    "answer": "Democracy is replacing dictatorship."
  },
  {
    "id": 603,
    "question": "Which conclusion about the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) can be drawn from this 1994 cartoon?",
    "option": [
      "NATO did not react quickly enough to the crisis in Bosnia.",
      "Bosnia and NATO continue to disagree about the causes of the civil war.",
      "NATO's actions have allowed communism to take advantage of the destruction of Bosnia.",
      "The United States will probably withdraw from NATO as a result of the Bosnian crisis."
    ],
    "answer": "NATO did not react quickly enough to the crisis in Bosnia."
  },
  {
    "id": 604,
    "question": "Russia Takes Soviet Union Seat",
    "option": [
      "is usually dominated by industrialized countries",
      "generally relies on the use of force to enforce its decisions",
      "responds to changing political conditions",
      "permits developing nations to block the proposals of Westerns nations"
    ],
    "answer": "responds to changing political conditions"
  },
  {
    "id": 605,
    "question": "Recent events in the former nations of Czechoslovakia and Yugoslavia reflect a nationalist trend of",
    "option": [
      "dividing nations along ethnic lines",
      "encouraging multiethnic cooperation",
      "uniting nations with similar interests",
      "supporting the development of a command economy"
    ],
    "answer": "dividing nations along ethnic lines"
  },
  {
    "id": 606,
    "question": "Disputes over India s control of Kashmir, Jammu, and Punjab are examples of the continuing problem of",
    "option": [
      "territorial claims based on religion",
      "Chinese claims to this region",
      "terrorist actions by Serbian refugees",
      "the policy of nonalignment"
    ],
    "answer": "territorial claims based on religion"
  },
  {
    "id": 607,
    "question": "One reason North Korea has been the focus of worldwide attention in the mid-1990 s is because of its",
    "option": [
      "nuclear weapons development programs",
      "commitment to increasing political freedoms",
      "development of a strong and expanding economy",
      "efforts to revive communism in Eastern Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "nuclear weapons development programs"
  },
  {
    "id": 608,
    "question": "The major goal of many minority groups, such as the Kurds, Tamils, and Sikhs, is to",
    "option": [
      "obtain self-rule and economic control of a homeland",
      "establish a multicultural state",
      "install Christianity as the state religion",
      "acquire economic aid from the World Bank"
    ],
    "answer": "obtain self-rule and economic control of a homeland"
  },
  {
    "id": 609,
    "question": "Under the leadership of Fidel Castro, Cuba has become an example of",
    "option": [
      "the success of democracy in improving conditions in a developing nation",
      "a nation in which the efforts of the United Nations has improved human rights",
      "a communist government struggling to maintain power despite economic problems",
      "the successful reform of agriculture from single-crop to multicrop production"
    ],
    "answer": "a communist government struggling to maintain power despite economic problems"
  },
  {
    "id": 610,
    "question": "Since the end of the Cold War, Cuba has experienced",
    "option": [
      "the loss of a major source of its foreign financial support",
      "increased economic growth from expanded trade",
      "expanded political influence in Latin American affairs",
      "greater independence from Communist China"
    ],
    "answer": "the loss of a major source of its foreign financial support"
  },
  {
    "id": 611,
    "question": "In France, a person drinks coffee imported from Brazil, works at a computer made in Japan, and uses gasoline from Saudi Arabia in a German automobile.  This situation illustrates the concept of",
    "option": ["empathy", "scarcity", "interdependence", "world citizenship"],
    "answer": "interdependence"
  },
  {
    "id": 612,
    "question": "Japan sells cars to the United States, the United States exports high technology to Saudi Arabia, and Saudi Arabia exports oil to Japan.  Which is a valid conclusion that can be drawn from this statement?",
    "option": [
      "Saudi Arabia controls most of the world's natural resources",
      "The United States is the world's leading exporter",
      "most nations of the world specialize in one export",
      "the nations of the world are economically interdependent"
    ],
    "answer": "the nations of the world are economically interdependent"
  },
  {
    "id": 613,
    "question": "Global problems of uneven economic development, environmental pollution, and hunger reflect the need for",
    "option": [
      "a return to policies of economic nationalism",
      "increased military spending by all nations",
      "a reduction in foreign aid provided by industrialized nations",
      "increased international cooperation"
    ],
    "answer": "increased international cooperation"
  },
  {
    "id": 614,
    "question": "The Middle East is a global importance today because it",
    "option": [
      "has become a model of economic and political equality",
      "allows major European powers to retain their spheres of influence",
      "provides much of the petroleum used by industrial nations",
      "remains a primary source of uranium"
    ],
    "answer": "provides much of the petroleum used by industrial nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 615,
    "question": "A major purpose of the Organization of African Unity (OAU), the Organization of American States (OAS), and the European Union (EU) is to",
    "option": [
      "encourage political and economic cooperation between member nations",
      "end colonialism in member nations",
      "control overpopulation in member nations",
      "provide military assistance to member nations"
    ],
    "answer": "encourage political and economic cooperation between member nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 616,
    "question": "In the past decade, Japanese automobile manufacturers have sought to improve Japanese-American trade relations by",
    "option": [
      "drastically lowering the price of Japanese automobiles for American consumers",
      "allowing an unlimited number of American automobiles to be sold in Japan",
      "importing most spare parts from Mexico",
      "building an increasing number of Japanese automobiles in the United States"
    ],
    "answer": "building an increasing number of Japanese automobiles in the United States"
  },
  {
    "id": 617,
    "question": "In recent years, a major success of the European Union (EU) has been the",
    "option": [
      "creation of a single military force",
      "rejection of national sovereignty",
      "adoption of a single language",
      "elimination of trade barriers"
    ],
    "answer": "elimination of trade barriers"
  },
  {
    "id": 618,
    "question": "The major reason the Mexican Government strongly supported the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) was that this agreement would",
    "option": [
      "raise tariffs on United States products entering Mexico",
      "reduce Mexico s economic dependence on Europe",
      "promote investment and economic growth in Mexico",
      "stimulate trade between Asia and Latin America"
    ],
    "answer": "promote investment and economic growth in Mexico"
  },
  {
    "id": 619,
    "question": "Within the past decade, the decision of the United States Government to grant China  most favored nation  status was important to China because this decision",
    "option": [
      "allowed China to join the Southeast Treaty Organization (SEATO)",
      "increased China s ability to trade with the United States",
      "helped protect China from a possible Japanese invasion",
      "eliminated Russian influence in East Asia"
    ],
    "answer": "increased China s ability to trade with the United States"
  },
  {
    "id": 620,
    "question": "Modern Japan must trade to maintain its industry and living standard because Japan has",
    "option": [
      "a limited amount of investment capital",
      "little access to the sea",
      "a lack of communication systems",
      "few mineral resources"
    ],
    "answer": "few mineral resources"
  },
  {
    "id": 621,
    "question": "The main idea of this cartoon is that Japan",
    "option": [
      "practices free trade",
      "restricts foreign imports",
      "has a policy of balanced trade",
      "imports most of its ships"
    ],
    "answer": "restricts foreign imports"
  },
  {
    "id": 622,
    "question": "Which action will help slow the trend indicated by the graph?",
    "option": [
      "expanding Green Revolution technology",
      "increasing industrialization in developing nations",
      "using alternative energy sources",
      "lowering worldwide oil prices"
    ],
    "answer": "using alternative energy sources"
  },
  {
    "id": 623,
    "question": "Which conclusion can be drawn from the information in the chart?",
    "option": [
      "Developing countries are instituting programs to limit the growth of their populations.",
      "Infant mortality is a greater problem in Africa than in Asia.",
      "The nations with relatively low birthrates have relatively high per capita incomes.",
      "The national birthrate is determined by many different factors."
    ],
    "answer": "The nations with relatively low birthrates have relatively high per capita incomes."
  },
  {
    "id": 624,
    "question": "In many Latin American nations, reliance on the production of a single cash crop has led to",
    "option": [
      "economic dependence on other nations",
      "rapid repayment of foreign loans",
      "a high per capita Gross National Product",
      "development of a strong industrial economy"
    ],
    "answer": "economic dependence on other nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 625,
    "question": "Which fact about China has been the cause of the other three?",
    "option": [
      "the economy of China has trouble providing for all the needs of the people",
      "the Chinese government has set limits on the number of children families may have",
      "Chinese cities have a severe shortage of housing",
      "China s population exceeds one billion"
    ],
    "answer": "China s population exceeds one billion"
  },
  {
    "id": 626,
    "question": "Since the collapse of the Soviet Union in the early 1990 s, Russia has attempted to build an economic system based on",
    "option": [
      "a return to feudalism",
      "the ideas of Marx and Lenin",
      "the writings of Mao Zedong",
      "free-market a system"
    ],
    "answer": "free-market a system"
  },
  {
    "id": 627,
    "question": "Which conclusion is valid concerning the food shortages some nations of Africa and Asia during the 1970 s and 1980 s?",
    "option": [
      "misuse of the land has destroyed many rich food-producing regions",
      "too few people in Africa and Asia are involved in food production",
      "acid rain has been the major cause of crop failures",
      "European nations stopped shipping food to these regions"
    ],
    "answer": "too few people in Africa and Asia are involved in food production"
  },
  {
    "id": 628,
    "question": "Which statement is best supported by the data in the graph?",
    "option": [
      "The urban areas of Honduras and Panama require the largest supply of water in Central America.",
      "Belize and Costa Rica are meeting the water needs of their urban population.",
      "Urban water supplies are declining in many Central American countries.",
      "Most Central American countries experienced a decrease in urban population between 1980 and 1988."
    ],
    "answer": "Belize and Costa Rica are meeting the water needs of their urban population."
  },
  {
    "id": 629,
    "question": "In Mexico and India, the Green Revolution has been successful because it has",
    "option": [
      "promoted democratic reform",
      "increased agricultural productivity",
      "introduced western culture and values",
      "established economic equality among the people"
    ],
    "answer": "increased agricultural productivity"
  },
  {
    "id": 630,
    "question": "The major goal of the Green Revolution has been to",
    "option": [
      "decrease the use of modern farm machinery",
      "decrease population growth",
      "increase agricultural output",
      "increase the number of traditional farms"
    ],
    "answer": "increase agricultural output"
  },
  {
    "id": 631,
    "question": "The term ?Green Revolution? is used to describe the",
    "option": [
      "tensions between developing and developed nations",
      "heavy reliance on manual labor in agriculture",
      "protests against environmental destruction caused by industry",
      "development of new types of grains and new methods of growing them"
    ],
    "answer": "development of new types of grains and new methods of growing them"
  },
  {
    "id": 632,
    "question": "The main goal of the Green Revolution was to",
    "option": [
      "prevent further destruction of the world?s rain forests",
      "solve chronic food shortages through the use of technology",
      "expand the economies of developing nations with foreign investment",
      "insure that foreign aid was received by people with the greatest need"
    ],
    "answer": "solve chronic food shortages through the use of technology"
  },
  {
    "id": 633,
    "question": "A study of the accident at the Chernobyl nuclear power plant in the Soviet Union and of severe air pollution in Mexico would lead to the conclusion that",
    "option": [
      "technology can cause problems throughout the world",
      "international trade is more profitable than domestic commerce",
      "modern science cannot solve most political problems",
      "agricultural nations have caused major world environmental problems"
    ],
    "answer": "technology can cause problems throughout the world"
  },
  {
    "id": 634,
    "question": "A major environmental problem affecting Latin America, Sub-Saharan Africa, and Southeast Asia has been",
    "option": [
      "air pollution",
      "Deforestation",
      "disposal of nuclear waste",
      "acid rain"
    ],
    "answer": "Deforestation"
  },
  {
    "id": 635,
    "question": "Many scientist believe that the ?greenhouse effect? is the result of",
    "option": [
      "overgrazing on land in developing nations",
      "using large amounts of gasoline, oil, and coal in developed nations",
      "testing nuclear weapons in violation of the Nuclear Test Ban Treaty",
      "using natural fertilizers to increase crop production"
    ],
    "answer": "using large amounts of gasoline, oil, and coal in developed nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 636,
    "question": "A major factor contributing to the destruction of the Amazon rain forests is the",
    "option": [
      "movement of people from rural to urban areas",
      "attempt of native peoples to end illegal drug traffic",
      "need for more farmland",
      "spread of Christianity"
    ],
    "answer": "need for more farmland"
  },
  {
    "id": 637,
    "question": "The amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere has increased in recent years.  Environmentalists suggest this change is a direct result of the",
    "option": [
      "improper storage of solid and nuclear waste",
      "overcutting of forests and the increased use of fossil fuels",
      "dumping of inorganic material into lakes and rivers",
      "use of herbicides and toxic substances such as asbestos and DDT"
    ],
    "answer": "overcutting of forests and the increased use of fossil fuels"
  },
  {
    "id": 638,
    "question": "In developing countries, the use of wood, charcoal, and dung as major sources of energy has created an increase in",
    "option": [
      "economic dependence on industrialized nations",
      "sales an profits for international oil corporations",
      "deforestation and other environmental problems",
      "nuclear waste products"
    ],
    "answer": "deforestation and other environmental problems"
  },
  {
    "id": 639,
    "question": "A negative impact of the use of modern technology is that",
    "option": [
      "levels of air and water pollution often increase",
      "economic opportunities are frequently limited",
      "contacts with other cultures decrease",
      "international trade is limited"
    ],
    "answer": "levels of air and water pollution often increase"
  },
  {
    "id": 640,
    "question": "In Latin America, the deforestation of the Amazon rain forest has led to",
    "option": [
      "the maintenance of a traditional way of life",
      "the discovery of new medicines",
      "overpopulation in rural regions",
      "environmental dangers"
    ],
    "answer": "environmental dangers"
  },
  {
    "id": 641,
    "question": "In the 1980?s, the governments of both Brazil and Malaysia supported the cutting of timber in their rain forests as a means of",
    "option": [
      "achieving economic prosperity",
      "increasing the national debt",
      "controlling rebellions of indigenous peoples",
      "preventing exploitation by imperialist nations"
    ],
    "answer": "achieving economic prosperity"
  },
  {
    "id": 642,
    "question": "?What harms the victim most is not the cruelty of the oppressor, but the silence of the bystander.?",
    "option": [
      "totalitarian governments generally support civil liberties",
      "nations of the world must always condemn human rights violations whenever they occur",
      "ethnic cleansing is not an issue to be addressed by the United Nations",
      "demonstrations against human rights violations are of limited value"
    ],
    "answer": "nations of the world must always condemn human rights violations whenever they occur"
  },
  {
    "id": 643,
    "question": "?United States Adopts Economic Sanctions Against South Africa?  ?Chinese Dissidents Imprisoned After Student Protest?",
    "option": [
      "imperialist expansion",
      "peasant revolts",
      "human rights violation",
      "isolationist policies"
    ],
    "answer": "human rights violation"
  },
  {
    "id": 644,
    "question": "The Tiananmen Square massacre in China was a reaction to",
    "option": [
      "Deng Xiaoping?s plan to revive the Cultural Revolution",
      "student demands for greater individual rights and freedom of expression",
      "China?s decision to seek Western investors",
      "Great Britain?s decision to return Hong Kong to China"
    ],
    "answer": "student demands for greater individual rights and freedom of expression"
  },
  {
    "id": 645,
    "question": "Which statement best describes a result of the student demonstrations in Beijing?s Tiananmen Square in 1989?",
    "option": [
      "prodemocracy protestors were successful in achieving their goals",
      "a state-controlled education program was begun",
      "the government further restricted freedom of expression in China",
      "collectivization programs were started in China"
    ],
    "answer": "the government further restricted freedom of expression in China"
  },
  {
    "id": 646,
    "question": "A common problem facing most Latin American and Eastern European nations today is that these nations",
    "option": [
      "have little arable land and few mineral resources with which to improve their economies",
      "have chosen not to belong to international organizations",
      "are struggling with a transition to democracy after experiencing years of dictatorial rule",
      "are experiencing major problems with the flood of illegal immigrants entering their nations"
    ],
    "answer": "are struggling with a transition to democracy after experiencing years of dictatorial rule"
  },
  {
    "id": 647,
    "question": "Today, human rights violations most often occur in nations in which",
    "option": [
      "freedom of the press exists",
      "government is limited by law",
      "leaders have absolute control",
      "government has a multiparty system"
    ],
    "answer": "leaders have absolute control"
  },
  {
    "id": 648,
    "question": "An analysis of the Chinese student demonstrations in Tiananmen Square in 1989 would show that",
    "option": [
      "communist governments continue to have little control over the actions of their citizens",
      "totalitarian governments frequently survive by the use of force",
      "peaceful demonstrations often succeed in achieving democratic reforms",
      "negative global reaction sometimes leads to economic decline"
    ],
    "answer": "totalitarian governments frequently survive by the use of force"
  },
  {
    "id": 649,
    "question": "In the Ancient Kingdom of Mali and in the Roman Republic, an important feature of life was the development of",
    "option": [
      "codified laws",
      "social and political equality",
      "the Islamic religion",
      "agricultural communes"
    ],
    "answer": "codified laws"
  },
  {
    "id": 650,
    "question": "Which statement best explains the periods of the Gupta Empire of India, the Golden Age of Greece, and the Renaissance in Italy?",
    "option": [
      "the winning of a war often inspires scientific and artistic achievement",
      "a combination of wealth and a time of relative peace often leads to cultural achievement",
      "a dictatorship usually encourages cultural growth and development",
      "periods of censorship are needed for a nation to achieve cultural and scientific greatness"
    ],
    "answer": "a combination of wealth and a time of relative peace often leads to cultural achievement"
  },
  {
    "id": 651,
    "question": "One way in which Medieval European society, Latin American colonial society, and society in Imperial China were similar is that each",
    "option": [
      "placed great value on public education",
      "experienced a surplus of skilled labor",
      "was organized according to a rigid class structure",
      "de-emphasized the role of religion"
    ],
    "answer": "was organized according to a rigid class structure"
  },
  {
    "id": 652,
    "question": "Which idea did Napoleon Bonaparte, Sun Yat-Sen, and Simone Bolivar have in common?",
    "option": ["divine right", "nationalism", "totalitarianism", "nonviolence"],
    "answer": "nationalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 653,
    "question": "Eighteenth-century Russia and nineteenth-century Japan were similar in that both countries",
    "option": [
      "began the process of modernization after a long period of isolation",
      "developed democratic governments after years under absolute monarchies",
      "refused to accept western technological ideas",
      "adopted socialist economic systems after capitalism had failed"
    ],
    "answer": "began the process of modernization after a long period of isolation"
  },
  {
    "id": 654,
    "question": "Until the 1500 s, China and Japan were similar in that both",
    "option": [
      "were invaded by the Mongols",
      "welcomed Christian Missionaries",
      "had little contact with Western European nations",
      "were developing democratic traditions"
    ],
    "answer": "had little contact with Western European nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 655,
    "question": "During the Middle Ages, Europeans did not eat potatoes or corn because these vegetables",
    "option": [
      "were forbidden by the Catholic Church for religious reasons",
      "had not yet been introduced to Europe from the New World",
      "were believed to be poisonous",
      "were too expensive to import from China"
    ],
    "answer": "had not yet been introduced to Europe from the New World"
  },
  {
    "id": 656,
    "question": "One way in which Medieval European society, Latin American colonial society, and society in Imperial China were similar is that each",
    "option": [
      "placed great value on public education",
      "experienced a surplus of skilled labor",
      "was organized according to a rigid class structure",
      "de-emphasized the role of religion"
    ],
    "answer": "was organized according to a rigid class structure"
  },
  {
    "id": 657,
    "question": "The societies of traditional China, Feudal Japan, and Czarist Russia were all characterized by",
    "option": [
      "a rigid class structure",
      "much interaction with other cultures",
      "great economic change",
      "rapidly changing social values"
    ],
    "answer": "a rigid class structure"
  },
  {
    "id": 658,
    "question": "One similarity between the decline of the Roman Empire and the fall of the Manchu Dynasty was that both initially led to",
    "option": [
      "improved economic conditions",
      "democratically elected governments",
      "political chaos and decentralization of government",
      "major accomplishments in art, science, and technology"
    ],
    "answer": "political chaos and decentralization of government"
  },
  {
    "id": 659,
    "question": "The Japanese feudal system and the Hindu caste system are similar in that both systems",
    "option": [
      "promoted social mobility",
      "developed a rigid class structure",
      "encouraged the people to take part in government",
      "resulted in economic opportunities for the lower classes"
    ],
    "answer": "developed a rigid class structure"
  },
  {
    "id": 660,
    "question": "Eighteenth-century Russia and nineteenth-century Japan were similar in that both countries",
    "option": [
      "began the process of modernization after a long period of isolation",
      "developed democratic governments after years under absolute monarchies",
      "refused to accept western technological ideas",
      "adopted socialist economic systems after capitalism had failed"
    ],
    "answer": "began the process of modernization after a long period of isolation"
  },
  {
    "id": 661,
    "question": "Changes in Russia under Peter the Great were most similar to changes that occurred in",
    "option": [
      "China before the Opium War",
      "Japan during the Meiji Restoration",
      "Iran after the fall of Shah Pahlevi",
      "France during the feudal period"
    ],
    "answer": "Japan during the Meiji Restoration"
  },
  {
    "id": 662,
    "question": "The Tamils in Sri Lanka, the Sikhs in India, and the Zulus in South Africa have all attempted to",
    "option": [
      "establish colonies in Asia",
      "practice passive resistance",
      "achieve political separatism",
      "encourage mercantilism"
    ],
    "answer": "achieve political separatism"
  },
  {
    "id": 663,
    "question": "Which was characteristic of France under Napoleon s rule and Germany under Hitler s rule?",
    "option": [
      "democratic ideas and diversity were encouraged",
      "authoritarian control and a strong sense of nationalism prevailed",
      "peaceful relations with neighboring countries wee fostered",
      "artistic and literary freedom flourished"
    ],
    "answer": "authoritarian control and a strong sense of nationalism prevailed"
  },
  {
    "id": 664,
    "question": "A study of the French Revolution and the Russian Revolution of 1917 would lead to the conclusion that",
    "option": [
      "revolutions only occur when a majority of citizens become directly involved",
      "university students are most often responsible for starting revolutions",
      "control of revolutions often shifts from moderates to radicals",
      "revolutions seldom result in long-term changes"
    ],
    "answer": "control of revolutions often shifts from moderates to radicals"
  },
  {
    "id": 665,
    "question": "The French Revolution, the Bolshevik Revolution in Russia, and the Communist Revolution in China were similar in that all three",
    "option": [
      "brought about few political changes",
      "were influenced by the peasants  desire for more land",
      "were inspired by Marxism",
      "were supported primarily by the nobility"
    ],
    "answer": "were influenced by the peasants  desire for more land"
  },
  {
    "id": 666,
    "question": "The ancient Greek city-state of Sparta and the Soviet Union under Stalin were similar in that both societies",
    "option": [
      "were primarily concerned with the health of their people",
      "were powerful military states",
      "granted universal suffrage to their people",
      "placed great emphasis on literature and the arts"
    ],
    "answer": "were powerful military states"
  },
  {
    "id": 667,
    "question": "In China, the building of the Great Wall, the use of the tribute system, and the government s support of the Boxer Rebellion are examples of attempts by different dynasties to limit",
    "option": [
      "foreign influence",
      "nationalism",
      "communist expansion",
      "industrialization"
    ],
    "answer": "foreign influence"
  },
  {
    "id": 668,
    "question": "The French Revolution of 1789 and the Cuban Revolution of 1959 were similar in that both were caused primarily by the",
    "option": [
      "desire of the people to be free from foreign rule",
      "pressure of religious leaders for government reform",
      "failure of the government to meet the needs of the people",
      "ambition of the upper class to attain wealth and property"
    ],
    "answer": "failure of the government to meet the needs of the people"
  },
  {
    "id": 669,
    "question": "The philosophies of Confucius and Mao Zedong both emphasized",
    "option": [
      "individual rather than cooperative gain",
      "industry rather than agriculture",
      "group rather than individual welfare",
      "religious values rather than economic profits"
    ],
    "answer": "group rather than individual welfare"
  },
  {
    "id": 670,
    "question": "Japan during the Meiji Restoration was similar to Japan after World War II in that during these periods Japan",
    "option": [
      "pursued a foreign policy of isolationism and limited political freedoms",
      "reduced the powers of the Emperor and the nobility",
      "underwent political reform and economic expansion",
      "was ruled by dictators and the military"
    ],
    "answer": "underwent political reform and economic expansion"
  },
  {
    "id": 671,
    "question": "Since the late 1940 s, India, Northern Ireland, and Israel have faced the common problem of",
    "option": [
      "adjusting to a post-Communist political and economic system",
      "continued violent confrontations between different religious groups",
      "economic depression as a result of rapid industrialization",
      "uncertainty of their acceptance by the European Community"
    ],
    "answer": "continued violent confrontations between different religious groups"
  },
  {
    "id": 672,
    "question": "The events that led to the overthrow of Czar Nicholas II in 1917 and to the forced resignation of Mikhail Gorbachev in 1991 show that",
    "option": [
      "economic crises often lead to political change",
      "Russian absolutism continued into the 1990 s",
      "international conflicts often strengthen the power of leaders",
      "Russia is an ethnically unified nation"
    ],
    "answer": "economic crises often lead to political change"
  },
  {
    "id": 673,
    "question": "Events in both Eastern Europe in the early 1900 s and in the Soviet Union in the late 1980 s were mainly the result of",
    "option": [
      "movements toward the repression of individual rights",
      "declines in the use of advanced technology",
      "the influence of religion on government",
      "challenges by ethnic groups desiring independence"
    ],
    "answer": "challenges by ethnic groups desiring independence"
  },
  {
    "id": 674,
    "question": "During the late 1980 s and early 1990 s, the Soviet Union experienced ethnic tensions that were most similar to those experienced by",
    "option": [
      "Japan in the early 17th century",
      "Austria-Hungary in the late 19th century",
      "Spain in the mid-18th century",
      "Cuba in the late 20th century"
    ],
    "answer": "Austria-Hungary in the late 19th century"
  },
  {
    "id": 675,
    "question": "The Holocaust in Europe and the actions of the Khmer Rouge in Kampuchea (Cambodia) were similar in that they were examples of",
    "option": ["Interdependence", "Segregation", "Genocide", "Empathy"],
    "answer": "Genocide"
  },
  {
    "id": 676,
    "question": "One similarity between Mao Zedong and Fidel Castro is that they",
    "option": [
      "achieved their goals through the use of peaceful resistance",
      "worked to protect citizens  rights to freedom of expression",
      "considered capitalism to be the best economic system",
      "led revolutionary movements that established communist governments"
    ],
    "answer": "led revolutionary movements that established communist governments"
  },
  {
    "id": 677,
    "question": "Germany Will Make Reparations For WWI    OPEC Supports Oil Embargo Against Western Nations",
    "option": [
      "economic measures are often designed to achieve political goals",
      "communism as an economic system has failed",
      "economic policies are often formulated to encourage investment",
      "nationalism plays a small role in economic decisionmaking"
    ],
    "answer": "economic measures are often designed to achieve political goals"
  },
  {
    "id": 678,
    "question": "A study of the policy of  ethnic cleansing  in Bosnia and the Holocaust in Europe would suggest that",
    "option": [
      "world opinion is effective in stopping genocide",
      "countries generally use reason and negotiation in dealing with important ethnic issues",
      "anti-Semitism and ethnic hatred remain powerful forces in the 20th century",
      "military leaders cannot be held responsible for acts committed during wartime"
    ],
    "answer": "anti-Semitism and ethnic hatred remain powerful forces in the 20th century"
  },
  {
    "id": 679,
    "question": "Which factor has most limited the development of national unity in India, Lebanon, and Bosnia-Herzegovina?",
    "option": [
      "lack of natural resources",
      "inability to end colonialism",
      "religious and ethnic differences",
      "rapid growth of industry"
    ],
    "answer": "religious and ethnic differences"
  },
  {
    "id": 680,
    "question": "Both the Chinese Mandate of Heaven and the Japanese belief that the Emperor descends from the Sun Goddess are similar to the",
    "option": [
      " master race  theory of Adolf Hitler s Third Reich",
      "natural rights theory of the Age of Reason",
      "divine right theory of the French monarchy",
      "Marxist theory of a workers  revolution"
    ],
    "answer": "divine right theory of the French monarchy"
  },
  {
    "id": 681,
    "question": "One way in which the caste system and apartheid were similar is that both",
    "option": [
      "described specific religious practices and beliefs",
      "supported a rigid class structure",
      "were created by British colonial governments",
      "gave power to the lower classes in their respective societies"
    ],
    "answer": "supported a rigid class structure"
  },
  {
    "id": 682,
    "question": "Within their respective nations, both Ho Chi Minh and Fidel Castro achieved their goals by",
    "option": [
      "seeking aid and support from the European Union",
      "using armed conflict to bring a communist government to power",
      "following a policy of nonalignment",
      "working to build a capitalist system"
    ],
    "answer": "using armed conflict to bring a communist government to power"
  },
  {
    "id": 683,
    "question": "One way in which the Meiji Restoration in Japan and the Golden Age of India are similar is that in each region these events led to",
    "option": [
      "the persecution of minority peoples",
      "periods of rapid change",
      "the rise of feudalism as the dominant political system",
      "governments ruled by absolute monarchs"
    ],
    "answer": "periods of rapid change"
  },
  {
    "id": 684,
    "question": "The Sepoy Rebellion in India and the Boxer Rebellion in China were similar in that both were",
    "option": [
      "attempts to improve foreign trade",
      "nonviolent resistance efforts",
      "revolts against foreign influence",
      "revolutions against traditional monarchs"
    ],
    "answer": "revolts against foreign influence"
  },
  {
    "id": 685,
    "question": "Suleiman held complete religious and political power.  Charles I stormed the English Parliament.",
    "option": [
      "scientific theory",
      "natural rights",
      "mercantilism",
      "absolutism"
    ],
    "answer": "absolutism"
  },
  {
    "id": 686,
    "question": "What would a study of the recent civil wars in Cambodia, Bosnia-Herzegovina, and Rwanda show about these conflicts?",
    "option": [
      "Ethnic conflict was not a factor in the late 20th century.",
      "The United Nations was successful in resolving these disputes.",
      "Genocide was used as a political and military tactic.",
      "Civilians were not affected by these disputes."
    ],
    "answer": "Genocide was used as a political and military tactic."
  },
  {
    "id": 687,
    "question": "A similarity of the goals of Nelson Mandela and Mohandas Gandhi is that both leaders wanted to",
    "option": [
      "secure political power for the majority of the people",
      "encourage a greater degree of industrialization",
      "improve the economy by expanding governmental control",
      "gain independence from the Soviet Union"
    ],
    "answer": "secure political power for the majority of the people"
  },
  {
    "id": 688,
    "question": "Statement 1:   This organization is created for the purpose of realizing the national ideal:",
    "option": [
      "War is a means of achieving national policies.",
      "Industrial growth is critical to a country s prosperity.",
      "Social class differences are the source of all conflicts.",
      "Self-determination of the people is an important goal."
    ],
    "answer": "Self-determination of the people is an important goal."
  },
  {
    "id": 689,
    "question": "One way in which Sim n Bol var, Jomo Kenyatta, and Ho Chi Minh are similar is that each leader",
    "option": [
      "sought independence from colonial rule",
      "ruled during a period of peace and prosperity",
      "demanded human rights for all citizens",
      "established a totalitarian government"
    ],
    "answer": "sought independence from colonial rule"
  },
  {
    "id": 690,
    "question": "Which document is an example of a primary source?",
    "option": [
      "a textbook on Russian history",
      "an encyclopedia article on religions of the Middle East",
      "a novel on the Age of Exploration",
      "the diary of a survivor of a Nazi death camp"
    ],
    "answer": "the diary of a survivor of a Nazi death camp"
  },
  {
    "id": 691,
    "question": "Which historical events are in the correct chronological order?",
    "option": [
      "Crusades -> Renaissance -> Neolithic Revolution -> Roman Empire",
      "Roman Empire -> Neolithic Revolution -> Crusades -> Renaissance",
      "Renaissance ->Neolithic Revolution -> Crusades -> Roman Empire",
      "Neolithic Revolution -> Roman Empire -> Crusades -> Renaissance"
    ],
    "answer": "Neolithic Revolution -> Roman Empire -> Crusades -> Renaissance"
  },
  {
    "id": 692,
    "question": "The United Nations Declaration of Human Rights",
    "option": [
      "secondary sources",
      "examples of oral traditions",
      "primary sources",
      "statements of different religious beliefs"
    ],
    "answer": "primary sources"
  },
  {
    "id": 693,
    "question": "Which statement best explains why most of the population of the people s Republic of China live in the eastern third of the nation?",
    "option": [
      "best agricultural land is in the East",
      "largest forests are in the East",
      "best fishing areas are off the eastern coast",
      "largest oil deposits are in the East"
    ],
    "answer": "best agricultural land is in the East"
  },
  {
    "id": 694,
    "question": "Which is an accurate statement about Japan s natural resources?",
    "option": [
      "Japan has extensively used the seas for fishing",
      "large reserves of petroleum are located in the northern part of Japan",
      "Japan has large fertile plains suitable for growing grain",
      "large coal and iron-ore deposits are located in the mountain region"
    ],
    "answer": "Japan has extensively used the seas for fishing"
  },
  {
    "id": 695,
    "question": "In Japan, a major economic problem has been the lack of",
    "option": [
      "natural resources",
      "investment capital",
      "skilled labor",
      "experienced management"
    ],
    "answer": "natural resources"
  },
  {
    "id": 696,
    "question": "Which statement best describes an effect that geography has had on Japan?",
    "option": [
      "Japan s smooth coastline has prevented the development of a fishing industry",
      "Japan s large plains have made wheat growing a primary industry",
      "the lack of important natural resources has led Japan to depend on trade with other nations",
      "the location of Japan has encouraged great ethnic diversity within the nation"
    ],
    "answer": "the lack of important natural resources has led Japan to depend on trade with other nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 697,
    "question": "Both Japan and Indonesia are made up of a chain of islands called",
    "option": ["an archipelago", "a peninsula", "a delta", "an atoll"],
    "answer": "an archipelago"
  },
  {
    "id": 698,
    "question": "The term  Latin America  most accurately refers to the",
    "option": [
      "areas of the Western Hemisphere south of the United States",
      "countries that belong to the Organization of American States",
      "continents of North and South America",
      "countries that have close economic ties with Spain"
    ],
    "answer": "areas of the Western Hemisphere south of the United States"
  },
  {
    "id": 699,
    "question": "Which generalization about geography of Latin America is accurate?",
    "option": [
      "geographic features prevented foreign imperialism",
      "harsh climatic conditions have prevented the development of large-scale agriculture",
      "the lack of geographic barriers facilitated the development of transportation and communication systems",
      "great variations in latitude and landforms resulted in a diversity of climates"
    ],
    "answer": "great variations in latitude and landforms resulted in a diversity of climates"
  },
  {
    "id": 700,
    "question": "Which geographic factor has had the most influence on Poland's historical and cultural development?",
    "option": [
      "a severe climate",
      "vast deposits of oil",
      "location on the great European Plain",
      "a rugged coastline"
    ],
    "answer": "location on the great European Plain"
  },
  {
    "id": 701,
    "question": "Which of these nations is located closet to the Philippines, Malaysia, and Indonesia?",
    "option": ["Korea", "Vietnam", "Somalia", "Pakistan"],
    "answer": "Vietnam"
  },
  {
    "id": 702,
    "question": "One effect that mountain ranges, rain forests, and river systems have had on Latin America has been to",
    "option": [
      "encourage cultural diffusion",
      "limit the development of transportation and communication systems",
      "permit the nations of the area to use a single form of government",
      "allow the development of large amounts of arable land"
    ],
    "answer": "limit the development of transportation and communication systems"
  },
  {
    "id": 703,
    "question": "In addition to providing water for Indian agriculture, the Ganges River remains important to India because it is",
    "option": [
      "the only source of Indian hydroelectric power",
      "a sacred river for the Hindu population",
      "the birthplace of Hindu culture",
      "an unofficial boundary between the Hindus and Muslims"
    ],
    "answer": "a sacred river for the Hindu population"
  },
  {
    "id": 704,
    "question": "An effect of a mountainous topography on Inca and Chinese civilizations was the development of",
    "option": [
      "industrialization",
      "single-crop economy",
      "desalinization projects",
      "terrace farming"
    ],
    "answer": "terrace farming"
  },
  {
    "id": 705,
    "question": "A major effect of geography on Japan is that the",
    "option": [
      "export of oil has helped Japan maintain a favorable balance of trade",
      "fertile plains have enabled Japan to keep food prices low",
      "mountains have prevented invasions obey foreign nations",
      "scarcity of natural resources has forced Japan to obtain raw materials from other nations"
    ],
    "answer": "scarcity of natural resources has forced Japan to obtain raw materials from other nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 706,
    "question": "Which geographic factor has most strongly influenced Russia s foreign policies and economic development?",
    "option": [
      "lack of natural resources",
      "vast desert regions",
      "limited access to warm-water ports",
      "extensive mountain ranges"
    ],
    "answer": "limited access to warm-water ports"
  },
  {
    "id": 707,
    "question": "Many people in Southeast Asia hope for the timely arrival of the summer monsoons each year because",
    "option": [
      "floods are the only way to water their farmlands",
      "daily temperatures often reach 100 degrees Fahrenheit",
      "little rain has fallen for many months",
      "oases provide water for nomadic herders"
    ],
    "answer": "little rain has fallen for many months"
  },
  {
    "id": 708,
    "question": "A topographical map would most likely be used to",
    "option": [
      "identify the major agricultural products of Egypt",
      "determine the population of Beijing, China",
      "estimate the elevation of Bangkok, Thailand",
      "count the number of provinces in India"
    ],
    "answer": "estimate the elevation of Bangkok, Thailand"
  },
  {
    "id": 709,
    "question": "On a map of the world, Asia is to Japan as Europe is to",
    "option": ["Great Britain", "the Netherlands", "Austria", "Italy"],
    "answer": "Great Britain"
  },
  {
    "id": 710,
    "question": "The Russian steppe is most similar in topography to the",
    "option": [
      "mountains in Switzerland",
      "deserts in the Middle East",
      "rainforests in South America",
      "savannas in Africa"
    ],
    "answer": "savannas in Africa"
  },
  {
    "id": 711,
    "question": "Areas of Africa and parts of Siberia in Russia are often said to be gems-in-the-rough because they have",
    "option": [
      "extensive tracts of permanently frozen land",
      "well-developed coastal fishing industries",
      "many undeveloped natural resources",
      "decreasing populations"
    ],
    "answer": "many undeveloped natural resources"
  },
  {
    "id": 712,
    "question": "In Africa, an effect of topography and climate has been to",
    "option": [
      "encourage rapid industrialization of the interior",
      "prevent the development of kingdoms",
      "promote large-scale trade between African and Asia",
      "promote the growth of diverse societies"
    ],
    "answer": "promote the growth of diverse societies"
  },
  {
    "id": 713,
    "question": "The Suez Canal, the Strait of Hormuz, and the Strait of Gibraltar are important because they",
    "option": [
      "prevent attacks on bordering nations",
      "control access to vital trade routes",
      "limit Russian access to warm-water points",
      "prohibit the movement of ships carrying nuclear weapons"
    ],
    "answer": "control access to vital trade routes"
  },
  {
    "id": 714,
    "question": "Geographic diversity in the Middle East has contributed to",
    "option": [
      "unequal standards of living",
      "a common economic system",
      "similar political systems",
      "military alliances with Japan"
    ],
    "answer": "unequal standards of living"
  },
  {
    "id": 715,
    "question": "The Suez Canal, the Panama Canal, and the Straits of the Dardanelles are similar because they",
    "option": [
      "are strategic waterways that have been the center of conflicts",
      "was part of the French colonial empire",
      "are located in regions that are rich in natural resources",
      "prohibit the movement of ships carrying nuclear weapons"
    ],
    "answer": "are strategic waterways that have been the center of conflicts"
  },
  {
    "id": 716,
    "question": "The map shows that the",
    "option": [
      "economies of all the regions of China are developing at the same rate",
      "distribution of income in China is unequal",
      "economies of the interior provinces of China are developing faster than those of the coastal provinces",
      "economic development in China is dependent upon the cash crops of Xinjiang and Tibet"
    ],
    "answer": "distribution of income in China is unequal"
  },
  {
    "id": 717,
    "question": "One factor that accounted for Chinese influence on traditional Japanese culture was the",
    "option": [
      "continuous warfare between the countries",
      "geographic location of the countries",
      "refusal of western nations to trade with Japan",
      "annexation of Japan into the Chinese Empire"
    ],
    "answer": "geographic location of the countries"
  },
  {
    "id": 718,
    "question": "Throughout the 1800 s, Russia was interested in acquiring Turkey mainly because Russia wanted",
    "option": [
      "to maintain peace in the Middle East",
      "access to the Mediterranean Sea",
      "to reestablish the Byzantine Empire",
      "the rich farmland of the Anatolian Plateau"
    ],
    "answer": "access to the Mediterranean Sea"
  },
  {
    "id": 719,
    "question": "Which geographic factor has contributed most to the economic growth of Japan, Egypt, and Great Britain?",
    "option": [
      "variety of natural resources",
      "reliable amount of rainfall",
      "abundance of arable land",
      "access to important waterways"
    ],
    "answer": "access to important waterways"
  },
  {
    "id": 720,
    "question": "In which way have the Andes Mountains and the Amazon rain forest affected the development of Latin America?",
    "option": [
      "promoting international unity",
      "increasing cultural diversity",
      "encouraging trade agreements",
      "strengthening political alliances"
    ],
    "answer": "increasing cultural diversity"
  },
  {
    "id": 721,
    "question": "Which geographic factor has helped China remain isolated for many centuries?",
    "option": [
      "many natural harbors",
      "navigable river systems",
      "severe climate",
      "northern and western mountain ranges"
    ],
    "answer": "northern and western mountain ranges"
  },
  {
    "id": 722,
    "question": "Which statement best describes an impact of topography on eastern Europe?",
    "option": [
      "Many different languages, religions, and customs developed.",
      "A Russian czar ruled the area as a single empire.",
      "An extensive single-crop agricultural system emerged.",
      "Neighbors who were more powerful could not invade the region."
    ],
    "answer": "Many different languages, religions, and customs developed."
  },
  {
    "id": 723,
    "question": "Which geographic factor was most important to the development of the early river valley civilizations?",
    "option": [
      "fertile soils",
      "high mountains",
      "vast deserts",
      "smooth coastlines"
    ],
    "answer": "fertile soils"
  },
  {
    "id": 724,
    "question": "Which factor contributes most to the recurring food shortages in Africa?",
    "option": [
      "poor distribution of agricultural products",
      "extensive river systems",
      "location between two major oceans",
      "rainforest environment"
    ],
    "answer": "poor distribution of agricultural products"
  },
  {
    "id": 725,
    "question": "Which condition is a major obstacle to economic development in the Middle East and Northern Africa",
    "option": [
      "use of strip mining to obtain minerals",
      "reliance on capitalist economic systems",
      "lack of access to world markets",
      "scarcity of water resources"
    ],
    "answer": "scarcity of water resources"
  },
  {
    "id": 726,
    "question": "Singapore and Hong Kong have become major economic powers by taking advantage of their",
    "option": [
      "abundant mineral resources",
      "imported cheap labor from Japan",
      "profits from agricultural surpluses",
      "favorable location on international trade routes"
    ],
    "answer": "favorable location on international trade routes"
  },
  {
    "id": 727,
    "question": "Throughout the 1800 s, Russia was interested in acquiring Turkey mainly because Russia wanted",
    "option": [
      "to maintain peace in the Middle East",
      "access to the Mediterranean Sea",
      "to reestablish the Byzantine Empire",
      "the rich farmland of the Anatolian Plateau"
    ],
    "answer": "access to the Mediterranean Sea"
  },
  {
    "id": 728,
    "question": "Which conclusion can be drawn from the information in the chart?",
    "option": [
      "Developing countries are instituting programs to limit the growth of their populations.",
      "Infant mortality is a greater problem in Africa than in Asia.",
      "The nations with relatively low birthrates have relatively high per capita incomes.",
      "The national birthrate is determined by many different factors."
    ],
    "answer": "The nations with relatively low birthrates have relatively high per capita incomes."
  },
  {
    "id": 729,
    "question": "A comparison of Japan s policies before 1945 with the policies in effect after 1945 indicates that",
    "option": [
      "reduction in spending on military goods leads to economic depression",
      "dependence on foreign trade usually leads to a weakened national economy",
      "territorial aggression is not necessary to secure national economic goals",
      "democratic institutions hinder economic growth"
    ],
    "answer": "territorial aggression is not necessary to secure national economic goals"
  },
  {
    "id": 730,
    "question": "A study of Japan s economy since World War II would lead to the conclusion that",
    "option": [
      "a. government support of technological advances can improve a nation s economic position",
      "a. imperialism is necessary form the economic development of a nation",
      "a. a communist system leads to economic prosperity",
      "a. the feudal system is more economically productive than the market system"
    ],
    "answer": "a. government support of technological advances can improve a nation s economic position"
  },
  {
    "id": 731,
    "question": "Which situation has contributed most to recent Japanese economic growth?",
    "option": [
      "The Japanese government has place limits on Japanese exports.",
      "Japanese industries spend very little on the research and development of new products.",
      "The Japanese government and Japanese businesses have cooperated with each other.",
      "Japanese citizens save less of their incomes than the citizens of other industrialized nation do."
    ],
    "answer": "The Japanese government and Japanese businesses have cooperated with each other."
  },
  {
    "id": 732,
    "question": "The emergence of Japan as a world economic power has been based mostly on Japan s",
    "option": [
      "development of nuclear power",
      "abundance of fossil fuels",
      "strong traditional of military rule",
      "business enterprise and organization"
    ],
    "answer": "business enterprise and organization"
  },
  {
    "id": 733,
    "question": "In recent years, which factor has been a major reason for the economic tensions between the United States and Japan?",
    "option": [
      "Japan s trade deficit with the United States was very high",
      "the United States refused to place quotas on Japanese goods",
      "the United States imported more from Japan than it exported to Japan",
      "Japan lowered tariffs on goods imported from the United States"
    ],
    "answer": "the United States imported more from Japan than it exported to Japan"
  },
  {
    "id": 734,
    "question": "Since World War II, people in both Africa and Latin America have moved from rural to urban areas.  The major cause of this movement has been the",
    "option": [
      "rejection of traditional custom",
      "expectation of improved economic opportunities",
      "guarantee of better housing",
      "fear of civil war"
    ],
    "answer": "expectation of improved economic opportunities"
  },
  {
    "id": 735,
    "question": "Which factor best accounts for the existence of cash-crop production as a major form of agriculture in many Central American nations today?",
    "option": [
      "demand of world markets for such crops",
      "lack of modern agricultural technology",
      "inadequate supply of water and other natural resources",
      "peasant ownership of most farmlands"
    ],
    "answer": "demand of world markets for such crops"
  },
  {
    "id": 736,
    "question": "Economic development in Japan after World War II and in Communist China since the 1980 s is similar in that both nations have sought to",
    "option": [
      "end foreign investment",
      "develop their vast natural resources to achieve economic growth",
      "utilize the concepts of capitalism to improve their economies",
      "nationalize most major industries and restrict competition"
    ],
    "answer": "nationalize most major industries and restrict competition"
  },
  {
    "id": 737,
    "question": "During the 1980 s and 1990 s, the economic policies of China, supported by Deng Xiaoping, have led directly to",
    "option": [
      "an expansion of China s colonial empire",
      "an increase in trade with the West",
      "a return to a strict command economy",
      "the success of the commune system"
    ],
    "answer": "an increase in trade with the West"
  },
  {
    "id": 738,
    "question": "Which statement best explains China s economic shift toward capitalism in the 1980 s and early 1990 s?",
    "option": [
      "China s economic policies were directly influenced by the success of the Soviet economic system",
      "the Tiananmen Square massacre resulted in major economic reforms in China",
      "the success of the Cultural Revolution resulted in the increased westernization of China",
      "communist economic policies were not meeting the needs of the society"
    ],
    "answer": "communist economic policies were not meeting the needs of the society"
  },
  {
    "id": 739,
    "question": "One principle in the theory of mercantilism is that colonies should be",
    "option": [
      "granted independence as soon as possible",
      "considered an economic burden for the colonial power",
      "encouraged to develop their own industries",
      "acquired as markets and sources of raw materials"
    ],
    "answer": "acquired as markets and sources of raw materials"
  },
  {
    "id": 740,
    "question": "Which statement best describes how a command economy functioned in the Soviet Union?",
    "option": [
      "The laws of supply and demand controlled the economy.",
      "Trade policies mandated that imports exceed exports.",
      "The success of the agricultural sector controlled the price of manufactured goods.",
      "A central authority determined the type and quantity of goods to be produced."
    ],
    "answer": "A central authority determined the type and quantity of goods to be produced."
  },
  {
    "id": 741,
    "question": "To maintain its economic position, Japan has often limited the number of cars or the quantity of farm products that the United States can sell in Japan. Japan has imposed these limits to develop",
    "option": [
      "an equality-of-trade position",
      "a favorable balance of trade",
      "a more open market",
      "a belief system"
    ],
    "answer": "a favorable balance of trade"
  },
  {
    "id": 742,
    "question": "The economic policy of mercantilism first developed during the",
    "option": [
      "Age of Exploration",
      "Enlightenment",
      "Cold War",
      "Green Revolution"
    ],
    "answer": "Age of Exploration"
  },
  {
    "id": 743,
    "question": "Statement A:   The might of a country consists of gaining surpluses of gold and silver.",
    "option": ["traditional", "feudal", "command", "mercantile"],
    "answer": "mercantile"
  },
  {
    "id": 744,
    "question": "Which generalization about democracy is most valid?",
    "option": [
      "democratic political systems require a highly industrialized society",
      "democratic governments first evolved in North America",
      "democratic governments prevent their citizens from traveling abroad",
      "democratic governments protect basic civil liberties"
    ],
    "answer": "democratic governments protect basic civil liberties"
  },
  {
    "id": 745,
    "question": "Which factor is necessary for the development of democratic institutions?",
    "option": [
      "strong military forces",
      "respect for individual rights",
      "a one-party system",
      "an agricultural economy"
    ],
    "answer": "respect for individual rights"
  },
  {
    "id": 746,
    "question": "Power tends to corrupt; absolute power corrupts absolutely.",
    "option": [
      "dictatorship",
      "absolute monarchy",
      "totalitarian state",
      "representative democracy"
    ],
    "answer": "representative democracy"
  },
  {
    "id": 747,
    "question": "Democracy in modern Japan resulted primarily from",
    "option": [
      "Shinto and Buddhist beliefs about equality and justice",
      "reforms imposed by the United States after World War II",
      "a history of imperial justice under the constitution of the Emperor",
      "the diffusion of ideas and practices from China and Korea"
    ],
    "answer": "reforms imposed by the United States after World War II"
  },
  {
    "id": 748,
    "question": "After the breakup of the Austro-Hungarian Empire and the Soviet Union, new nations were formed.  Which generalization accurately reflects the effect of the breakup on these new nations?",
    "option": [
      "new nations are generally too poor and weak to become active members of the United Nations",
      "new nations rarely use their limited resources to wage war",
      "national and ethnic differences often lead to instability and violence in new nations",
      "self-determination generally leads to democratic forms of government in new nations"
    ],
    "answer": "national and ethnic differences often lead to instability and violence in new nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 749,
    "question": "Which statement describes a characteristic of the British parliamentary system today?",
    "option": [
      "the Prime Minister is elected by the majority party in Parliament",
      "the monarch serves as a strong head of state",
      "the members of the House of Commons are appointed for life",
      "the minority party has no vote in the Parliament"
    ],
    "answer": "the Prime Minister is elected by the majority party in Parliament"
  },
  {
    "id": 750,
    "question": "Which political system is the basis of Japan s government today?",
    "option": [
      "parliamentary democracy",
      "military dictatorship",
      "absolute monarchy",
      "national socialism"
    ],
    "answer": "parliamentary democracy"
  },
  {
    "id": 751,
    "question": "A constitution? What for? The Koran is the oldest and most efficient constitution in the world.   --King Faisal of Saudi Arabia (1966)",
    "option": [
      "the laws of Islam can be used to govern a country",
      "every country needs elected leaders",
      "Muslims believe in a weak central government",
      "religion should be separated from government"
    ],
    "answer": "the laws of Islam can be used to govern a country"
  },
  {
    "id": 752,
    "question": "Cavour Provokes War Against Austria    Mazzini Establishes Young Italy",
    "option": ["nationalism", "isolationism", "imperialism", "totalitarianism"],
    "answer": "nationalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 753,
    "question": "What did Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels believe would be the result when communism finally emerged as the dominant political and economic system?",
    "option": [
      "Only two classes would exist in society.",
      "All the evils of industrial society would disappear.",
      "The Soviet Union would become the world s only superpower.",
      "Citizens would own their individual homes and farms."
    ],
    "answer": "All the evils of industrial society would disappear."
  },
  {
    "id": 754,
    "question": "A similarity of the rule of the ancient Mongols and the ancient Greeks is that both",
    "option": [
      "protected the human rights of the peoples they controlled",
      "destroyed the civilizations they defeated",
      "remained isolated and peaceful for centuries",
      "established vast empires and spread their cultures to the people they conquered"
    ],
    "answer": "established vast empires and spread their cultures to the people they conquered"
  },
  {
    "id": 755,
    "question": "The code of Hammurabi is an example of",
    "option": [
      "written rules for legal procedures",
      "the power of strong kings to control trade",
      "regulations on the way to conduct wars against neighboring nations",
      "the power of a legislature to veto laws passed by absolute monarchs"
    ],
    "answer": "written rules for legal procedures"
  },
  {
    "id": 756,
    "question": ". . . suspending laws . . . , by regal [royal] authority without consent of Parliament is illegal.",
    "option": [
      "limited monarchy",
      "dynastic rule",
      "totalitarian",
      "theocracy"
    ],
    "answer": "limited monarchy"
  },
  {
    "id": 757,
    "question": "The Magna Carta, the Glorious Revolution, and the writings of John Locke all contributed to Great Britain s development of",
    "option": [
      "absolute monarchy",
      "ethnic rivalries",
      "parliamentary democracy",
      "imperialist policies"
    ],
    "answer": "parliamentary democracy"
  },
  {
    "id": 758,
    "question": "In the Soviet Union, Joseph Stalin governed by means of secret police, censorship, and purges.",
    "option": ["democracy", "totalitarian", "limited monarchy", "theocracy"],
    "answer": "totalitarian"
  },
  {
    "id": 759,
    "question": "Speaker A:   The gods approached Vishnu, the lord of creatures, and said:  Indicate to us that one person among mortals who alone is worthy of the highest rank . . .  Vishnu reflected, and brought forth a glorious son who became the first king.",
    "option": ["A and D", "B and C", "A and C", "B and D"],
    "answer": "A and D"
  },
  {
    "id": 760,
    "question": "Which aspect of a nation s culture is most directly influenced by the physical geography of that nation?",
    "option": [
      "form of government",
      "religious beliefs",
      "population distribution",
      "social class system"
    ],
    "answer": "population distribution"
  },
  {
    "id": 761,
    "question": "One reason the cultures of North Africa developed differently from the cultures of the rest of Africa was that these areas of Africa were separated by the",
    "option": [
      "Congo River Basin",
      "Great Rift Valley",
      "Sahara Desert",
      "Arabian Sea"
    ],
    "answer": "Sahara Desert"
  },
  {
    "id": 762,
    "question": "In China, the development of ethnocentrism was most influenced by",
    "option": [
      "its historic reliance on foreign nations",
      "a long history of democratic government",
      "a strong belief in Christianity",
      "its geographic isolation"
    ],
    "answer": "its geographic isolation"
  },
  {
    "id": 763,
    "question": "In most societies, works of art and architecture generally serve to",
    "option": [
      "satisfy the needs of the leaders",
      "limit the influence of religion",
      "reflect the values of that society",
      "express opposition to the government in power"
    ],
    "answer": "reflect the values of that society"
  },
  {
    "id": 764,
    "question": "In modern African nations, the continued strength of the tribe or ethnic group is a reflection of the continuing influence of",
    "option": [
      "European imperialism",
      "urban growth",
      "the slave trade",
      "traditional cultures"
    ],
    "answer": "traditional cultures"
  },
  {
    "id": 765,
    "question": "Traditional African art has had the greatest influence on",
    "option": [
      "classical Roman mosaics and pottery",
      "Renaissance painting",
      "20th century sculpture and painting",
      "Medieval European architecture"
    ],
    "answer": "20th century sculpture and painting"
  },
  {
    "id": 766,
    "question": "Which generalization is characteristic of most traditional societies?",
    "option": [
      "people move from city to city seeking new jobs",
      "sons learn the same trades as their fathers",
      "a high degree of social mobility exists",
      "all people have the same economic opportunities"
    ],
    "answer": "sons learn the same trades as their fathers"
  },
  {
    "id": 767,
    "question": "Recent archeological studies suggest the theory that",
    "option": [
      "the earliest humans evolved in the Rift Valley in Africa",
      "farming societies developed before hunting and gathering societies",
      "all the continents were settled at about the same time",
      "the wheel was used by all ancient societies"
    ],
    "answer": "the earliest humans evolved in the Rift Valley in Africa"
  },
  {
    "id": 768,
    "question": "Which factor has contributed most to the social and cultural identity of the Middle East?",
    "option": [
      "political stability of the region",
      "ability of the region to export oil",
      "lack of foreign involvement in the region",
      "strong influence of Islam on the region"
    ],
    "answer": "strong influence of Islam on the region"
  },
  {
    "id": 769,
    "question": "The Chinese called their land  Middle Kingdom.   Europeans often used the term  backward  to refer to China.  These statements best illustrate",
    "option": [
      "the failure of geographers to establish a universal terminology",
      "the importance of East Asia in world history",
      "the adoption of policies of nonalignment",
      "attitudes of ethnocentrism in both cultures"
    ],
    "answer": "attitudes of ethnocentrism in both cultures"
  },
  {
    "id": 770,
    "question": "Geographic isolation of a people frequently reinforces",
    "option": [
      "a traditional way of life",
      "the development of scientific investigation",
      "the need for higher education",
      "a process of cultural diffusion"
    ],
    "answer": "a traditional way of life"
  },
  {
    "id": 771,
    "question": "In  most societies, urbanization has",
    "option": [
      "weakened traditional values and life patterns",
      "strengthened the influence of the extended family system",
      "discouraged economic growth",
      "promoted population growth"
    ],
    "answer": "weakened traditional values and life patterns"
  },
  {
    "id": 772,
    "question": "Which statement cites an example of cultural diffusion?",
    "option": [
      "Venezuela has large reserves of oil",
      "young people dance to rock music in Russia",
      "students in China learn calligraphy in school",
      "the Caste system is an important part of life in India"
    ],
    "answer": "young people dance to rock music in Russia"
  },
  {
    "id": 773,
    "question": "In most traditional societies, the teaching of values is mainly the responsibility of the",
    "option": ["judicial system", "government", "educational system", "family"],
    "answer": "family"
  },
  {
    "id": 774,
    "question": "The study of culture primarily involves",
    "option": [
      "observing the physical environment of people",
      "learning why various peoples live as they do",
      "understanding the technology of modern machinery",
      "analyzing the personalities of children in the same family"
    ],
    "answer": "learning why various peoples live as they do"
  },
  {
    "id": 775,
    "question": "Extended families and limited social mobility are characteristic of",
    "option": [
      "constitutional monarchies",
      "polytheistic religions",
      "traditional societies",
      "socialist economies"
    ],
    "answer": "traditional societies"
  },
  {
    "id": 776,
    "question": "People in both Japan and India eat very little meat.  A study of these cultures would show that",
    "option": [
      "although these cultures have similar practices, the reasons for these practices differ",
      "the raising of cattle in both nations is very difficult due to the extreme climate",
      "neither culture is concerned with health issues",
      "the governments of both nations enforce strict dietary laws"
    ],
    "answer": "although these cultures have similar practices, the reasons for these practices differ"
  },
  {
    "id": 777,
    "question": "The dominance of the Spanish language in Latin America and continued use of the French language in Senegal are examples of",
    "option": ["cultural diffusion", "social mobility", "humanism", "Marxism"],
    "answer": "cultural diffusion"
  },
  {
    "id": 778,
    "question": "Which activity is the best example of cultural diffusion in Africa?",
    "option": [
      "weaving kente cloth in Ghana",
      "using masks in traditional African ceremonies",
      "discovering bronze sculptures from Benin",
      "practicing of Islam in Nigeria"
    ],
    "answer": "practicing of Islam in Nigeria"
  },
  {
    "id": 779,
    "question": "Which statement about India is a fact rather than an opinion?",
    "option": [
      "most Indians are happy with the Hindu practice of arranged marriages",
      "India is fortunate to have a multiparty system of government",
      "The Mongols ruled India for more that 100 years",
      "the partition of British India in 1947 helped India prosper"
    ],
    "answer": "The Mongols ruled India for more that 100 years"
  },
  {
    "id": 780,
    "question": "Which reference would be used to find the most recent information about the gross domestic product (GDP) of a nation?",
    "option": ["historical atlas", "thesaurus", "world almanac", "dictionary"],
    "answer": "world almanac"
  },
  {
    "id": 781,
    "question": "Culture is sometimes referred to as  a blueprint for living  because it",
    "option": [
      "flourished best in traditional societies",
      "includes all the things that contribute to a society s development",
      "is determined by genetics",
      "determines the types of jobs offered to the members of a society"
    ],
    "answer": "includes all the things that contribute to a society s development"
  },
  {
    "id": 782,
    "question": "In many African nations, a major result of migration from rural to urban areas has been",
    "option": [
      "a strengthening of traditional values",
      "a decline in employment opportunities for educated Africans",
      "a weakening of ancestral lines and kinship bonds",
      "increased agricultural productivity"
    ],
    "answer": "a weakening of ancestral lines and kinship bonds"
  },
  {
    "id": 783,
    "question": "Which statement about Japan is a fact rather than an opinion?",
    "option": [
      "Japanese family values have declined with modernization",
      "many of Japan s cultural traditions were borrowed from China",
      "rapid industrialization has caused few problems for the Japanese people",
      "traditional farming techniques in Japan were better than modern ones"
    ],
    "answer": "many of Japan s cultural traditions were borrowed from China"
  },
  {
    "id": 784,
    "question": "One similarity between the culture of traditional China under dynastic rule and the culture of modern China under communism is that both stress",
    "option": [
      "a state-supported religion",
      "loyalty to the authority of leaders",
      "the importance of a matriarchal society",
      "limits on population growth"
    ],
    "answer": "loyalty to the authority of leaders"
  },
  {
    "id": 785,
    "question": "The ancient Chinese expression  Middle Kingdom  and the European terms  Near East  and  Far East  best reflect",
    "option": [
      "the impact of the Enlightenment on global thinking",
      "an improved knowledge of world geography",
      "an objective view of the world s cultures",
      "the influence of ethnocentrism on geographic perspective"
    ],
    "answer": "the influence of ethnocentrism on geographic perspective"
  },
  {
    "id": 786,
    "question": "The accusations of witchcraft in 17th century England and the practice of foot-binding in 19th century China are examples of the",
    "option": [
      "discrimination against women in various cultures",
      "negative aspects of a matriarchal society",
      "gradual improvement of women s rights around the world",
      "respect give to mothers in traditional cultures"
    ],
    "answer": "discrimination against women in various cultures"
  },
  {
    "id": 787,
    "question": "Buildings such as the Gothic cathedrals in Western Europe and the Parthenon in ancient Greece reflect each society s",
    "option": [
      "imperialistic attitudes",
      "cultural values",
      "belief in democracy",
      "rigid social structure"
    ],
    "answer": "cultural values"
  },
  {
    "id": 788,
    "question": "Before towns and cities can develop in a society, the society needs to establish",
    "option": [
      "an educational system",
      "an agricultural surplus",
      "a writing system",
      "a democratic government"
    ],
    "answer": "an agricultural surplus"
  },
  {
    "id": 789,
    "question": "Which statement best supports the idea that cultural diffusion has greatly affected Southeast Asia?",
    "option": [
      "the population of Southeast Asia is concentrated in rural areas",
      "monsoon climates affect food production in Indonesia",
      "a reliance on subsistence agriculture remains a problem for many Southeast Asian economies",
      "Buddhism, Hinduism, and Islam are practiced throughout Southeast Asia"
    ],
    "answer": "Buddhism, Hinduism, and Islam are practiced throughout Southeast Asia"
  },
  {
    "id": 790,
    "question": "In India, which aspect of society has been most heavily influenced by religious beliefs, tradition, and the division of labor?",
    "option": [
      "caste system",
      "policy of neutrality",
      "urbanization",
      "parliamentary government"
    ],
    "answer": "caste system"
  },
  {
    "id": 791,
    "question": "One similarity between the cultures of traditional China and traditional Japan was that",
    "option": [
      "the educated class was held in high esteem",
      "religion played a minor role in society",
      "social mobility was encouraged",
      "the people elected the political leaders"
    ],
    "answer": "the educated class was held in high esteem"
  },
  {
    "id": 792,
    "question": "The invention of writing systems and the growth of cities occurred only in civilizations that",
    "option": [
      "originated in south Asia",
      "developed matriarchal leadership",
      "developed complex institutions",
      "borrowed heavily from the Greeks and Romans"
    ],
    "answer": "developed complex institutions"
  },
  {
    "id": 793,
    "question": "A sociologist interested in Indian culture would most likely focus on the study of",
    "option": [
      "Hinduism and its influence on life in India",
      "India s development of nuclear weapons",
      "the parliamentary government of India",
      "the influence of agricultural production on India s Gross national Product (GNP)"
    ],
    "answer": "Hinduism and its influence on life in India"
  },
  {
    "id": 794,
    "question": "In India, the Caste System determined a person s occupation, personal associations, and marriage partner.  This situation shows that the Caste system",
    "option": [
      "has helped eliminate ethnic and religious rivalries",
      "has promoted social mobility within Indian society",
      "has been stronger in urban areas that in rural areas",
      "has been a way of life as well as an element of religion"
    ],
    "answer": "has been a way of life as well as an element of religion"
  },
  {
    "id": 795,
    "question": "During the centuries of dynastic rule, the Chinese rejected other cultures as inferior to their own.  This situation illustrates the concept of",
    "option": [
      "ethnocentrism",
      "imperialism",
      "social mobility",
      "cultural diffusion"
    ],
    "answer": "ethnocentrism"
  },
  {
    "id": 796,
    "question": "Which statement best describes the status of women in most traditional Asian societies?",
    "option": [
      "women were encouraged to obtain an education",
      "women were expected to run for political office",
      "women were expected to dedicate their lives to their families",
      "women were encouraged to work outside the home"
    ],
    "answer": "women were expected to dedicate their lives to their families"
  },
  {
    "id": 797,
    "question": "One result of the Neolithic Revolution was",
    "option": [
      "an increase in the number of nomadic tribes",
      "a reliance on hunting and gathering for food",
      "the establishment of villages and the rise of governments",
      "a decrease in trade between cultural groups"
    ],
    "answer": "the establishment of villages and the rise of governments"
  },
  {
    "id": 798,
    "question": "The Japanese feudal system and the Hindu caste system are similar in that both systems",
    "option": [
      "promoted social mobility",
      "developed a rigid class structure",
      "encouraged the people to take part in government",
      "resulted in economic opportunities for the lower classes"
    ],
    "answer": "developed a rigid class structure"
  },
  {
    "id": 799,
    "question": "Which situation best illustrates a traditional practice of women in Masai society?",
    "option": [
      "a young woman leaving her village to attend a university in the capital city",
      "an educated woman returning to her village to become leader of her tribe",
      "a young woman marrying and her husband giving cattle to her family as a wedding gift",
      "a young mother discouraging her children from practicing animism"
    ],
    "answer": "a young woman marrying and her husband giving cattle to her family as a wedding gift"
  },
  {
    "id": 800,
    "question": "The Japanese feudal system and the Hindu caste system are similar in that both systems",
    "option": [
      "promoted social mobility",
      "developed a rigid class structure",
      "encouraged the people to take part in government",
      "resulted in economic opportunities for the lower classes"
    ],
    "answer": "developed a rigid class structure"
  },
  {
    "id": 801,
    "question": "Which statement concerning modern Japan is most accurate?",
    "option": [
      "Japan has modernized while maintaining some elements of its traditional culture",
      "Japan has become a leader in global peacekeeping efforts",
      "Japan has shown little concern for its natural environment",
      "Japan has severed all traditional ties in favor of western values"
    ],
    "answer": "Japan has modernized while maintaining some elements of its traditional culture"
  },
  {
    "id": 802,
    "question": "The introduction of Buddhism into China and of Islam into Indonesia are examples of",
    "option": [
      "social mobility",
      "cultural diffusion",
      "ethnocentrism",
      "interdependence"
    ],
    "answer": "cultural diffusion"
  },
  {
    "id": 803,
    "question": "In a traditional society, the influence of an extended family decreases when that society is",
    "option": [
      "being governed by a council of elders",
      "experiencing rapid urbanization and industrialization",
      "faced with a decreasing population",
      "raising only enough crops to feed its people"
    ],
    "answer": "experiencing rapid urbanization and industrialization"
  },
  {
    "id": 804,
    "question": "Which factor has been most responsible for the common culture found in Japan?",
    "option": [
      "religious diversity",
      "success of democracy",
      "ethnic homogeneity",
      "political instability"
    ],
    "answer": "ethnic homogeneity"
  },
  {
    "id": 805,
    "question": "From a little spark may burst a mighty flame.   --Dante",
    "option": [
      "All cultures are concerned with transportation and conservation.",
      "In all cultures, people make excuses for their mistakes.",
      "Geography is important to the development of all cultures.",
      "People from different cultures often view situations in similar ways."
    ],
    "answer": "People from different cultures often view situations in similar ways."
  },
  {
    "id": 806,
    "question": "The Church of the Holy Sepulchre, the Dome of the Rock, and the Western (Wailing) Wall are religious sites in Jerusalem. These sites symbolize the",
    "option": [
      "Roman domination of the Mediterranean region in the 1st century",
      "cultural diversity of the Middle East",
      "limited architectural skills of builders in the Middle East",
      "geographic isolation of the city"
    ],
    "answer": "cultural diversity of the Middle East"
  },
  {
    "id": 807,
    "question": "Throughout much of history, both China and Japan held a common view that other nations were",
    "option": [
      "valued sources of worthwhile knowledge",
      "envoys of an advanced civilization",
      "barbarians not worthy of their attention",
      "sources of cheap labor and goods"
    ],
    "answer": "barbarians not worthy of their attention"
  },
  {
    "id": 808,
    "question": "Historians are interested in studying Maya ruins in Mexico, the haiku poetry of Japan, and the music of Chopin because such cultural and intellectual developments",
    "option": [
      "reflect the values of that society",
      "illustrate the economic status of individuals in that society",
      "help to explain the role of geography in that society",
      "reveal the political structure of that society"
    ],
    "answer": "reflect the values of that society"
  },
  {
    "id": 809,
    "question": "Which term is used to describe the spread of Buddhism from India through Southeast Asia?",
    "option": [
      "ethnocentrism",
      "isolation",
      "imperialism",
      "cultural diffusion"
    ],
    "answer": "cultural diffusion"
  },
  {
    "id": 810,
    "question": "One reason for the development of an early civilization in the Tigris-Euphrates river valleys was that",
    "option": [
      "the location protected the people from land invasion",
      "periodic flooding left rich soil, which was ideal for farming",
      "these rivers provided a direct trade route between Europe and Asia",
      "these rivers flowed into the Mediterranean Sea"
    ],
    "answer": "periodic flooding left rich soil, which was ideal for farming"
  },
  {
    "id": 811,
    "question": "Which characteristic did the early civilizations that developed along the Nile, the Tigris-Euphrates and the Huang He (Yellow River) have in common?",
    "option": [
      "each society s religious beliefs were based on monotheism",
      "urban communities were built using iron and steel tools",
      "the form of government in each community was based on male suffrage",
      "transportation and communication were promoted by a mild climate, fertile soil, and natural waterways"
    ],
    "answer": "transportation and communication were promoted by a mild climate, fertile soil, and natural waterways"
  },
  {
    "id": 812,
    "question": "The early civilizations of the Nile River Valley, Mesopotamia, and the Yellow River Valley were similar because they were",
    "option": [
      "industrialized societies",
      "monotheistic",
      "dependent on fertile land",
      "dependent on each other for trade"
    ],
    "answer": "dependent on fertile land"
  },
  {
    "id": 813,
    "question": "One way in which the civilizations of the Sumerians, the Phoenicians, and the Maya were similar is that each",
    "option": [
      "developed extensive writing systems",
      "emphasized equality in education",
      "established monotheistic religions",
      "encouraged democratic participation in government"
    ],
    "answer": "developed extensive writing systems"
  },
  {
    "id": 814,
    "question": "If a seignior (noble) has knocked out the tooth of a seignior of his own rank, they shall knock out his tooth.  But if he has knocked out a commoner s tooth, he shall pay one-third mina of silver.   -Code of Hammurabi",
    "option": [
      "all men were equal under the law",
      "fines were preferable to corporal punishment",
      "divisions existed between social classes",
      "violence was always punished with violence"
    ],
    "answer": "divisions existed between social classes"
  },
  {
    "id": 815,
    "question": "The ancient civilizations of Mesopotamia and Egypt were similar in that both cultures",
    "option": [
      "developed along rivers",
      "used the ziggurat form for their temples",
      "established trade routes to China",
      "used a hieroglyphic writing system"
    ],
    "answer": "developed along rivers"
  },
  {
    "id": 816,
    "question": "Notre Dame Cathedral in Paris, the Dome of the Rock in Jerusalem and the Great Pyramid in Egypt are examples of",
    "option": [
      "architectural accomplishments that reflect religious beliefs",
      "the influence of Buddhist architecture on conquered nations",
      "ancient architectural monuments no longer in use",
      "the influence of cultural diffusion on contemporary architecture"
    ],
    "answer": "architectural accomplishments that reflect religious beliefs"
  },
  {
    "id": 817,
    "question": "Judaism, Islam, and Christianity share a belief in",
    "option": [
      "the central authority of the Pope",
      "a prohibition of the consumption of port",
      "reincarnation and the Four Noble Truths",
      "monotheism and ethical conduct"
    ],
    "answer": "monotheism and ethical conduct"
  },
  {
    "id": 818,
    "question": "Which is a valid statement about the history of South Asia?",
    "option": [
      "Religious beliefs have both unified and divided the people of the region.",
      "Little cultural diffusion has occurred in this region.",
      "Urbanization has strengthened the traditional beliefs and lifestyles of the people of the region.",
      "Superpower involvement has brought peace and economic prosperity to the region."
    ],
    "answer": "Religious beliefs have both unified and divided the people of the region."
  },
  {
    "id": 819,
    "question": "When I go to the office, I put on my shirt and I take off my caste; when I come home, I take off my shirt and I put on my caste.",
    "option": [
      "the caste system continues to influence Indian society",
      "the caste system has been reflected by most Indians",
      "successful urban workers in India belong the same Caste",
      "the Indian government officially supports the Caste system"
    ],
    "answer": "the caste system continues to influence Indian society"
  },
  {
    "id": 820,
    "question": "According the teachings of Confucius, the key to the successful organization of society is that",
    "option": [
      "the ruler should be chosen democratically",
      "the evil in humans must be eliminated",
      "ancestor worship should be discontinued",
      "individuals should know and do what is expected of them"
    ],
    "answer": "individuals should know and do what is expected of them"
  },
  {
    "id": 821,
    "question": "In traditional Chinese culture, which philosophy had the greatest influence on the development of social order and political organization?",
    "option": ["Taoism", "Shintoism", "Confucianism", "Marxism"],
    "answer": "Confucianism"
  },
  {
    "id": 822,
    "question": "The teachings of Confucius encouraged people to",
    "option": [
      "put their own interests first",
      "reject government authority",
      "believe in reincarnation",
      "follow a code of moral conduct"
    ],
    "answer": "follow a code of moral conduct"
  },
  {
    "id": 823,
    "question": "In Japan, the martial arts, the tea ceremony, and flower arranging best reflect the influences of",
    "option": [
      "imperialism and militarism",
      "Buddhism and Shintoism",
      "capitalism",
      "mercantilism"
    ],
    "answer": "Buddhism and Shintoism"
  },
  {
    "id": 824,
    "question": "A person who practices the Shinto faith would be most likely to",
    "option": [
      "visit a shrine placed on the shore of a lake",
      "pray five times a day",
      "bathe in the Ganges River",
      "make a pilgrimage to Jerusalem"
    ],
    "answer": "visit a shrine placed on the shore of a lake"
  },
  {
    "id": 825,
    "question": "Taoism and Shintoism are similar in that both religions stress",
    "option": [
      "adhering to the five Confucian relationships",
      "following the Eightfold Path",
      "developing harmony between humans and nature",
      "believing in one God"
    ],
    "answer": "developing harmony between humans and nature"
  },
  {
    "id": 826,
    "question": "One similarity between the Five Pillars of Islam and the Ten Commandments is that both",
    "option": [
      "support a belief in reincarnation",
      "promote learning as a means to salvation",
      "encourage the use of statues to symbolize God",
      "provide a guide to proper ethical and moral behavior"
    ],
    "answer": "provide a guide to proper ethical and moral behavior"
  },
  {
    "id": 827,
    "question": "One way in which Eastern Orthodoxy, Roman Catholicism, and Protestantism are similar is that each",
    "option": [
      "accepts the supreme authority of the Pope",
      "rejects the Old Testament as part of the Bible",
      "is a branch of Christianity",
      "was once the official religion of the Byzantine Empire"
    ],
    "answer": "is a branch of Christianity"
  },
  {
    "id": 828,
    "question": "The Koran, jihad, and the hegira are most closely associated with the practice of",
    "option": ["Islam", "Judaism", "Shinto", "Buddhism"],
    "answer": "Islam"
  },
  {
    "id": 829,
    "question": "The Buddhist religion teaches that salvation is earned by",
    "option": [
      "following the Ten Commandments",
      "worshiping Allah as the one true god",
      "learning to give up selfish desire",
      "being baptized and confirmed"
    ],
    "answer": "learning to give up selfish desire"
  },
  {
    "id": 830,
    "question": "Confucianism in traditional China served to",
    "option": [
      "maintain social order",
      "create ethnic unrest",
      "emphasize material wealth",
      "support democratic government"
    ],
    "answer": "maintain social order"
  },
  {
    "id": 831,
    "question": "Traditional animistic beliefs in Africa, Asia, and Latin America are based on",
    "option": [
      "a desire for wealth",
      "a written tradition",
      "an appreciation for the forces of nature",
      "a willingness to accept Christianity"
    ],
    "answer": "an appreciation for the forces of nature"
  },
  {
    "id": 832,
    "question": "Jewish religions and cultural identity has been greatly influenced by",
    "option": [
      "Ramadan and the concept of reincarnation",
      "the Torah and the Diaspora",
      "the New Testament and the Four Noble Truths",
      "the Koran and the code of bushido"
    ],
    "answer": "the Torah and the Diaspora"
  },
  {
    "id": 833,
    "question": "In India, the Caste system determined a person s occupation, personal associations, and marriage partner.  This situation shows that the Caste system",
    "option": [
      "has helped eliminate ethnic and religious rivalries",
      "has promoted social mobility within Indian society",
      "has been stronger in urban areas that in rural areas",
      "has been a way of life as well as an element of religion"
    ],
    "answer": "has been a way of life as well as an element of religion"
  },
  {
    "id": 834,
    "question": "Mansa Musa s journey to Mecca in the 1300 s is evidence that",
    "option": [
      "the Crusades had a great influence on western Africa",
      "most African leaders were educated in the Middle East",
      "European culture was superior to the cultures of western Africa",
      "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire"
    ],
    "answer": "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire"
  },
  {
    "id": 835,
    "question": "From as early as I can remember, the Emperor was an important presence even in our remote home.  He was a descendant of the gods from thousands of years before, never to be looked at or listened to by mere mortals, a presence to be revered and protected and obeyed Finally , my family and neighbors gathered around the radio and listened in stunned silence to the voice that had never before been heard, saying he was only human after all.  Everyone was crying.  I was sad and confused",
    "option": ["Shintoism", "Christianity", "Islam", "Judaism"],
    "answer": "Shintoism"
  },
  {
    "id": 836,
    "question": "Beginning with childhood, all of man s study is centered on one aim alone   to emerge successfully from the three days  examination   and all he has in his mind is what success can bring to him in terms of power, influence, and prestige.",
    "option": [
      "civil service system",
      "social welfare system",
      "contemplation of nature",
      "religious practices"
    ],
    "answer": "civil service system"
  },
  {
    "id": 837,
    "question": "The Eightfold Path, the Four Noble Truths, and the concept of nirvana are associated with the religion of",
    "option": ["Islam", "Jainism", "Shinto", "Buddhism"],
    "answer": "Buddhism"
  },
  {
    "id": 838,
    "question": "One way in which the Vedas, the Bible, and the Koran are similar is that these religious books",
    "option": [
      "provide guidelines to govern the behavior of believers",
      "deny the existence of a supreme being who rules the universe",
      "encourage strife between segments of believers",
      "support political rebellions to overthrow existing governments"
    ],
    "answer": "provide guidelines to govern the behavior of believers"
  },
  {
    "id": 839,
    "question": "Which values are most closely associated with the fundamental principles of Buddhism?",
    "option": [
      "competition and financial success",
      "maintaining the caste system and providing education for all people",
      "practicing nonviolence and giving up worldly desires",
      "self-determination and democracy"
    ],
    "answer": "practicing nonviolence and giving up worldly desires"
  },
  {
    "id": 840,
    "question": "A belief of animism is that",
    "option": [
      "after death the soul is reborn in another human form",
      "holy wars must be fought to gain entry into heaven",
      "meditation leads followers to nirvana",
      "spirits of nature inhabit all living and nonliving objects"
    ],
    "answer": "spirits of nature inhabit all living and nonliving objects"
  },
  {
    "id": 841,
    "question": "The Analects :    In his [the leader] personal conduct, he was respectful.",
    "option": ["anarchy", "law", "trade", "architecture"],
    "answer": "law"
  },
  {
    "id": 842,
    "question": "A major impact of Ancient Greece and Rome on Western Civilization was that",
    "option": [
      "the Greeks and Romans succeeded in achieving a classless society, which was later copied in Western Europe",
      "Greek sculpture and Roman architecture were much admired and copied in the 18th and 19th centuries",
      "Greece and Rome transmitted Islamic philosophy to the areas they conquered",
      "Greek and Latin are still widely spoken in universities throughout the West"
    ],
    "answer": "Greek sculpture and Roman architecture were much admired and copied in the 18th and 19th centuries"
  },
  {
    "id": 843,
    "question": "The Ancient Romans  most significant contribution to Europe has been in the area of",
    "option": ["economics", "poetry", "drama", "law"],
    "answer": "law"
  },
  {
    "id": 844,
    "question": "An immediate result of the fall of the Roman Empire was",
    "option": [
      "a renewed interest in education and the arts",
      "a period of disorder and weak central government",
      "an increase in trade and manufacturing",
      "the growth of cities and dominance by the middle class"
    ],
    "answer": "a period of disorder and weak central government"
  },
  {
    "id": 845,
    "question": "The Ancient Athenians are credited with",
    "option": [
      "inventing and using the wheel",
      "eliminating slavery",
      "establishing governments that had democratic elements",
      "inventing the printing press"
    ],
    "answer": "establishing governments that had democratic elements"
  },
  {
    "id": 846,
    "question": "Both the Ancient Romans and the Ancient Chinese viewed foreigners as barbarians.  This is an example of",
    "option": [
      "cultural diffusion",
      "materialism",
      "imperialism",
      "ethnocentrism"
    ],
    "answer": "ethnocentrism"
  },
  {
    "id": 847,
    "question": "A major contribution of the Roman Republic to Western European culture was the",
    "option": [
      "concept of government by laws",
      "belief that political power should be controlled by the military",
      "establishment of agricultural communes",
      "rejection of the concept of slavery"
    ],
    "answer": "concept of government by laws"
  },
  {
    "id": 848,
    "question": "Which ancient civilization established the basis of western democracy?",
    "option": ["Phoenician", "Egyptian", "Sumerian", "Greek"],
    "answer": "Greek"
  },
  {
    "id": 849,
    "question": "The political system of the Ancient Roman Empire was characterized by",
    "option": [
      "a strong central government",
      "rule by a coalition of emperors and religious leaders",
      "universal suffrage in national elections",
      "a strict adherence to constitutional principles"
    ],
    "answer": "a strong central government"
  },
  {
    "id": 850,
    "question": "Which societal condition was basic to the development of Greek philosophy?",
    "option": [
      "rigid social classes",
      "emphasis on individualism",
      "religious uniformity",
      "mass education"
    ],
    "answer": "mass education"
  },
  {
    "id": 851,
    "question": "Important long-term contributions of Ancient Greek and Roman civilizations are primarily found in the area of",
    "option": [
      "military technology",
      "religious doctrine",
      "economic policy and planning",
      "government and law"
    ],
    "answer": "government and law"
  },
  {
    "id": 852,
    "question": "The Ancient Greek city-state of Sparta",
    "option": [
      "was primarily concerned with the health of their people",
      "was a powerful military state",
      "granted universal suffrage to their people",
      "placed great emphasis on literature and the arts"
    ],
    "answer": "was a powerful military state"
  },
  {
    "id": 853,
    "question": "An immediate result of the fall of the Roman Empire was",
    "option": [
      "a renewed interest in education and the arts",
      "a period of disorder and weak central government",
      "an increase in trade and manufacturing",
      "the growth of cities and dominance by the middle class"
    ],
    "answer": "a period of disorder and weak central government"
  },
  {
    "id": 854,
    "question": "Which societal condition was basic to the development of Greek philosophy and Renaissance art?",
    "option": [
      "rigid social classes",
      "emphasis on individualism",
      "religious uniformity",
      "mass education"
    ],
    "answer": "emphasis on individualism"
  },
  {
    "id": 855,
    "question": "An influence that spread from the Byzantine Empire to Early Russia was the",
    "option": [
      "Orthodox Christian religion",
      "use of the Latin alphabet",
      "beginning of democracy",
      "factory system"
    ],
    "answer": "Orthodox Christian religion"
  },
  {
    "id": 856,
    "question": "The adoption of the Eastern Orthodox religion and the Cyrillic alphabet by the Russian people occurred as a result of",
    "option": [
      "territorial expansion during the reign of Catherine the Great",
      "the westernization policies of Peter the Great",
      "contact with Byzantine culture in the 10th century",
      "the influence of the Crusaders during the Middle Ages"
    ],
    "answer": "contact with Byzantine culture in the 10th century"
  },
  {
    "id": 857,
    "question": "One similarity between Axum, Kush, and Nubia was that they were",
    "option": [
      "military leaders in the Neolithic Age",
      "rivers along which early trade developed",
      "writers of epic poems about Greek cities",
      "early civilizations in Africa"
    ],
    "answer": "early civilizations in Africa"
  },
  {
    "id": 858,
    "question": "One similarity between the decline of the Roman Empire and the fall of the Manchu Dynasty was that both initially led to",
    "option": [
      "improved economic conditions",
      "democratically elected governments",
      "political chaos and decentralization of government",
      "major accomplishments in art, science, and technology"
    ],
    "answer": "political chaos and decentralization of government"
  },
  {
    "id": 859,
    "question": "A major contribution of the Roman Empire to Western society was the development of",
    "option": [
      "gunpowder",
      "the principles of revolutionary socialism",
      "monotheism",
      "an effective legal system"
    ],
    "answer": "an effective legal system"
  },
  {
    "id": 860,
    "question": "After the fall of Rome, the eastern portion of the Roman Empire became known as the",
    "option": [
      "Persian Empire",
      "Byzantine Empire",
      "Mongol Empire",
      "Gupta Empire"
    ],
    "answer": "Byzantine Empire"
  },
  {
    "id": 861,
    "question": "Which conclusion can be drawn from a study of the early civilizations of Axum, Kush, Mali and Songhai?",
    "option": [
      "these African societies flourished at the same time",
      "farming was more extensive in the Nile River Valley than it was in the Fertile Crescent",
      "the Neolithic Revolution occurred in Africa",
      "these societies had a long and rich history before their first contact with Europeans"
    ],
    "answer": "these societies had a long and rich history before their first contact with Europeans"
  },
  {
    "id": 862,
    "question": "A major effect of the decline of the Roman Empire was that Western Europe",
    "option": [
      "came under the control of the Muslims",
      "was absorbed by the Byzantine Empire",
      "returned to a republican form of government",
      "entered a period of chaos and disorder"
    ],
    "answer": "entered a period of chaos and disorder"
  },
  {
    "id": 863,
    "question": "Which characteristic was common to the Golden Age of Greece and the Italian Renaissance?",
    "option": [
      "a strong military led to national unity",
      "written constitutions led to the establishment of democratic governments",
      "prosperity led to the creation of many works of art",
      "political instability led directly to the formation of unified nation-states"
    ],
    "answer": "prosperity led to the creation of many works of art"
  },
  {
    "id": 864,
    "question": "During the centuries of dynastic rule, the Chinese rejected other cultures as inferior to their own.  This situation illustrates the concept of",
    "option": [
      "ethnocentrism",
      "imperialism",
      "social mobility",
      "cultural diffusion"
    ],
    "answer": "ethnocentrism"
  },
  {
    "id": 865,
    "question": "Alexander the Great s conquests of Greece, Asia Minor, Egypt, and Persia led to the",
    "option": [
      "spread of Hellenic culture",
      "adoption of a feudal system",
      "establishment of representative democracy",
      "spread of Islamic culture throughout Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "spread of Hellenic culture"
  },
  {
    "id": 866,
    "question": "One similarity between the Ancient African kingdoms of Egypt, Ghana, Mali and Songhai is that all of these kingdoms were located",
    "option": [
      "in mountainous terrain",
      "in coastal areas",
      "on major trading routes",
      "in rain forest areas"
    ],
    "answer": "on major trading routes"
  },
  {
    "id": 867,
    "question": "One reason the ancient kingdoms in western Africa prospered was that they",
    "option": [
      "were located along the Tigris and Euphrates rivers",
      "had no contact with the rest of the world",
      "followed the Hindu beliefs of their rulers",
      "developed extensive trade in gold, ivory, and salt"
    ],
    "answer": "developed extensive trade in gold, ivory, and salt"
  },
  {
    "id": 868,
    "question": "Mansa Musa s journey to Mecca in the 1300 s is evidence that",
    "option": [
      "the Crusades had a great influence on western Africa",
      "most African leaders were educated in the Middle East",
      "European culture was superior to the cultures of western Africa",
      "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire"
    ],
    "answer": "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire"
  },
  {
    "id": 869,
    "question": "The contributions of the ancient civilizations of Ghana, Axum, Kush, and Mali demonstrate that",
    "option": [
      "industrial technology was needed for African civilizations to develop",
      "many African civilizations developed in southern Africa",
      "most of the African Continent was unified under a single political system",
      "advanced societies developed in Africa before Europeans colonized this region"
    ],
    "answer": "advanced societies developed in Africa before Europeans colonized this region"
  },
  {
    "id": 870,
    "question": "A similarity between the ancient western African kingdoms of Mali, Ghana, and Songhai is that these kingdoms",
    "option": [
      "limited the power of their rulers",
      "practiced Christianity",
      "established economies based on trade",
      "isolated themselves from contact with other cultures"
    ],
    "answer": "established economies based on trade"
  },
  {
    "id": 871,
    "question": "Western Europe owed a debt of gratitude to the Empire that for almost a thousand years ensured the survival of Christianity during a time when Europe was too weak to accomplish the task.",
    "option": ["Hellenistic", "Mongol", "Byzantine", "Ottoman"],
    "answer": "Byzantine"
  },
  {
    "id": 872,
    "question": "An influence that spread from the Byzantine Empire to Early Russia was the",
    "option": [
      "Orthodox Christian religion",
      "use of the Latin alphabet",
      "beginning of democracy",
      "factory system"
    ],
    "answer": "Orthodox Christian religion"
  },
  {
    "id": 873,
    "question": "Which empire introduced the Eastern Orthodox Church and the Cyrillic alphabet to Russia?",
    "option": ["Mongol", "Byzantine", "British", "Gupta"],
    "answer": "Byzantine"
  },
  {
    "id": 874,
    "question": "A major feature of the Golden Age of Moslem culture was the",
    "option": [
      "political and economic isolation of the Arab world",
      "development of the foundations of modern science and mathematics",
      "adoption of democratic government",
      "persecution of Jews and Christians"
    ],
    "answer": "development of the foundations of modern science and mathematics"
  },
  {
    "id": 875,
    "question": "Which factor helps explain the scientific and literary achievements of the Muslims during their Golden Age (A.D. 800-1300)?",
    "option": [
      "expansion of trans-Atlantic trade",
      "innovations introduced by the Europeans during the Renaissance",
      "cultural diversity accepted by many Islamic governments",
      "legal equality of all people in the Islamic empire"
    ],
    "answer": "cultural diversity accepted by many Islamic governments"
  },
  {
    "id": 876,
    "question": "Mansa Musa s journey to Mecca in the 1300 s is evidence that",
    "option": [
      "the Crusades had a great influence on western Africa",
      "most African leaders were educated in the Middle East",
      "European culture was superior to the cultures of western Africa",
      "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire"
    ],
    "answer": "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire"
  },
  {
    "id": 877,
    "question": "Which activity occurred during the Golden Age of Muslim culture?",
    "option": [
      "destruction of books containing Greek and Roman ideas",
      "beginning of pilgrimages to Mecca",
      "opposition to freedom of thought and to foreign ideas by rulers",
      "major discoveries in mathematics and science"
    ],
    "answer": "major discoveries in mathematics and science"
  },
  {
    "id": 878,
    "question": "The contributions of the Golden Age of Islamic civilization include",
    "option": [
      "advances in mathematics",
      "irrigation systems",
      "polytheistic beliefs",
      "gunpowder and guns"
    ],
    "answer": "advances in mathematics"
  },
  {
    "id": 879,
    "question": "In Europe during the Middle Ages, increases in trade and commerce resulted in",
    "option": [
      "lower living standards for industrial workers",
      "decreased economic rivalry between kings",
      "increased political power for the clergy",
      "development of towns and cities"
    ],
    "answer": "development of towns and cities"
  },
  {
    "id": 880,
    "question": "During the Middle Ages, Europeans did not eat potatoes or corn because these vegetables",
    "option": [
      "were forbidden by the Catholic Church for religious reasons",
      "had not yet been introduced to Europe from the New World",
      "were believed to be poisonous",
      "were too expensive to import from China"
    ],
    "answer": "had not yet been introduced to Europe from the New World"
  },
  {
    "id": 881,
    "question": "All things were under its domain...its power was such that no one could hope to escape its scrutiny.",
    "option": ["the Guild", "Knighthood", "the Church", "the nation-state"],
    "answer": "the Church"
  },
  {
    "id": 882,
    "question": "The Middle Ages in Western Europe was characterized by",
    "option": [
      "the manor system and the importance of land ownership",
      "absolute monarchies and strong central governments",
      "decreased emphasis on religion in daily life",
      "extensive trade with Asia and the Middle East"
    ],
    "answer": "the manor system and the importance of land ownership"
  },
  {
    "id": 883,
    "question": "Feudal societies are generally characterized by",
    "option": [
      "an emphasis on social order",
      "a representative government",
      "many economic opportunities",
      "the protection of political rights"
    ],
    "answer": "an emphasis on social order"
  },
  {
    "id": 884,
    "question": "In Europe, a long-term effect of the Crusades was",
    "option": [
      "the strengthening of the feudal system",
      "the adoption of Islamic religious practices",
      "an increased demand for goods from the East",
      "increased European isolation"
    ],
    "answer": "an increased demand for goods from the East"
  },
  {
    "id": 885,
    "question": "The art, music, and philosophy of the medieval period in Europe generally dealt with",
    "option": [
      "human scientific achievements",
      "religious themes",
      "materialism",
      "classic Greek and Roman subjects"
    ],
    "answer": "religious themes"
  },
  {
    "id": 886,
    "question": "Which statement best describes the result of the Crusades?",
    "option": [
      "Europeans maintained a lasting control over much of the Middle East",
      "Islamic influence dominated Europe",
      "Europeans developed tolerance of Non-Christian religions",
      "trade between Europe and the Middle East was expanded"
    ],
    "answer": "trade between Europe and the Middle East was expanded"
  },
  {
    "id": 887,
    "question": "What were two indirect results of the Crusades?",
    "option": [
      "trade and commerce increased and the feudal system was strengthened",
      "trade and commerce declined and the feudal system was strengthened",
      "trade and commerce increased and the feudal system was weakened",
      "trade and commerce declined and the feudal system was weakened"
    ],
    "answer": "trade and commerce increased and the feudal system was weakened"
  },
  {
    "id": 888,
    "question": "In Europe during the Middle Ages, the force that provided unification and stability was the",
    "option": [
      "central government in Rome",
      "military alliance between France and Germany",
      "federation of the craft guilds",
      "Roman Catholic Church"
    ],
    "answer": "Roman Catholic Church"
  },
  {
    "id": 889,
    "question": "Feudalism in Western Europe was similar to feudalism in Japan in that",
    "option": [
      "power was based on class relationships",
      "equality among the social classes",
      "direct democracy",
      "monotheism"
    ],
    "answer": "power was based on class relationships"
  },
  {
    "id": 890,
    "question": "Which is a characteristic of a feudal society?",
    "option": [
      "rapid social change",
      "high literacy rate",
      "industrial-based economy",
      "rigid class structure"
    ],
    "answer": "rigid class structure"
  },
  {
    "id": 891,
    "question": "In Europe, the Crusades resulted in",
    "option": [
      "greater isolation of the region from the world",
      "an increased demand for goods from the Middle East and Asia",
      "the adoption of Islam as the official religion of many European nations",
      "the strengthening of the feudal system"
    ],
    "answer": "an increased demand for goods from the Middle East and Asia"
  },
  {
    "id": 892,
    "question": "One important effect of the Crusades on Western Europe was that they",
    "option": [
      "led to a decline in the importance of the church in Western Europe",
      "furthered cultural diffusion throughout Western Europe",
      "introduced the Industrial Revolution to Western Europe",
      "ended the western European quest for an overseas empire"
    ],
    "answer": "furthered cultural diffusion throughout Western Europe"
  },
  {
    "id": 893,
    "question": "In European feudal society, an individual s social status was generally determined by",
    "option": [
      "birth",
      "education and training",
      "individual abilities",
      "marriage"
    ],
    "answer": "birth"
  },
  {
    "id": 894,
    "question": "Which economic system existed in Europe during the early Middle Ages?",
    "option": ["free market", "socialism", "manorialism", "command"],
    "answer": "manorialism"
  },
  {
    "id": 895,
    "question": "One major result of the Crusades was the",
    "option": [
      "permanent occupation of the Holy Land by the Europeans",
      "long-term decrease in European trade",
      "conversion of most Muslims to Christianity",
      "spread of Middle Eastern culture and technology to Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "spread of Middle Eastern culture and technology to Europe"
  },
  {
    "id": 896,
    "question": "The growth of feudalism in Europe during the Middle Ages was primarily caused by the",
    "option": [
      "rivalry between the colonial empires",
      "suppression of internationalism",
      "decline of the Roman Catholic Church",
      "collapse of a strong central government"
    ],
    "answer": "collapse of a strong central government"
  },
  {
    "id": 897,
    "question": "The Crusades have been called  history s most successful failures.     Which statement best explains this expression?",
    "option": [
      "The Crusades did not achieve their original goals, but they brought about many desirable changes in Europe.",
      "Although the Crusaders captured the Holy Land, they were unable to bring about democratic reforms.",
      "The Crusades helped bring about the fall of the Roman Empire",
      "The Crusaders prevented the Turks from capturing Constantinople for many centuries"
    ],
    "answer": "The Crusades did not achieve their original goals, but they brought about many desirable changes in Europe."
  },
  {
    "id": 898,
    "question": "The Roman Catholic Church during the Middle Ages in Europe can best be described as a church that",
    "option": [
      "favored separation from secular governments",
      "avoided involvement in social and educational matters",
      "was a strong force that divided many people",
      "was a stabilizing influence during a period of weak central governments"
    ],
    "answer": "was a stabilizing influence during a period of weak central governments"
  },
  {
    "id": 899,
    "question": "A major goal of the Christian Church during the Crusades (1096 1291) was to",
    "option": [
      "establish Christianity in western Europe",
      "capture the Holy Land from Islamic rulers",
      "unite warring Arab peoples",
      "strengthen English dominance in the Arab world"
    ],
    "answer": "capture the Holy Land from Islamic rulers"
  },
  {
    "id": 900,
    "question": "Korea greatly influenced the development of early Japan by",
    "option": [
      "acting as a bridge for ideas from China",
      "providing Japan with the technology for industrialization",
      "serving as a barrier against Chinese aggression",
      "protecting Japan from early European exploration"
    ],
    "answer": "acting as a bridge for ideas from China"
  },
  {
    "id": 901,
    "question": "In Japan between 1603 and 1868, the most notable action taken by the Tokugawa Shogunate was the",
    "option": [
      "military conquest of China",
      "development of extensive trade with the Americas",
      "formation of cultural links with Europe",
      "virtual isolation of the country from the outside world"
    ],
    "answer": "virtual isolation of the country from the outside world"
  },
  {
    "id": 902,
    "question": "The code of bushido of the Japanese samurai is most similar to",
    "option": [
      "belief in reincarnation and karma of Hindus",
      "practice of chivalry by European knights",
      "teachings of Judaism",
      "theory of natural rights of the Enlightenment writers"
    ],
    "answer": "practice of chivalry by European knights"
  },
  {
    "id": 903,
    "question": "Feudal societies are generally characterized by",
    "option": [
      "an emphasis on social order",
      "a representative government",
      "many economic opportunities",
      "the protection of political rights"
    ],
    "answer": "an emphasis on social order"
  },
  {
    "id": 904,
    "question": "Feudalism in Western Europe was similar to feudalism in Japan in that",
    "option": [
      "power was based on class relationships",
      "equality among the social classes",
      "direct democracy",
      "monotheism"
    ],
    "answer": "power was based on class relationships"
  },
  {
    "id": 905,
    "question": "Which is a characteristic of a feudal society?",
    "option": [
      "rapid social change",
      "high literacy rate",
      "industrial-based economy",
      "rigid class structure"
    ],
    "answer": "rigid class structure"
  },
  {
    "id": 906,
    "question": "The diagram illustrates the social structure of feudal Japan.",
    "option": [
      "a classless society",
      "a growing middle class",
      "high social mobility",
      "a well-defined class system"
    ],
    "answer": "a well-defined class system"
  },
  {
    "id": 907,
    "question": "A valid generalization about early Japanese culture is that Japan",
    "option": [
      "had a strong influence on the development of culture in Korea",
      "spread Shinto throughout Asia",
      "maintained a uniquely individual culture while borrowing much from other cultures",
      "imported almost all of its cultural ideas from China, resulting in nearly identical cultures"
    ],
    "answer": "maintained a uniquely individual culture while borrowing much from other cultures"
  },
  {
    "id": 908,
    "question": "The Mongols played a significant role in Russian history by",
    "option": [
      "supporting Czar Nicholas II during the Russian Revolution",
      "supporting the rule of Ivan the Terrible",
      "ending the reign of Catherine the Great",
      "isolating Russia from Western Europe during the early Renaissance"
    ],
    "answer": "isolating Russia from Western Europe during the early Renaissance"
  },
  {
    "id": 909,
    "question": "In Europe, a major characteristic of humanism was",
    "option": [
      "a belief in the supremacy of the state in relation to individual rights",
      "a rejection of ancient civilizations and their cultures",
      "an emphasis on social control and obedience to national rulers",
      "an appreciation for the basic worth of individual achievement"
    ],
    "answer": "an appreciation for the basic worth of individual achievement"
  },
  {
    "id": 910,
    "question": "Which statement best describes a characteristic of the Renaissance in Europe?",
    "option": [
      "the social structure became very rigid",
      "creativity in the arts was encouraged",
      "the political structure was similar to that of the Roman Empire",
      "humanism decreased in importance"
    ],
    "answer": "creativity in the arts was encouraged"
  },
  {
    "id": 911,
    "question": "Europe is waking out of a long, deep sleep time was when learning was only found in the religious orders learning has passed to secular princes and peers.",
    "option": [
      "Renaissance",
      "decline of the Roman Empire",
      "Crusades",
      "rise of Christianity"
    ],
    "answer": "Renaissance"
  },
  {
    "id": 912,
    "question": "Which was a major characteristic of the Renaissance?",
    "option": ["conformity", "humanism", "mysticism", "obedience"],
    "answer": "humanism"
  },
  {
    "id": 913,
    "question": "Which statement describes a direct effect of the Renaissance on Western Europe?",
    "option": [
      "the philosophy of humanism brought about a decrease in the power of the Roman Catholic Church",
      "art began to reflect an increased emphasis on religious themes",
      "nationalistic movements among the minority ethnic groups in the region declines",
      "the feudal system was developed to provide stability in a decentralized political structure"
    ],
    "answer": "the philosophy of humanism brought about a decrease in the power of the Roman Catholic Church"
  },
  {
    "id": 914,
    "question": "The Renaissance and the Protestant Reformation were similar in that both were",
    "option": [
      "stimulated by a spirit of inquiry",
      "supported by the working class",
      "limited to Italy, France, and Germany",
      "encouraged by the successes of the French Revolution"
    ],
    "answer": "stimulated by a spirit of inquiry"
  },
  {
    "id": 915,
    "question": "Which statement best describes a change that occurred during both the Renaissance and the Enlightenment?",
    "option": [
      "feudalism became the dominant political system",
      "the use of reason and logic were discouraged",
      "technology and science were considered unimportant",
      "a new questioning spirit and attitude emerged"
    ],
    "answer": "a new questioning spirit and attitude emerged"
  },
  {
    "id": 916,
    "question": "One factor that enabled the Renaissance to flourish in Northern Italy was that the region had",
    "option": [
      "a wealthy class that invested in the arts",
      "a socialist for of government",
      "limited contact with the Byzantine Empire",
      "a shrinking middle class"
    ],
    "answer": "a wealthy class that invested in the arts"
  },
  {
    "id": 917,
    "question": "European society during the Renaissance differed from European society during the Middle Ages in that during the Renaissance",
    "option": [
      "the Church was no longer influential",
      "the emphasis on individual worth increased",
      "economic activity declined",
      "art no longer contained religious themes"
    ],
    "answer": "the emphasis on individual worth increased"
  },
  {
    "id": 918,
    "question": "Which societal condition was basic to the development of Greek philosophy and Renaissance art?",
    "option": [
      "rigid social classes",
      "emphasis on individualism",
      "religious uniformity",
      "mass education"
    ],
    "answer": "emphasis on individualism"
  },
  {
    "id": 919,
    "question": "The humanists of the Renaissance differed from the traditional medieval philosophers in the humanists",
    "option": [
      "interest in the spiritual life of people",
      "lack of interest in Ancient Greek and Roman culture",
      "rejection of Christian principles",
      "emphasis on the importance of the individual"
    ],
    "answer": "emphasis on the importance of the individual"
  },
  {
    "id": 920,
    "question": "Which characteristic was common to the Golden Age of Greece and the Italian Renaissance?",
    "option": [
      "a strong military led to national unity",
      "written constitutions led to the establishment of democratic governments",
      "prosperity led to the creation of many works of art",
      "political instability led directly to the formation of unified nation-states"
    ],
    "answer": "prosperity led to the creation of many works of art"
  },
  {
    "id": 921,
    "question": "Which idea about leadership would Niccolo Machiavelli most likely support?",
    "option": [
      "leaders should do whatever is necessary to achieve their goals",
      "leaders should fight against discrimination and intolerance",
      "leaders should listen to the desires of the people",
      "elected leaders should be fair and good"
    ],
    "answer": "leaders should do whatever is necessary to achieve their goals"
  },
  {
    "id": 922,
    "question": "In the Renaissance period, which factor was emphasized by the philosophy of humanism?",
    "option": [
      "superiority of medieval thought",
      "devotion to religion",
      "value of the individual",
      "obedience to government officials"
    ],
    "answer": "value of the individual"
  },
  {
    "id": 923,
    "question": "Which statement concerning the Renaissance in Europe is based on opinion rather than on fact?",
    "option": [
      "Literature began to appear in languages other than Latin.",
      "The art of the Northern Renaissance was superior to that of the Italian Renaissance.",
      "Art reflected the ideas of humanism and individualism.",
      "Art produced during the Renaissance had religious as well as secular themes."
    ],
    "answer": "The art of the Northern Renaissance was superior to that of the Italian Renaissance."
  },
  {
    "id": 924,
    "question": "Martin Luther s Ninety-Five Theses were a call for",
    "option": [
      "religious revolt against the German princes",
      "reforms within the Roman Catholic Church",
      "greater papal authority",
      "crusades to spread Christianity"
    ],
    "answer": "reforms within the Roman Catholic Church"
  },
  {
    "id": 925,
    "question": "In Western Europe, a major immediate effect of the Reformation was a",
    "option": [
      "renewed domination of the Catholic Church over the German states",
      "greater tolerance of religions other than Christianity",
      "decrease in educational opportunities for the middle class",
      "decline in religious unity and in the power of the Catholic Church"
    ],
    "answer": "decline in religious unity and in the power of the Catholic Church"
  },
  {
    "id": 926,
    "question": "During the Renaissance, which development contributed most to the Protestant Reformation?",
    "option": [
      "interest in Ancient Greece and Rome",
      "advances in mathematics and science",
      "questioning of traditional authority",
      "attention to realism and detail"
    ],
    "answer": "questioning of traditional authority"
  },
  {
    "id": 927,
    "question": "Which was a result of the Protestant Reformation in Europe?",
    "option": [
      "the Catholic Church accepted the dominance of the new Protestant religions in Italy, France, and Germany",
      "Spain became a predominately Protestant nation",
      "Catholic Church leaders refused to make any changes in church practices",
      "the power of the Catholic Church in Europe was weakened"
    ],
    "answer": "the power of the Catholic Church in Europe was weakened"
  },
  {
    "id": 928,
    "question": "Which was a major result of the Reformation?",
    "option": [
      "new Christian denominations emerged",
      "religious teachings were no longer allowed in the universities",
      "the Crusades were organized",
      "the power of the Pope was strengthened"
    ],
    "answer": "new Christian denominations emerged"
  },
  {
    "id": 929,
    "question": "Which factor helped most to bring about the Protestant Reformation?",
    "option": [
      "the Catholic clergy had lost faith in their religion",
      "Islam was attracting many converts in Western Europe",
      "kings and princes in Northern Europe resented the power of the Catholic Church",
      "the exploration of the Americas led to the introduction of new religious ideas"
    ],
    "answer": "kings and princes in Northern Europe resented the power of the Catholic Church"
  },
  {
    "id": 930,
    "question": "The Protestant Reformation and the European Renaissance were similar in that both",
    "option": [
      "discouraged the growth of strong monarchs",
      "encouraged people to question tradition",
      "were led by the military",
      "supported the return of the Roman Empire"
    ],
    "answer": "encouraged people to question tradition"
  },
  {
    "id": 931,
    "question": "The Protestant Reformation represents a turning point in European history because it",
    "option": [
      "allowed religious reformers to escape persecution",
      "standardized all religious writings",
      "ended religious unity in Western Europe",
      "forced most of Europe s monarchs to become Protestants"
    ],
    "answer": "ended religious unity in Western Europe"
  },
  {
    "id": 932,
    "question": "Christians should be taught that he who gives to a poor man or lends to a needy man does better than if he used the money to buy an indulgence.",
    "option": [
      "Commercial Revolution",
      "Industrial Revolution",
      "Renaissance",
      "Protestant Reformation"
    ],
    "answer": "Protestant Reformation"
  },
  {
    "id": 933,
    "question": "The Renaissance and the Protestant Reformation were similar in that both were",
    "option": [
      "stimulated by a spirit of inquiry",
      "supported by the working class",
      "limited to Italy, France, and Germany",
      "encouraged by the successes of the French Revolution"
    ],
    "answer": "stimulated by a spirit of inquiry"
  },
  {
    "id": 934,
    "question": "One major influence the Renaissance had on the Protestant Reformation was that the philosophers of the Renaissance",
    "option": [
      "supported democratic forms of government",
      "encouraged a questioning attitude",
      "stressed the importance of life after death",
      "denied the existence of God"
    ],
    "answer": "encouraged a questioning attitude"
  },
  {
    "id": 935,
    "question": "Unless I am convinced by Scripture and plain reason... my conscience is captive to the Word of God. I cannot and I will hot recant anything, for to go against conscience is neither right nor safe. Here I stand, I cannot do otherwise.    Martin Luther, Diet of Worms (1517)",
    "option": [
      "the supremacy of the Bible over Church policies",
      "imprisoning those who disagreed with Church teachings",
      "maintaining the unity of the Church",
      "the need for nepotism"
    ],
    "answer": "the supremacy of the Bible over Church policies"
  },
  {
    "id": 936,
    "question": "Martin Luther s posting of the Ninety-Five Theses is considered by many to be a turning point in history because",
    "option": [
      "the Pope s right to sell indulgences was strengthened",
      "Luther soon became the leader of Germany",
      "the power of the Roman Catholic Church was lessened and royal power grew",
      "the Roman Catholic Church unified the German states"
    ],
    "answer": "the power of the Roman Catholic Church was lessened and royal power grew"
  },
  {
    "id": 937,
    "question": "In Spain, an effect of the Inquisition during the 16th century was to",
    "option": [
      "prevent the introduction of Protestant religions",
      "reintroduce Moorish culture to the Iberian Peninsula",
      "encourage the development of the Industrial Revolution",
      "implement the ideas of the Renaissance in major cities"
    ],
    "answer": "prevent the introduction of Protestant religions"
  },
  {
    "id": 938,
    "question": "In Latin America, the Maya and the Aztec civilizations were similar in that they",
    "option": [
      "showed little evidence of urbanization",
      "lacked a strong central government",
      "developed complex mathematical and calendar systems",
      "used military weapons superior to those of Europeans"
    ],
    "answer": "developed complex mathematical and calendar systems"
  },
  {
    "id": 939,
    "question": "A study of Mayas, Aztecs, and Incas would show that these ancient American civilizations",
    "option": [
      "produced few cultural achievements",
      "lived at peace with their neighbors",
      "welcomed the new technology brought by European explorers",
      "rivaled the accomplishments of early Middle Eastern cultures"
    ],
    "answer": "rivaled the accomplishments of early Middle Eastern cultures"
  },
  {
    "id": 940,
    "question": "A study of the Maya, Aztec, and Inca civilizations of Latin America would show that these civilizations",
    "option": [
      "developed advanced and complex societies before the arrival of the Europeans",
      "established extensive trade with Pacific Rim nations",
      "were strongly influenced by their contact with Asian and African civilizations",
      "were relatively large, but not well organized"
    ],
    "answer": "developed advanced and complex societies before the arrival of the Europeans"
  },
  {
    "id": 941,
    "question": "Which was a result of the Commercial Revolution",
    "option": [
      "decline in population growth in Europe",
      "shift of power from Western Europe to Eastern Europe",
      "spread of feudalism throughout Western Europe",
      "expansion of European influence overseas"
    ],
    "answer": "expansion of European influence overseas"
  },
  {
    "id": 942,
    "question": "Which was an immediate result of the European Age of Exploration?",
    "option": [
      "Islamic culture spread across Africa and Asia",
      "European influence spread to the Western hemisphere",
      "independence movements developed in Asia and Africa",
      "military dictatorships were established throughout Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "European influence spread to the Western hemisphere"
  },
  {
    "id": 943,
    "question": "A major result of the Age of Exploration was",
    "option": [
      "a long period of peace and prosperity for the nations of Western Europe",
      "extensive migration of people from the Western Hemisphere to Europe and Asia",
      "the fall of European national monarchies and the end of the power of the Catholic Church",
      "the end of regional isolation and the beginning of a period of European global domination"
    ],
    "answer": "the end of regional isolation and the beginning of a period of European global domination"
  },
  {
    "id": 944,
    "question": "The Commercial Revolution in Western Europe led directly to the",
    "option": [
      "development of a socialist economy",
      "establishment of the Guild System",
      "weakening of the power of the middle class",
      "expansion of world trade"
    ],
    "answer": "expansion of world trade"
  },
  {
    "id": 945,
    "question": "Which system developed as a result of the Commercial Revolution",
    "option": ["manorialism", "communism", "bartering", "market economy"],
    "answer": "market economy"
  },
  {
    "id": 946,
    "question": "Which of these events during the Age of Exploration was a cause of the other three?",
    "option": [
      "Europeans brought food, animals, and ideas from one continent to another",
      "European diseases had an adverse effect on the native populations of new territories",
      "warfare increased as European nations competed for land and power",
      "advances in learning and technology made long ocean voyages possible"
    ],
    "answer": "advances in learning and technology made long ocean voyages possible"
  },
  {
    "id": 947,
    "question": "The Native American population of Mexico in 1492 has been estimated at 25 million; the population in 1608 has been estimated at 1.7 million.  This decrease in population was mainly a result of",
    "option": [
      "crop failures brought on by poor weather conditions",
      "emigration of Native Americans to Europe and Africa",
      "wars between various native groups",
      "diseases introduced by the Spanish"
    ],
    "answer": "diseases introduced by the Spanish"
  },
  {
    "id": 948,
    "question": "In Latin America during the early period of Spanish colonialism, the deaths of large numbers of the native people led to",
    "option": [
      "a decline in Spanish immigration to the Americas",
      "the removal of most Spanish troops from the Americas",
      "the importation of slaves from Africa",
      "improved health care in the colonies"
    ],
    "answer": "the importation of slaves from Africa"
  },
  {
    "id": 949,
    "question": "Both Japan and China decided to limit trade with Europe during much of the 16th and 17th centuries because the Japanese and the Chinese",
    "option": [
      "had few products to sell to the Europeans",
      "held religious beliefs that prohibited contact with foreigners",
      "thought European technology would hinder any effort to modernize",
      "believed they would receive no benefit from increased contact with the Europeans"
    ],
    "answer": "believed they would receive no benefit from increased contact with the Europeans"
  },
  {
    "id": 950,
    "question": "One reason the Spanish conquistadors were able to conquer the Aztec and Inca Empires rapid is that",
    "option": [
      "these empires had no standing armies",
      "the Spanish had better weapons than the Aztecs and Incas did",
      "the Spanish greatly outnumbered the Aztecs and Incas",
      "the Aztecs and Incas joined together to fight the Spanish"
    ],
    "answer": "the Spanish had better weapons than the Aztecs and Incas did"
  },
  {
    "id": 951,
    "question": "Which conclusion can be drawn from a study of the early civilizations of Axum, Kush, Mali and Songhai?",
    "option": [
      "these African societies flourished at the same time",
      "farming was more extensive in the Nile River Valley than it was in the Fertile Crescent",
      "the Neolithic Revolution occurred in Africa",
      "these societies had a long and rich history before their first contact with Europeans"
    ],
    "answer": "these societies had a long and rich history before their first contact with Europeans"
  },
  {
    "id": 952,
    "question": "Which was a characteristic of the policy of mercantilism followed by Spanish colonial rulers in Latin America?",
    "option": [
      "the colonies were forced to develop local industries to support themselves",
      "Spain sought trade agreements between its colonies and the English colonies in North America",
      "the colonies were required to provide raw materials to Spain and to purchase Spanish manufactured goods",
      "Spain encouraged the colonies to develop new political systems to meet colonial needs"
    ],
    "answer": "the colonies were required to provide raw materials to Spain and to purchase Spanish manufactured goods"
  },
  {
    "id": 953,
    "question": "Which statement best describes a result of the scarcity of native Indian labor in Latin America during the colonial period?",
    "option": [
      "unskilled laborers were imported from Asia",
      "many people from Spain and Portugal immigrated to the region",
      "Native American Indians from the British colonies went south to work",
      "large numbers of African slaves were imported"
    ],
    "answer": "large numbers of African slaves were imported"
  },
  {
    "id": 954,
    "question": "The influence of African culture on some areas of Latin America was largely a result of the",
    "option": [
      "American Revolution",
      "building of the Panama Canal",
      "success of Communist Revolutions",
      "Atlantic slave trade"
    ],
    "answer": "Atlantic slave trade"
  },
  {
    "id": 955,
    "question": "In many Latin American nations, a major effect of colonial rule has been the",
    "option": [
      "concentration of power in a small group of landowners",
      "minor political role of the military",
      "equal distribution of wealth among social classes",
      "economic control held by the Indian population"
    ],
    "answer": "concentration of power in a small group of landowners"
  },
  {
    "id": 956,
    "question": "Spain s colonial policy of mercantilism affected the development of Latin American nations by promoting",
    "option": [
      "the production of raw material and cash crops",
      "free and rapid trade with Asia and Africa",
      "respect for the rights of indigenous people",
      "isolationism as a response to international political issues"
    ],
    "answer": "the production of raw material and cash crops"
  },
  {
    "id": 957,
    "question": "One result of the European conquest of Latin America was that in Latin America",
    "option": [
      "Spanish became the major spoken language",
      "Native American cultures flourished",
      "the Aztec religion spread",
      "many parliamentary democracies were established"
    ],
    "answer": "Spanish became the major spoken language"
  },
  {
    "id": 958,
    "question": "In colonial Latin America, the main purpose of the encomienda system was to",
    "option": [
      "insure that the Indians were humanely treated",
      "provide a steady labor supply for early colonists",
      "prevent slaver in Spain s New World colonies",
      "build and maintain forts to repel foreign invaders"
    ],
    "answer": "provide a steady labor supply for early colonists"
  },
  {
    "id": 959,
    "question": "According to the theory of mercantilism, colonies should be",
    "option": [
      "acquired as markets and sources of raw materials",
      "considered an economic burden for the colonial power",
      "grated independence as soon as possible",
      "encouraged to develop their own industries"
    ],
    "answer": "acquired as markets and sources of raw materials"
  },
  {
    "id": 960,
    "question": "He once sent fifty horsemen with pikes (spears) to destroy an entire province.  Not a single human being survived that massacre, neither women nor children nor aged infirm This terrible massacre was punishment for a trifling offense: some Indians had not responded to a summons promptly enough when the tyrant had commanded that they bring him a load of maize (corn) , or else had asked for more Indians to be assigned to serve him or his comrades.  And there was no place where the Indians could take refuge",
    "option": [
      "encourage the colonial government to change its policies toward native peoples",
      "explain the problems associated with using native laborers",
      "justify the need for the harsh treatment of the native people",
      "show support for the governor s policy toward native peoples"
    ],
    "answer": "encourage the colonial government to change its policies toward native peoples"
  },
  {
    "id": 961,
    "question": "The Treaty of Tordesillas (1494), concerning Latin America, and the Berlin Conference (1884-1885), concerning Africa, were similar in that each agreement",
    "option": [
      "provided for self-government by the native peoples",
      "declared that in these areas monarchs rule by divine right",
      "divided each area into European-controlled segments",
      "suppressed revolts by native peoples against European imperialists"
    ],
    "answer": "divided each area into European-controlled segments"
  },
  {
    "id": 962,
    "question": "Which statement best illustrates the contradictory actions of the Catholic Church in colonial Latin America?",
    "option": [
      "the Jesuits destroyed the temples of the Native Americans, but allowed them to continue their religious rituals",
      "the Church expressed concern over the mistreatment of Native Americans, but supported the encomienda system",
      "the Church moved many Native Americas from Spanish territory to Portuguese territory, but encouraged the importation of African slaves",
      "the Pope endorsed the Treaty of Tordesillas, but outlawed further exploration"
    ],
    "answer": "the Church expressed concern over the mistreatment of Native Americans, but supported the encomienda system"
  },
  {
    "id": 963,
    "question": "The Crusades indirectly contributed to the discovery of the New World by",
    "option": [
      "forcing the religious conversion of the Muslim population",
      "forcing the Turks to flee from Constantinople",
      "stimulating European demand for goods from the East",
      "increasing the power of the feudal lords"
    ],
    "answer": "stimulating European demand for goods from the East"
  },
  {
    "id": 964,
    "question": "In the 1600 s, the interest of Europeans in Africa was based mainly on Europe s need to",
    "option": [
      "market its surplus agricultural products",
      "obtain workers for its colonies in the Americas",
      "establish collective security arrangements",
      "settle its surplus population on new lands"
    ],
    "answer": "obtain workers for its colonies in the Americas"
  },
  {
    "id": 965,
    "question": "The printing press, the astrolabe, and the Mercator projection were technological advances that contributed to the",
    "option": [
      "exploration and overseas expansion of the colonial empires",
      "unification of Germany and Italy in the late 1800 s",
      "growth of industry in Latin America during the late 1900 s",
      "spread of Islam in the 700 s and 800 s"
    ],
    "answer": "exploration and overseas expansion of the colonial empires"
  },
  {
    "id": 966,
    "question": "Peter the Great and Catherine the Great changed Russia by",
    "option": [
      "abolishing all social class distinctions",
      "becoming constitutional monarchs",
      "preventing wars with neighboring nations",
      "introducing western ideas and customs"
    ],
    "answer": "introducing western ideas and customs"
  },
  {
    "id": 967,
    "question": "Changes in Russia under Peter the Great were most similar to changes that occurred in",
    "option": [
      "China before the Opium War",
      "Japan during the Meiji Restoration",
      "Iran after the fall of Shah Pahlevi",
      "France during the feudal period"
    ],
    "answer": "Japan during the Meiji Restoration"
  },
  {
    "id": 968,
    "question": "Westernization in Russia came about largely through the",
    "option": [
      "efforts of Peter the Great and his successors",
      "invasion of Russia by Sweden",
      "desire of the United States to seek new markets",
      "acceptance of the policies of the Eastern Orthodox Church"
    ],
    "answer": "efforts of Peter the Great and his successors"
  },
  {
    "id": 969,
    "question": "God hath power to create or destroy, make or unmake, at his pleasure; to give life or send death; to judge and to be judged (by) none And the like power have kings;",
    "option": [
      "theory of divine right",
      "enlightened despotism",
      "Social Darwinism",
      "constitutional monarchy"
    ],
    "answer": "theory of divine right"
  },
  {
    "id": 970,
    "question": "Which type of government is shown in the cartoon?",
    "option": [
      "a socialist republic",
      "an absolute monarchy",
      "a communist dictatorship",
      "a democracy"
    ],
    "answer": "an absolute monarchy"
  },
  {
    "id": 971,
    "question": ". . .The person of the King is sacred, and to attack him in any way is an attack on religion itself. Kings represent the divine majesty and have been appointed by Him to carry out His purposes. Serving God and respecting kings are bound together.    Bishop Jacques Bossuet",
    "option": [
      "existed during the",
      "Age of Absolutism",
      "Renaissance",
      "Industrial Revolution"
    ],
    "answer": "Age of Absolutism"
  },
  {
    "id": 972,
    "question": ". . .The person of the King is sacred, and to attack him in any way is an attack on religion itself. Kings represent the divine majesty and have been appointed by Him to carry out His purposes. Serving God and respecting kings are bound together.    Bishop Jacques Bossuet",
    "option": ["John Locke", "Karl Marx", "Elizabeth II", "Louis XIV"],
    "answer": "Louis XIV"
  },
  {
    "id": 973,
    "question": "Francis Bacon, Galileo, and Isaac Newton promoted the idea that knowledge should be based on",
    "option": [
      "the experiences of past civilizations",
      "experimentation and observation",
      "emotions and feelings",
      "the teachings of the Catholic Church"
    ],
    "answer": "experimentation and observation"
  },
  {
    "id": 974,
    "question": "During the Scientific Revolution and the Enlightenment, one similarity in the work of many scientists and philosophers was that they",
    "option": [
      "relied heavily on the ideas of medieval thinkers",
      "favored an absolute monarchy as a way of improving economic conditions",
      "received support from the Catholic Church",
      "examined natural laws governing the universe"
    ],
    "answer": "examined natural laws governing the universe"
  },
  {
    "id": 975,
    "question": "Which statement best describes the effects of the works of Nicolaus Copernicus, Galileo Galilei, Sir",
    "option": [
      "The acceptance of traditional authority was strengthened.",
      "The scientific method was used to solve problems.",
      "Funding to education was increased by the English government.",
      "Interest in Greek and Roman drama was renewed."
    ],
    "answer": "The scientific method was used to solve problems."
  },
  {
    "id": 976,
    "question": "Speaker A  : Good government stresses the importance of the nation and accepts the rights of the individual only if the interests of the individual are the same as those of the nation.",
    "option": ["A", "B", "C", "D"],
    "answer": "C"
  },
  {
    "id": 977,
    "question": "Speaker A  :  The story of history is the story of class struggles.  Revolution is necessary to overthrow the ruling class and eventually create a classless society in which no one will be exploited.",
    "option": ["A", "B", "C", "D"],
    "answer": "D"
  },
  {
    "id": 978,
    "question": "One important result of the French Revolution was that",
    "option": [
      "France enjoyed a lengthy period of peace and prosperity",
      "the church was restored to its former role and power in the French government",
      "political power shifted to the bourgeoisie",
      "France lost its spirit of nationalism"
    ],
    "answer": "political power shifted to the bourgeoisie"
  },
  {
    "id": 979,
    "question": "Which statement is a valid generalization about the immediate results of the French Revolution of 1789?",
    "option": [
      "the Roman Catholic Church increased its power and wealth",
      "the revolution achieved its goal of establishing peace, democracy, and justice for all",
      "the revolution had little impact outside France",
      "the French middle class gained more power"
    ],
    "answer": "the French middle class gained more power"
  },
  {
    "id": 980,
    "question": "In France, which was a major result of the French Revolution?",
    "option": [
      "the king was restored to unlimited power",
      "the clergy dominated government",
      "the middle class gained political influence",
      "the tax burden was carried by the lower class"
    ],
    "answer": "the middle class gained political influence"
  },
  {
    "id": 981,
    "question": "A study of revolutions would most likely lead to the conclusion that pre-Revolutionary governments",
    "option": [
      "are more concerned about human rights than the governments that replace them",
      "refuse to modernize their armed forces with advanced technology",
      "attempt to bring about the separation of government from religion",
      "fail to meet the political and economic needs of their people"
    ],
    "answer": "fail to meet the political and economic needs of their people"
  },
  {
    "id": 982,
    "question": "Congress of Vienna Restores Monarchy to France    Czar Nicholas I Limits Freedom of the Russian Press",
    "option": [
      "reactions to the French Revolution",
      "movements to unify all of western Europe",
      "efforts to improve the conditions of factory workers",
      "attempts to promote trade between European nations"
    ],
    "answer": "reactions to the French Revolution"
  },
  {
    "id": 983,
    "question": "The French people supported Napoleon Bonaparte because they hoped he would",
    "option": [
      "adopt the ideas of the Protestant Reformation",
      "restore Louis XVI to power",
      "provide stability for the nation",
      "end British control of France"
    ],
    "answer": "provide stability for the nation"
  },
  {
    "id": 984,
    "question": "Simon Bolivar and Miguel Hidalgo, leaders of Latin American independence movements, were inspired by successful revolutions in",
    "option": [
      "the Untied States and France",
      "the Soviet Union and China",
      "Cuba and Costa Rica",
      "Egypt and Kenya"
    ],
    "answer": "the Untied States and France"
  },
  {
    "id": 985,
    "question": "During the early 1800 s, which was a major influence on the struggle for political independence in Latin America?",
    "option": [
      "poor conditions in urban centers in Latin America",
      "the American and French Revolutions",
      "the desire of the Roman Catholic Church in Latin America to escape European control",
      "demands by Latin American workers to own their own factories"
    ],
    "answer": "the American and French Revolutions"
  },
  {
    "id": 986,
    "question": "One similarity in the leadership of Latin Americas Jose de San Martin, Toussaint l Ouverture, Bernanrdo O Higgins, and Pedro I was that each leader",
    "option": [
      "opposed United States intervention in Haiti",
      "led a struggle to gain freedom for the people of his nation",
      "opposed membership of his nation in the League of Nations",
      "established an absolute monarchy in his nation"
    ],
    "answer": "led a struggle to gain freedom for the people of his nation"
  },
  {
    "id": 987,
    "question": "I will never allow my hands to be idle nor my soul to rest until I have broken the chains laid upon us by Spain.",
    "option": [
      "a Latin American nationalist",
      "a Portuguese explorer",
      "a Roman Catholic bishop",
      "a Spanish conquistador"
    ],
    "answer": "a Latin American nationalist"
  },
  {
    "id": 988,
    "question": "Which of these situations was the direct result of the other three?",
    "option": [
      "nations of Latin America won independence",
      "revolutions occurred in North America and France",
      "the Napoleonic wars weakened Spain s power",
      "creoles and mestizos became discontented with Spanish rule"
    ],
    "answer": "nations of Latin America won independence"
  },
  {
    "id": 989,
    "question": "The 19th-century independence movements in Latin America were influenced by",
    "option": [
      "Marxist ideology",
      "the Aztec wars against Hernando Cortez",
      "liberation theology",
      "the American and the French Revolutions"
    ],
    "answer": "the American and the French Revolutions"
  },
  {
    "id": 990,
    "question": "Simon Bolivar, Toussaint L Overture, and Bernardo O Higgins were Latin American leaders of",
    "option": [
      "economic development",
      "educational reforms",
      "independence movements",
      "colonial expansion"
    ],
    "answer": "independence movements"
  },
  {
    "id": 991,
    "question": "In which region of the world did the American Revolution and the French Revolution have the greatest influence during the 1800 s?",
    "option": [
      "Southeast Asia",
      "Latin America",
      "South Asia",
      "sub-Saharan Africa"
    ],
    "answer": "Latin America"
  },
  {
    "id": 992,
    "question": "Sim n Bol var, Jos  de San Mart n, and Toussaint l Ouverture are important in Latin American history because they were",
    "option": [
      "20th-century caudillos",
      "leaders of liberation movements",
      "members of the Organization of American States (OAS)",
      "winners of the Nobel Peace Prize"
    ],
    "answer": "leaders of liberation movements"
  },
  {
    "id": 993,
    "question": "A country is not merely a geographic territory.  A country is also the idea given birth by the geographic territory.  A country is a sense of love that unites, as one, all the sons and daughters of that geographic territory",
    "option": [
      "totalitarian rule",
      "absolute monarchy",
      "mercantilism",
      "nationalism"
    ],
    "answer": "nationalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 994,
    "question": "In a number of European countries in the 1800 s, which situation occurred as a result of the influence of the French Revolution?",
    "option": [
      "increase in religious conflict",
      "rise of nationalistic movements",
      "decentralization of governmental power",
      "economic depression"
    ],
    "answer": "rise of nationalistic movements"
  },
  {
    "id": 995,
    "question": "Which quotation best reflects a feeling of nationalism?",
    "option": [
      " An eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth",
      " A person s greatest social obligation is loyalty to the family",
      " For God, King, and Country",
      " Opposition to evil is as much a duty as is cooperation with good"
    ],
    "answer": " For God, King, and Country"
  },
  {
    "id": 996,
    "question": "Nationalism is most likely to develop in an area that has",
    "option": [
      "land suited to agriculture",
      "adequate industry to supply consumer demands",
      "a moderate climate with rivers for irrigation",
      "common customs, language, and history"
    ],
    "answer": "common customs, language, and history"
  },
  {
    "id": 997,
    "question": "Nationalism is best defined as",
    "option": [
      "the achievement of world peace and global understanding",
      "the desire to take over other societies by force",
      "a method of solving basic economic problems of the society",
      "the loyalty of a people to their values, traditions, and a geographic region"
    ],
    "answer": "the loyalty of a people to their values, traditions, and a geographic region"
  },
  {
    "id": 998,
    "question": "The best example of the success of nationalism in Europe is the",
    "option": [
      "development of socialism in France",
      "Industrial Revolution in Great Britain",
      "establishment of the Common Market",
      "unification of Germany"
    ],
    "answer": "unification of Germany"
  },
  {
    "id": 999,
    "question": "Which condition is most necessary to the process of industrialization in a society?",
    "option": [
      "dependence on subsistence agriculture",
      "creation of a one-crop economy",
      "availability of investment capital",
      "capture of foreign lands"
    ],
    "answer": "availability of investment capital"
  },
  {
    "id": 1000,
    "question": "According to Karl Marx, history is the record of the",
    "option": [
      "granting of more political liberties to all people",
      "struggle between classes in society",
      "wars and conflicts between national leaders",
      "increasing prosperity brought about by industrialization"
    ],
    "answer": "struggle between classes in society"
  },
  {
    "id": 1001,
    "question": "A main idea of Karl Marx and Friedrich Engles  Communist Manifesto is that the proletariat",
    "option": [
      "would need foreign help to achieve its revolutionary ends",
      "had to cooperate with the capitalists to gain economic rewards",
      "should allow the capitalists to control the means of production",
      "must unite to overthrow the capitalist class"
    ],
    "answer": "must unite to overthrow the capitalist class"
  },
  {
    "id": 1002,
    "question": "Revolution will occur more and more frequently in the industrialized nations as the proletariat struggles to overcome the abuses of the capitalist system.",
    "option": [
      "Charles Darwin",
      "Karl Marx",
      "Niccolo Machiavelli",
      "John Locke"
    ],
    "answer": "Karl Marx"
  },
  {
    "id": 1003,
    "question": "The proletarians have nothing to lose but their chains Workers of the world, unite!",
    "option": [
      "Protestant Reformation",
      "Counter-Reformation",
      "Commercial Revolution",
      "Industrial Revolution"
    ],
    "answer": "Industrial Revolution"
  },
  {
    "id": 1004,
    "question": "Before a nation can begin to industrialize, that nation must first develop",
    "option": [
      "a democratic government",
      "a rigid class structure",
      "a strong religious foundation",
      "an adequate food supply"
    ],
    "answer": "an adequate food supply"
  },
  {
    "id": 1005,
    "question": "A major result of the Industrial Revolution was the",
    "option": [
      "concentration of workers in urban areas",
      "increased desire of the wealthy class to share its power",
      "formation of powerful craft guilds",
      "control of agricultural production by governments"
    ],
    "answer": "concentration of workers in urban areas"
  },
  {
    "id": 1006,
    "question": "According to the theories of Karl Marx, history can be viewed as a",
    "option": [
      "succession of famines that result in the destruction of civilizations",
      "repeating cycle of imperialism and colonialism",
      "listing of the accomplishments of the ruling classes",
      "continuous struggle between economic classes"
    ],
    "answer": "continuous struggle between economic classes"
  },
  {
    "id": 1007,
    "question": "-Europeans sought new markets for their goods.  -Many Europeans migrated to the cities in search of jobs.",
    "option": [
      "Industrial Revolution",
      "rise of feudalism",
      "Congress of Vienna",
      "French Revolution"
    ],
    "answer": "Industrial Revolution"
  },
  {
    "id": 1008,
    "question": "Which revolution inspired Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels to express their ideas in The Communist Manifesto?",
    "option": ["Industrial", "Scientific", "Glorious", "Neolithic"],
    "answer": "Industrial"
  },
  {
    "id": 1009,
    "question": "Before Commodore Matthew Perry s expedition to Japan in 1853, Japan was most influenced by",
    "option": [
      "Russia s need for warm water ports",
      "the introduction of advanced technology from the United States",
      "France s quest for new colonies",
      "China s religion, art, and writing"
    ],
    "answer": "China s religion, art, and writing"
  },
  {
    "id": 1010,
    "question": "In Japan, the Meiji Restoration resulted in the",
    "option": [
      "division of the nation between the European powers",
      "modernization of the nation s industry",
      "abolition of the position of emperor",
      "government being controlled by the samurai"
    ],
    "answer": "modernization of the nation s industry"
  },
  {
    "id": 1011,
    "question": "An immediate result of Commodore Matthew Perry s visit to Japan in 1853 was",
    "option": [
      "an alliance between Japan and Russia",
      "the development of trade between Japan and the West",
      "a war between Japan and the United States",
      "the continued isolation of Japan"
    ],
    "answer": "the development of trade between Japan and the West"
  },
  {
    "id": 1012,
    "question": "The arrival of Commodore Matthew Perry in Japan in 1853 signaled the end of Japanese",
    "option": [
      "cultural contacts with the West",
      "policies of isolationism",
      "militarism in Southeast Asia",
      "trade relations with the United States"
    ],
    "answer": "policies of isolationism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1013,
    "question": "A major goal of the Meiji government in Japan was to",
    "option": [
      "isolate Japan from other nations",
      "achieve political union with China",
      "establish Japan as an industrial power",
      "encourage colonization of Asia by Western nations"
    ],
    "answer": "establish Japan as an industrial power"
  },
  {
    "id": 1014,
    "question": "The modernization of Japan during the Meiji Restoration resulted in",
    "option": [
      "a return to a feudal system of government",
      "the rise of Japan as an imperialistic nation",
      "an alliance between China, Korea, Russia, and Japan",
      "a strengthening of Japan s isolationist policies"
    ],
    "answer": "the rise of Japan as an imperialistic nation"
  },
  {
    "id": 1015,
    "question": "Which statement best describes events in Japan during the period of the Meiji Restoration?",
    "option": [
      "Japan sought to isolate itself from world affairs.",
      "Rapid industrialization and economic growth occurred.",
      "Local lords increased their power over the Japanese emperor.",
      "Agriculture was taken over by the government."
    ],
    "answer": "Rapid industrialization and economic growth occurred."
  },
  {
    "id": 1016,
    "question": "A primary purpose for building the Suez Canal was to",
    "option": [
      "encourage Jewish settlement in nearby Palestine",
      "increase trade between the Middle East, Europe and Asia",
      "reduce the time needed for travel between the Atlantic Ocean and the Caribbean Sea",
      "allow Indian merchants to reach the east coast of Africa"
    ],
    "answer": "increase trade between the Middle East, Europe and Asia"
  },
  {
    "id": 1017,
    "question": "Which is an accurate statement about the partitioning of Africa by European imperialist nations during the 1800 s?",
    "option": [
      "new nations were based on old tribal boundaries",
      "the cultural and ethnic diversity of the African people was disregarded",
      "the continent was divided equally among the colonial powers",
      "African unity was encouraged"
    ],
    "answer": "the cultural and ethnic diversity of the African people was disregarded"
  },
  {
    "id": 1018,
    "question": "After 1880, European nations sought colonies in Africa primarily because the Europeans were",
    "option": [
      "in need of land for their surplus populations",
      "competing of raw materials and markets",
      "determined to bring Christianity to the Moslem world",
      "interested in completing their geographic knowledge of the world"
    ],
    "answer": "competing of raw materials and markets"
  },
  {
    "id": 1019,
    "question": "The 19th century term  White Man s Burden  reflects the idea that",
    "option": [
      "Asians and Africans were equal to Europeans",
      "Asians and Africans would be grateful for European help",
      "imperialism was opposed by most Europeans",
      "Europeans had a responsibility to improve the lives of the colonial peoples"
    ],
    "answer": "Europeans had a responsibility to improve the lives of the colonial peoples"
  },
  {
    "id": 1020,
    "question": "The Sepoy Mutiny in India, the Boxer Rebellion in China, and the Islamic Revolution in Iran were similar in that they",
    "option": [
      "restored power to the hereditary monarchies",
      "attempted to reject the traditional cultures in these countries",
      "resisted foreign influence in these countries",
      "reestablished the power of religious leaders"
    ],
    "answer": "resisted foreign influence in these countries"
  },
  {
    "id": 1021,
    "question": "During the 19th century, Europeans were able to divide China in Spheres of Influence mainly because the",
    "option": [
      "Chinese were eager to adopt western culture",
      "Europeans had technologically superior military forces",
      "Europeans were willing to adopt Chinese customs",
      "Chinese lacked raw materials and resources"
    ],
    "answer": "Europeans had technologically superior military forces"
  },
  {
    "id": 1022,
    "question": "The Boxer Rebellion of the early 20th century was an attempt to",
    "option": [
      "eliminate poverty among the Chinese peasants",
      "bring western-style democracy to China",
      "restore trade between China and European nations",
      "remove foreign influences from China"
    ],
    "answer": "remove foreign influences from China"
  },
  {
    "id": 1023,
    "question": "Yesterday, your ambassador petitioned my ministers regarding your trade with China our Celestial Empire possesses all things in great abundance and lacks no product within its own borders.  There is, therefore, no need to import any product manufactured by outside barbarians in exchange for our own goods.",
    "option": [
      "maintaining economic isolation",
      "expanding foreign trade",
      "increasing international interdependence",
      "developing into a colonial power"
    ],
    "answer": "maintaining economic isolation"
  },
  {
    "id": 1024,
    "question": "British control over South Africa, French control over Indochina, and Spanish control over Mexico are examples of",
    "option": ["isolationism", "appeasement", "nonalignment", "imperialism"],
    "answer": "imperialism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1025,
    "question": "In the past, European nations have conquered other lands, made them into colonies, and controlled their economies.",
    "option": ["socialism", "isolationism", "imperialism", "monotheism"],
    "answer": "imperialism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1026,
    "question": "In the past, European nations have conquered other lands, made them into colonies, and controlled their economies.",
    "option": [
      "industrialization of Europe and the need for raw materials",
      "desire of Europeans to spread communism throughout the world",
      "European belief in human rights for all people",
      "requests of developing nations for modern machines and technology"
    ],
    "answer": "industrialization of Europe and the need for raw materials"
  },
  {
    "id": 1027,
    "question": "During the 1840 s, China signed  unequal treaties  with Western nations mainly because",
    "option": [
      "China had won the Opium War",
      "Western nations had superior military technology",
      "leaders in China favored expansion",
      "China had requested economic assistance from the West"
    ],
    "answer": "Western nations had superior military technology"
  },
  {
    "id": 1028,
    "question": "Throughout the 1800 s, an increased need for both raw materials and new markets for manufactured goods led various European nations to pursue policies of",
    "option": ["imperialism", "socialism", "isolationism", "communism"],
    "answer": "imperialism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1029,
    "question": "During the 18th and 19th centuries, increased contact between European and the continents of Africa, Asia, and South America resulted in",
    "option": [
      "closer cultural cooperation between Europe and these continents",
      "the exploitation of the labor and resources of these continents",
      "a return to the political and economic systems of feudal Europe",
      "preservation of the rights of the indigenous peoples"
    ],
    "answer": "the exploitation of the labor and resources of these continents"
  },
  {
    "id": 1030,
    "question": "Take up the White Man s burden",
    "option": [
      "negative attitude of Europeans toward peoples of the non-Western world",
      "advantages Europeans would gain by colonizing Africa, Asia, and Latin America",
      "positive role of the Roman Catholic Church in Africa and Asia",
      "challenges non-Europeans faced when trading with the Europeans"
    ],
    "answer": "negative attitude of Europeans toward peoples of the non-Western world"
  },
  {
    "id": 1031,
    "question": "Both the French and the British were interested in controlling Egypt in the mid-19th century because Egypt had",
    "option": [
      "control of the spice trade",
      "an industrial-based economy",
      "vital mineral resources",
      "a strategic location"
    ],
    "answer": "a strategic location"
  },
  {
    "id": 1032,
    "question": ", you, Africa, suffered like a beast  Your ashes strewn to the wind that roams the desert,",
    "option": ["imperialism", "communism", "nationalism", "regionalism"],
    "answer": "imperialism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1033,
    "question": "The results of the Opium War (1839-1842) indicate that China was",
    "option": [
      "still a major military power",
      "not strong enough to resist Western demands",
      "rapidly building a modern industrial economy",
      "accepting Western nations as equal trading partners"
    ],
    "answer": "not strong enough to resist Western demands"
  },
  {
    "id": 1034,
    "question": "During the 18th and 19th centuries, Europeans improved roads and bridges and built railroads in their colonies primarily to",
    "option": [
      "provide jobs for the colonists",
      "obtain raw materials needed for industrialization",
      "impress the colonists with their technological knowledge",
      "help missionaries spread Christianity"
    ],
    "answer": "obtain raw materials needed for industrialization"
  },
  {
    "id": 1035,
    "question": "Compared to other peoples of the world we have the greatest (largest) population and our civilization is four thousand years old Today we are the poorest and weakest nation in the world and occupy the lowest position in international affairs.  Other men are the carving knife and serving dish, we are the fish and the meat.  As a consequence we are being transformed everywhere into a colony of the foreign powers.",
    "option": [
      "Opium War and Boxer Rebellion",
      "Mau Mau uprising and adoption of apartheid",
      "Sepoy Mutiny and the Salt March",
      "Haitian Revolution and Cortes  march on Mexico City"
    ],
    "answer": "Opium War and Boxer Rebellion"
  },
  {
    "id": 1036,
    "question": "One result of British colonialism in India was that India",
    "option": [
      "adopted a parliamentary system of government",
      "developed religious unity",
      "supported Western foreign policies in the United Nations",
      "created programs to increase its population"
    ],
    "answer": "adopted a parliamentary system of government"
  },
  {
    "id": 1037,
    "question": "The Ashanti and Ijebu... strongly resisted missionary incursion [interference]-for a time at least . . . Both groups grudgingly [reluctantly] accepted missionaries and their schools only after military defeat by imperial forces.       Edward H. Berman",
    "option": [
      "opposed giving up their religious and cultural heritage",
      "returned to the worship of their traditional gods after the defeat of the missionaries",
      "cooperated with the missionaries for economic gain",
      "feared that missionaries would refuse to teach their children"
    ],
    "answer": "opposed giving up their religious and cultural heritage"
  },
  {
    "id": 1038,
    "question": "In 19th-century China, the Opium War resulted in",
    "option": [
      "the control of Hong Kong being returned to China",
      "the removal of all British naval forces from China",
      "an increase in European spheres of influence in China",
      "the rejection of Buddhism by the Chinese people"
    ],
    "answer": "an increase in European spheres of influence in China"
  },
  {
    "id": 1039,
    "question": "The borders that were established for many African nations during the late 1800 s were based primarily on",
    "option": [
      "natural geographic barriers",
      "easy access to natural resources",
      "territorial claims of colonial rulers",
      "cultural differences between ethnic groups"
    ],
    "answer": "territorial claims of colonial rulers"
  },
  {
    "id": 1040,
    "question": "An analysis of the Russo-Japanese War and the Boer War shows that one reason nations go to war is to",
    "option": [
      "assist oppressed people",
      "spread religious beliefs",
      "satisfy imperialist goals",
      "honor provisions of a treaty"
    ],
    "answer": "satisfy imperialist goals"
  },
  {
    "id": 1041,
    "question": "Which statement best expresses the motive for 19th-century European imperialism?",
    "option": [
      "Living space was needed for the excess population in western Europe.",
      "European leaders believed imperialism was an effective method of reducing the number of wars.",
      "European nations would benefit from some aspects of the conquered nation s culture.",
      "Imperialism would benefit the economies of the colonial powers."
    ],
    "answer": "Imperialism would benefit the economies of the colonial powers."
  },
  {
    "id": 1042,
    "question": "In 1917, Bolshevik leaders in Russia sought peace with Germany because the new Russian government",
    "option": [
      "decided to join forces with Germany and the Central Powers",
      "needed to concentrate its troops and resources on its war with Turkey",
      "wanted to retain power and avoid German occupation",
      "needed to control the Baltic Sea and wanted a warm water port"
    ],
    "answer": "wanted to retain power and avoid German occupation"
  },
  {
    "id": 1043,
    "question": "In Eastern Europe after World War I, the greatest obstacle to national unity in many nation-states was the",
    "option": [
      "great ethnic diversity found in the region",
      "economic dependence of Eastern Europe on Japan",
      "acceptance of democratic traditions by most Eastern Europeans",
      "expansion of United States influence in the region"
    ],
    "answer": "great ethnic diversity found in the region"
  },
  {
    "id": 1044,
    "question": "Which statement best describes the relationship between World War I and the Russian Revolution?",
    "option": [
      "World War I created conditions within Russia that helped trigger a revolution",
      "World War I postponed the Russian Revolution by restoring confidence in the Czar",
      "the Russian Revolution inspired the Russian people to win World War I",
      "World War I gave the Czar s army the needed experience to suppress the Russian Revolution"
    ],
    "answer": "World War I created conditions within Russia that helped trigger a revolution"
  },
  {
    "id": 1045,
    "question": "A major cause of World War I was",
    "option": [
      "a decline in the policy of imperialism",
      "the existence of opposing alliances",
      "an increase in acts of aggression by England",
      "the spread of communism throughout Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "the existence of opposing alliances"
  },
  {
    "id": 1046,
    "question": "Why was the Balkan region referred to as the  Powder Keg of Europe  prior to World War I?",
    "option": [
      "The aggression of the Ottoman Empire was disrupting the balance of power.",
      "Yugoslavia was invading its neighboring countries.",
      "Nationalistic and imperialistic rivalries were increasing.",
      "The area was the leading supplier of military equipment to the rest of the world."
    ],
    "answer": "Nationalistic and imperialistic rivalries were increasing."
  },
  {
    "id": 1047,
    "question": "The major impact of the Treaty of Versailles on Germany was that the treaty led to",
    "option": [
      "an era of peace and international good will in Germany",
      "a stable Germany that was both democratic and strong",
      "an increase in Germany s desire to regain its power and prestige",
      "a leadership position for Germany in the League of Nations"
    ],
    "answer": "an increase in Germany s desire to regain its power and prestige"
  },
  {
    "id": 1048,
    "question": "Archduke Franz Ferdinand Assassinated!    Germany Declares War on Russia and France!",
    "option": ["Franco-Prussian War", "Crimean War", "World War I", "Cold War"],
    "answer": "World War I"
  },
  {
    "id": 1049,
    "question": "Which is generally a characteristic of a communist economy?",
    "option": [
      "investment is encouraged by the promise of large profits",
      "the role of government in the economy is restricted by law",
      "government agencies are involved in production planning",
      "entrepreneurs sell shares in their companies to the government"
    ],
    "answer": "government agencies are involved in production planning"
  },
  {
    "id": 1050,
    "question": "A group of planners makes all economic decisions. The group assigns natural, human, and capital resources to the production of those goods and services it wants. The group decides how to produce them and to whom to distribute them",
    "option": [
      "manorial economy of feudal Europe",
      "mercantile economy of 18th century Europe",
      "command economy of the Soviet Union",
      "market economy of the United States"
    ],
    "answer": "command economy of the Soviet Union"
  },
  {
    "id": 1051,
    "question": "Which situation resulted from the Russo-Japanese War of 1905?",
    "option": [
      "Japan lost its status as a world power",
      "the Japanese Emperor encouraged reforms in Russia",
      "dissident groups challenged the power of the Russian Czar",
      "Russia gained control of China and Japan"
    ],
    "answer": "dissident groups challenged the power of the Russian Czar"
  },
  {
    "id": 1052,
    "question": "Stalin s Five-Year Plans and his decision to form collectives are examples of",
    "option": [
      "strategies to modernize the economy of the Soviet Union through forced communism",
      "a more friendly foreign policy toward China",
      "methods of dealing with the United States during the Cold War",
      "programs to westernize, educate, and enlighten the population"
    ],
    "answer": "strategies to modernize the economy of the Soviet Union through forced communism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1053,
    "question": "A major cause of the Russian Revolution of 1917 was the",
    "option": [
      "defeat of Germany in the Russian campaign",
      "marriage of Czar Nicholas II to a German princess",
      "existence of sharp economic differences between social classes",
      "appeal of Marxism to the Russian nobility"
    ],
    "answer": "existence of sharp economic differences between social classes"
  },
  {
    "id": 1054,
    "question": "Which is an accurate statement about the Soviet economy under the leadership of Joseph Stalin?",
    "option": [
      "a large selection of consumer goods became available",
      "the Soviet Union increased its industrial output by developing heavy industry",
      "private farmers were encouraged to sell their surplus produce in an open market",
      "the government reduced its role in planning industrial production"
    ],
    "answer": "the Soviet Union increased its industrial output by developing heavy industry"
  },
  {
    "id": 1055,
    "question": "A major effect of Josef Stalin s policy of Collectivization on Soviet agriculture was",
    "option": [
      "a widespread food shortage throughout the nation",
      "an increase in the export of agricultural products",
      "a surplus of agricultural goods",
      "the immediate creation of many small private farms"
    ],
    "answer": "a widespread food shortage throughout the nation"
  },
  {
    "id": 1056,
    "question": "One action taken by both V.I. Lenin and Joseph Stalin was",
    "option": [
      "attempting to bring democracy to Russia",
      "jailing or murdering potential opponents",
      "supporting the Russian Orthodox Church",
      "providing economic aid to Japan after World War I and World War II"
    ],
    "answer": "jailing or murdering potential opponents"
  },
  {
    "id": 1057,
    "question": "The Russian peasants supported the Bolsheviks in the 1917 Revolutions mainly because the Bolsheviks promised to",
    "option": [
      "establish collective farms",
      "maintain the agricultural price-support system",
      "bring modern technology to Russian farms",
      "redistribute the land owned by the nobility"
    ],
    "answer": "redistribute the land owned by the nobility"
  },
  {
    "id": 1058,
    "question": "Which statement best describes the political situation in the Soviet Union immediately after Lenin s death in 1924?",
    "option": [
      "the nation adopted a constitutional monarchy",
      "Trotsky and his followers assumed full control of the Communist Party",
      "popular elections were held to choose a new general secretary",
      "a power struggle developed among Communist Party leaders"
    ],
    "answer": "a power struggle developed among Communist Party leaders"
  },
  {
    "id": 1059,
    "question": "The term that best describes the position of Jews in Czarist Russia is",
    "option": [
      "political elite",
      "persecuted minority",
      "landed gentry",
      "military leaders"
    ],
    "answer": "persecuted minority"
  },
  {
    "id": 1060,
    "question": "the organizations of the revolutionaries must consist first, foremost, and mainly of people who make revolutionary activity their profession such an organization must of necessity be not too extensive and as secret as possible",
    "option": [
      "defeat Germany in World War I",
      "establish democracy in Russia",
      "maintain communist power in Western Europe",
      "overthrow the Russian government"
    ],
    "answer": "overthrow the Russian government"
  },
  {
    "id": 1061,
    "question": "The 1917 victory of the communists in Russia was a contradiction of Marxist theory because Russia was",
    "option": [
      "already ruled by a socialist government",
      "involved in World War I",
      "mainly an agricultural society",
      "not considered to be a military power"
    ],
    "answer": "mainly an agricultural society"
  },
  {
    "id": 1062,
    "question": "Josef Stalin s leadership of the Soviet Union can best be characterized as a period of",
    "option": [
      "democratic reform and nationalism",
      "humanism and democracy",
      "religious freedom and tolerance",
      "censorship and terror"
    ],
    "answer": "censorship and terror"
  },
  {
    "id": 1063,
    "question": "The political reorganization of Russia after the Communist Revolution of 1917 resulted in",
    "option": [
      "the establishment of a two-party political system",
      "increased political power for ethnic minorities",
      "a limited monarchy with the czar as a figurehead",
      "a federation of socialist republics"
    ],
    "answer": "a federation of socialist republics"
  },
  {
    "id": 1064,
    "question": "Under Josef Stalin, the Soviet Union emphasized centralized economic planning and Five-Year Plans primarily to",
    "option": [
      "produce more consumer goods",
      "expand exports",
      "create a demand for high-quality imports",
      "develop heavy industry"
    ],
    "answer": "develop heavy industry"
  },
  {
    "id": 1065,
    "question": "Which characteristic was common to both Russia under the Czars and the Soviet Union under Josef Stalin?",
    "option": [
      "a lack of concern about territorial expansion",
      "support of artistic and literary freedom",
      "encouragement of free enterprise",
      "persecution of political dissenters"
    ],
    "answer": "persecution of political dissenters"
  },
  {
    "id": 1066,
    "question": "Under Joseph Stalin, life in the Soviet Union was characterized by",
    "option": [
      "an abundance of consumer goods",
      "political instability and numerous civil wars",
      "support for small family-run farms",
      "the use of censorship and the secret police"
    ],
    "answer": "the use of censorship and the secret police"
  },
  {
    "id": 1067,
    "question": "Which slogan expressed the ideals of the Bolshevik Revolution of 1917?",
    "option": [
      "Liberty, Equality, and Fraternity",
      "Bread, Land, and Peace",
      "Land and Liberty",
      "Nationalism, Democracy, and the People s Livelihood"
    ],
    "answer": "Bread, Land, and Peace"
  },
  {
    "id": 1068,
    "question": "Russian peasants supported the Bolsheviks in 1917 primarily because the Bolsheviks pledged to",
    "option": [
      "establish and maintain collective farms",
      "redistribute land and make peace",
      "keep crop yields low",
      "limit the income of the nobility"
    ],
    "answer": "redistribute land and make peace"
  },
  {
    "id": 1069,
    "question": "Which statement best describes a relationship between World War I and the Bolshevik Revolution?",
    "option": [
      "World War I created conditions in Russia that helped trigger a revolution.",
      "World War I postponed the revolution in Russia by restoring confidence in the Czar.",
      "Opposing Russian forces cooperated to fight the foreign invaders.",
      "World War I gave the Czar s army the needed experience to suppress the revolution."
    ],
    "answer": "World War I created conditions in Russia that helped trigger a revolution."
  },
  {
    "id": 1070,
    "question": "The Kirghiz with whom we stopped was very well off. . . . After some tea our host asked me,  Where is the Ak Padsha now, the White Tsar Nikolai?    He and all his family, the Tsaritsa, their daughters and son, have been killed by the Bolsheviks,  I answered.",
    "option": [
      "during the Napoleonic Wars",
      "after Mao Zedong came to power",
      "after the Russian Revolution",
      "during World War II"
    ],
    "answer": "after the Russian Revolution"
  },
  {
    "id": 1071,
    "question": "In the 1920 s and 1930 s, the rise of totalitarian governments in Germany, Italy, and Spain was largely the result of",
    "option": [
      "the success of the Communists in establishing a command economy in the Soviet Union",
      "severe economic and social problems that arose in Europe after World War I",
      "the active support of the United States",
      "movements demanding the return of the old monarchies"
    ],
    "answer": "severe economic and social problems that arose in Europe after World War I"
  },
  {
    "id": 1072,
    "question": "The harsh conditions imposed by the Treaty of Versailles after World War I helped lay the foundation for the",
    "option": [
      "rise of fascism Germany",
      "uprisings during the French Revolution",
      "division of Korea along the 38th parallel",
      "Bolshevik Revolution in Russia"
    ],
    "answer": "rise of fascism Germany"
  },
  {
    "id": 1073,
    "question": "Between the Meiji Restoration and World War II, Japan tried to solve the problem of its scarcity of natural resources by",
    "option": [
      "exporting agricultural products in exchange for new technology",
      "establishing a policy of imperialism",
      "building nuclear power plants",
      "cooperating with the Soviet Union to gain needed resources"
    ],
    "answer": "establishing a policy of imperialism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1074,
    "question": "Which idea was included in the provisions of the Treaty of Versailles to show the intent of the Allies to punish the Central Powers for their role in World War II?",
    "option": [
      "all nations shall maintain open covenants of peace",
      "freedom of the seas will be maintained",
      "Germany will accept full responsibility for causing the war",
      "territorial settlements shall be made along clearly recognizable lines of nationality"
    ],
    "answer": "Germany will accept full responsibility for causing the war"
  },
  {
    "id": 1075,
    "question": "Fascism in Europe during the 1920 s and 1930 s is best described as a",
    "option": [
      "demonstration of laissez-faire capitalism that promoted free enterprise",
      "form of totalitarianism that glorified the state above the individual",
      "type of economic system that stressed a classless society",
      "set of humanist ideas that emphasized the dignity and worth of the individual"
    ],
    "answer": "form of totalitarianism that glorified the state above the individual"
  },
  {
    "id": 1076,
    "question": "Censorship, mass arrests, and a secret police force are most characteristic of",
    "option": [
      "parliamentary democracies",
      "republics",
      "totalitarian regimes",
      "constitutional monarchies"
    ],
    "answer": "totalitarian regimes"
  },
  {
    "id": 1077,
    "question": "After World War I, Japan attempted to solve some of its economic problems by",
    "option": [
      "establishing extensive trade with the Soviet Union",
      "expanding its influence in Asia",
      "practicing the principles of Marxism",
      "refusing to rely on Western technology"
    ],
    "answer": "expanding its influence in Asia"
  },
  {
    "id": 1078,
    "question": "Which policy shows that appeasement does not always prevent war?",
    "option": [
      "British policy toward Germany in Munich during the 1930 s",
      "French policy in Indochina in the 1950 s",
      "United States policy toward Cuba in the early 1960 s",
      "Iraqi policy toward Iran in the 1980 s"
    ],
    "answer": "British policy toward Germany in Munich during the 1930 s"
  },
  {
    "id": 1079,
    "question": "In the 1930 s, the Japanese government followed a policy of imperialism primarily to",
    "option": [
      "acquire new sources of raw materials",
      "spread Zen Buddhism throughout Asia",
      "sell more consumer goods to European nations",
      "spread the ideas of bushido"
    ],
    "answer": "acquire new sources of raw materials"
  },
  {
    "id": 1080,
    "question": "What was one reason the Nazi programs and policies of the early 1930 s appealed to many people in Germany?",
    "option": [
      "the people were frustrated with their current economic and political situation",
      "Germany had been denied membership in the United Nations",
      "a coup d etat had forced communism on the German people",
      "the German people feared that the French of the British would soon gain control of the Polish corridor"
    ],
    "answer": "the people were frustrated with their current economic and political situation"
  },
  {
    "id": 1081,
    "question": "The imperialist policies followed by Japan after World War I were based on a desire to",
    "option": [
      "convert people to Shinto",
      "acquire markets for its oil industry",
      "compete with Chinese trade policies",
      "obtain natural resources for manufacturing"
    ],
    "answer": "obtain natural resources for manufacturing"
  },
  {
    "id": 1082,
    "question": "During the mid-1930 s, which characteristic was common to Fascist Italy, Nazi Germany, and Communist Russia?",
    "option": [
      "government ownership of the means of production and distribution",
      "one-party system that denied basic human rights",
      "encouragement of individual freedom of expression in the arts",
      "emphasis on consumer goods rather than on weapons"
    ],
    "answer": "one-party system that denied basic human rights"
  },
  {
    "id": 1083,
    "question": "One reason the Fascist governments of Benito Mussolini and Adolf Hitler came to power in Italy",
    "option": [
      "were threatened by the United States",
      "supported civil liberties for all",
      "failed to join the League of Nations",
      "faced economic and political difficulties"
    ],
    "answer": "faced economic and political difficulties"
  },
  {
    "id": 1084,
    "question": "Which was a characteristic of Germany under Adolf Hitler and the Soviet Union under Josef Stalin?",
    "option": [
      "an official foreign policy of isolationism",
      "governmental control of the media",
      "public ownership of business and industry",
      "the absence of a written constitution"
    ],
    "answer": "governmental control of the media"
  },
  {
    "id": 1085,
    "question": "World War II is often considered to be a turning point in history because",
    "option": [
      "the League of nations demonstrated that an international organization could maintain world peace",
      "the war brought an end to dictatorships as a form of government",
      "European domination of the world began to weaken as nationalism in colonies increased",
      "religious and ethnic differences were no longer a source of conflict between nations"
    ],
    "answer": "European domination of the world began to weaken as nationalism in colonies increased"
  },
  {
    "id": 1086,
    "question": "From as early as I can remember, the Emperor was an important presence even in our remote home.  He was a descendant of the gods from thousands of years before, never to be looked at or listened to by mere mortals, a presence to be revered and protected and obeyed Finally , my family and neighbors gathered around the radio and listened in stunned silence to the voice that had never before been heard, saying he was only human after all.  Everyone was crying.  I was sad and confused",
    "option": [
      "his overthrow by communist forces",
      "defeat of the Japanese in World War II",
      "signing of the Versailles Treaty",
      "conclusion of the Russo-Japanese War"
    ],
    "answer": "defeat of the Japanese in World War II"
  },
  {
    "id": 1087,
    "question": "Which reform took place in Japan after World War II?",
    "option": [
      "Japan s industrial capability was greatly reduced",
      "the Emperor s position was abolished",
      "Japan became a representative democracy",
      "labor unions were declared illegal"
    ],
    "answer": "Japan became a representative democracy"
  },
  {
    "id": 1088,
    "question": "A major factor in the economic recoveries of Japan and West Germany after World War II was their",
    "option": [
      "desire to avoid an invasion from China",
      "acceptance into the United Nations",
      "ability to produce nuclear weapons",
      "need to replace destroyed factories"
    ],
    "answer": "need to replace destroyed factories"
  },
  {
    "id": 1089,
    "question": "Which factor most enabled Japan to rebuild and modernize rapidly after World War II?",
    "option": [
      "vast mineral reserves",
      "large amounts of fertile land",
      "a strong military",
      "a well-trained workforce"
    ],
    "answer": "a well-trained workforce"
  },
  {
    "id": 1090,
    "question": "Which is one major reason the Holocaust is considered a unique event in modern European history?",
    "option": [
      "Jews of Europe have seldom been victims of persecution.",
      "Civilians rarely were killed during air raids on Great Britain.",
      "Adolf Hitler concealed his anti-Jewish feelings until after he came to power.",
      "The genocide was planned in great detail and required the cooperation of many people."
    ],
    "answer": "The genocide was planned in great detail and required the cooperation of many people."
  },
  {
    "id": 1091,
    "question": "The economic policies of the Soviet Union traditionally emphasized the production of",
    "option": [
      "automobiles for export",
      "building materials for luxury housing",
      "consumer goods",
      "heavy industrial goods"
    ],
    "answer": "heavy industrial goods"
  },
  {
    "id": 1092,
    "question": "Which is generally a characteristic of a communist economy?",
    "option": [
      "investment is encouraged by the promise of large profits",
      "the role of government in the economy is restricted by law",
      "government agencies are involved in production planning",
      "entrepreneurs sell shares in their companies to the government"
    ],
    "answer": "government agencies are involved in production planning"
  },
  {
    "id": 1093,
    "question": "One reason the Soviet Union formed the Warsaw Pact was to",
    "option": [
      "ease the transition to democracy",
      "help institute capitalism in Eastern Europe",
      "limit the threat of invasion from Western Europe",
      "challenge the economic successes of the Common Market"
    ],
    "answer": "limit the threat of invasion from Western Europe"
  },
  {
    "id": 1094,
    "question": "Which statement best describes most Eastern European countries immediately after World War II?  They",
    "option": [
      "adopted democratic reforms in their political systems",
      "became satellite states of the Soviet Union",
      "became dependent on aid provided by the Marshall Plan",
      "emerged as world economic powers"
    ],
    "answer": "became satellite states of the Soviet Union"
  },
  {
    "id": 1095,
    "question": "Communist governments were established in most nations of Eastern Europe shortly after World War II because",
    "option": [
      "the region had a long tradition of strong communist parties",
      "communist governments were able to significantly increase agricultural productivity",
      "the Soviet Union used military and diplomatic pressures to install their governments",
      "members of the Communist party won free elections in these nations"
    ],
    "answer": "the Soviet Union used military and diplomatic pressures to install their governments"
  },
  {
    "id": 1096,
    "question": "During the Cold War Era (1945-1990), the United States and the Soviet Union were reluctant to become involved in direct military conflict mainly because of",
    "option": [
      "the peacekeeping role of the United Nations",
      "pressure from nonaligned nations",
      "the potential for global nuclear destruction",
      "increased tensions in the Middle East"
    ],
    "answer": "the potential for global nuclear destruction"
  },
  {
    "id": 1097,
    "question": "After World War II, the Soviet Union established satellites in Eastern Europe to",
    "option": [
      "support the remaining Fascist governments in Eastern Europe",
      "preserve capitalism in Eastern Europe",
      "establish democratic governments in Eastern European nations",
      "expand its power and control over Eastern Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "expand its power and control over Eastern Europe"
  },
  {
    "id": 1098,
    "question": "In the Soviet Union, a negative aspect of the Cold War Era was the",
    "option": [
      "attempt to preserve democratic ideals",
      "development of peaceful uses for modern technology",
      "development of effective means of international cooperation",
      "high cost of maintaining the arms race"
    ],
    "answer": "high cost of maintaining the arms race"
  },
  {
    "id": 1099,
    "question": "From Stetin in the Baltic to Trieste in the Adriatic, an Iron Curtain has descended across the continent. Behind that line lie all the capitals of the ancient states of Central and Eastern Europe. Warsaw, Berlin, Prague, Vienna, Budapest, Belgrade, Bucharest and Sofia, all these famous cities and the populations around them lie in what I might call the Soviet Sphere, and all are subject, in one form or another, not only to Soviet influence, but to very high, and in some cases increasing measure of control from Moscow.\"",
    "option": [
      "The Soviet Union has expanded its influence throughout Eastern Europe",
      "The Soviet Union has helped the nations of Eastern Europe improve their standard of living",
      "The democratic nations of Western Europe have stopped the expansion of Soviet influence in the world",
      "The Soviet Union will support communist revolutions in Southeast Asia"
    ],
    "answer": "The Soviet Union has expanded its influence throughout Eastern Europe"
  },
  {
    "id": 1100,
    "question": "Prior to the 1980 s, the emphasis of the Five-Year Plans in the Soviet Union was on heavy industry.  One result was the",
    "option": [
      "scarcity of consumer goods",
      "abundance of manufactured goods",
      "rejection of agricultural planning",
      "decline in military spending"
    ],
    "answer": "scarcity of consumer goods"
  },
  {
    "id": 1101,
    "question": "The Soviet Union s reaction to the 1968 revolt in Czechoslovakia was to",
    "option": [
      "permit limited political and economic reforms in Czechoslovakia",
      "withdraw Soviet troops from Eastern Europe",
      "send Soviet troops to occupy Czechoslovakia",
      "bring the matter to the attention of the United Nations"
    ],
    "answer": "send Soviet troops to occupy Czechoslovakia"
  },
  {
    "id": 1102,
    "question": "Which was a major reason for the success of Soviet domination in Eastern Europe after World War II?",
    "option": [
      "Eastern Europeans accepted the doctrine of Pan-Slavism",
      "the democracies of Western Europe needed greater security",
      "the Soviet Union had military forces in Eastern Europe as a result of World War II",
      "Western Europeans feared that Nazism would be rekindled in Eastern Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "the Soviet Union had military forces in Eastern Europe as a result of World War II"
  },
  {
    "id": 1103,
    "question": "The events that took place in Hungary in the 1950 s and in Czechoslovakia in the 1960 s demonstrated the Soviet Union s",
    "option": [
      "support of nationalism among satellite nations",
      "influence on the economies of developing nations",
      "determination to maintain political control over Eastern Europe at that time",
      "attempts to promote its artistic and literary achievements in Western Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "determination to maintain political control over Eastern Europe at that time"
  },
  {
    "id": 1104,
    "question": "The expansion of communism into Eastern Europe was a direct result of",
    "option": [
      "the Crimean war",
      "the Napoleonic Wars",
      "World War I",
      "World War II"
    ],
    "answer": "World War II"
  },
  {
    "id": 1105,
    "question": "United States involvement in the Vietnam War and the Soviet Union s involvement in Afghanistan were motivated mainly by a desire to",
    "option": [
      "exploit the mineral resources of the regions",
      "support governments that would remain strong allies",
      "stop the expansion of Japan into the Middle East",
      "establish independent nation-states in the regions"
    ],
    "answer": "support governments that would remain strong allies"
  },
  {
    "id": 1106,
    "question": "Warsaw Pact Tanks Invade Budapest\"",
    "option": [
      "Mikhail Gorbachev s introduction of the policy of Glasnost",
      "Adolf Hitler s efforts to promote national socialism",
      "the Soviet Union s acceptance of capitalism",
      "attempts by the Soviet Union to strengthen communist control"
    ],
    "answer": "attempts by the Soviet Union to strengthen communist control"
  },
  {
    "id": 1107,
    "question": "The invasion of Hungary in 1956 by the Soviet Union and the building of the Berlin Wall in 1961 are examples of",
    "option": [
      "United Nations Security Council resolutions",
      "Truman Doctrine failures",
      "Marshall Plan effects",
      "Cold War Era conflicts"
    ],
    "answer": "Truman Doctrine failures"
  },
  {
    "id": 1108,
    "question": "During the Cold War Era, many Asian and African nations followed a policy of nonalignment because they",
    "option": [
      "had the same goals and needs as the Soviet Union",
      "needed the natural resources of Western European nations",
      "wished to receive aid from the Soviet Union and the United States",
      "were afraid of losing their vote in the United Nations"
    ],
    "answer": "wished to receive aid from the Soviet Union and the United States"
  },
  {
    "id": 1109,
    "question": "We believe in nonaggression and noninterference by one country in the affairs of another and the growth of tolerance between them and the capacity for peaceful coexistence.  We, therefore, endeavor to maintain friendly relations with all countries, even though we may disagree with them in their policies.",
    "option": ["imperialism", "mercantilism", "isolationism", "nonalignment"],
    "answer": "nonalignment"
  },
  {
    "id": 1110,
    "question": "Which is a major reason Cuban and Nicaraguan revolutionary movements were attracted to communism?",
    "option": [
      "communist groups promised economic reform and better living standards",
      "business owners and the military were supported by communist groups",
      "the goal of communism was to encourage religion",
      "communist leaders promised to reduce Spanish colonialism in the Western Hemisphere"
    ],
    "answer": "communist groups promised economic reform and better living standards"
  },
  {
    "id": 1111,
    "question": "The main reason the United Nations sent troops to Korea in 1950 was to",
    "option": [
      "ensure that food reached areas of the Korean Peninsula affected by famine",
      "prevent North Korea from conquering the people of South Korea",
      "force the inspection of nuclear weapons plants in North Korea",
      "restore peace between warring factions of Buddhism and Shinto"
    ],
    "answer": "prevent North Korea from conquering the people of South Korea"
  },
  {
    "id": 1112,
    "question": "The conflict between Israel and the Arab nations since 1948 was often considered part of the Cold War primarily because",
    "option": [
      "the policy of detente evolved from this conflict",
      "communist governments were established in many Arab nations",
      "the leadership of Joseph Stalin strongly influenced the policies of Saddam Hussein",
      "the United States supported Israel and the Soviet Union supported several Arab nations"
    ],
    "answer": "the United States supported Israel and the Soviet Union supported several Arab nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 1113,
    "question": "-Berlin Blockade (1948-1949)",
    "option": [
      "throughout the period, the United States and the Soviet Union were reluctant to solve conflicts",
      "the level of tension between the United States and the Soviet Union varied",
      "economics played a key role in causing conflict between the United States and the Soviet Union",
      "the United Nations was instrumental in reducing tensions between the United States and the Soviet Union"
    ],
    "answer": "the level of tension between the United States and the Soviet Union varied"
  },
  {
    "id": 1114,
    "question": "Which statement would be consistent with the views of Fidel Castro?",
    "option": [
      "The spread of communism is the greatest danger facing Latin America",
      "An American military presence is the key to the defense of Latin America",
      "Progress and justice in Latin America can only be achieved through revolutionary socialism",
      "Introducing a free-market system will improve the economies of Latin American nations"
    ],
    "answer": "Progress and justice in Latin America can only be achieved through revolutionary socialism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1115,
    "question": "From the perspective of the North Vietnamese, the war in Vietnam in the 1960 s was a battle between",
    "option": [
      "fascism and liberalism",
      "nationalism and imperialism",
      "republicanism and totalitarianism",
      "theocracy and monarchy"
    ],
    "answer": "nationalism and imperialism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1116,
    "question": "Which headline concerning the Soviet Union refers to a Cold War event?",
    "option": [
      " Yeltsin Assumes Power",
      " Trotsky Forms Red Army",
      " Germany Invades USSR",
      " Warsaw Pact Formed"
    ],
    "answer": " Warsaw Pact Formed"
  },
  {
    "id": 1117,
    "question": "A major development in relations between the Soviet Union and the United States occurred in the late 1980 s when the two nations agreed to",
    "option": [
      "purchase all their oil from Mexico",
      "withdraw from the United Nations",
      "eliminate a group of nuclear missiles",
      "ban arms sales to developing nations"
    ],
    "answer": "eliminate a group of nuclear missiles"
  },
  {
    "id": 1118,
    "question": "During the 1980 s, the Soviet Union experimented with modifications of its command economy by",
    "option": [
      "eliminating central planning",
      "allowing private ownership of major industries",
      "introducing some market economy strategies",
      "legalizing independent trade unions"
    ],
    "answer": "introducing some market economy strategies"
  },
  {
    "id": 1119,
    "question": "In the 30 years after World War II, which area was most influenced by the Soviet Union?",
    "option": [
      "Southeast Asia",
      "North Africa",
      "Eastern Europe",
      "Central America"
    ],
    "answer": "Eastern Europe"
  },
  {
    "id": 1120,
    "question": "Which statement best describes the political situation in Eastern Europe during the 1980 s?",
    "option": [
      "nationalism has often been a strong force for change",
      "communist governments have gained power through democratic elections",
      "ethnic rivalries have been eliminated throughout the region",
      "United States influence has been used to keep communist governments in power"
    ],
    "answer": "nationalism has often been a strong force for change"
  },
  {
    "id": 1121,
    "question": "The withdrawal of France from Indochina, the involvement of the Soviet Union in Cuba, and the United States support of the Contras in Nicaragua illustrate that nations",
    "option": [
      "consistently discard traditional foreign policy goals after changes in administration",
      "tend to base foreign policy decisions on what they believe to be their self-interests",
      "no longer use warfare as a means to resolve international conflict",
      "tend to refer foreign policy conflicts to the United Nations"
    ],
    "answer": "tend to base foreign policy decisions on what they believe to be their self-interests"
  },
  {
    "id": 1122,
    "question": "Which is a valid statement about the Soviet Union from the time of the Bolshevik Revolution through 1991?",
    "option": [
      "Education has been limited to the communist party elite",
      "Demand for consumer goods has exceeded production",
      "Military expenditures have been low",
      "Industrialization has not occurred"
    ],
    "answer": "Demand for consumer goods has exceeded production"
  },
  {
    "id": 1123,
    "question": "In the Soviet Union, Vladimir Lenin s New Economic Policy (NEP) and Mikhail Gorbachev s policy of Perestroika both sought to",
    "option": [
      "increase spending of nuclear weapons",
      "strengthen central planning",
      "increase production through individual enterprise",
      "reduce the influence of middle-class farmers"
    ],
    "answer": "increase production through individual enterprise"
  },
  {
    "id": 1124,
    "question": "During the 1980 s in the Soviet Union, a major element of the economic policy of Perestroika was",
    "option": [
      "increased collectivization of farms",
      "more reliance on local and regional decision making",
      "the expanded use of national Five-Year plans",
      "an emphasis on the redistribution of wealth"
    ],
    "answer": "more reliance on local and regional decision making"
  },
  {
    "id": 1125,
    "question": "Blockade of Berlin    Operation of the Berlin Airlift",
    "option": [
      "efforts to prevent military conflict between the superpowers",
      "situations that increased tensions between communist and democratic nations in Europe",
      "attempts to weaken the Soviet Union s control of its Eastern European allies",
      "policies of peaceful coexistence and d tente"
    ],
    "answer": "situations that increased tensions between communist and democratic nations in Europe"
  },
  {
    "id": 1126,
    "question": "In Eastern Europe during the 1950 s and 1960 s, the Soviet Union responded to challenges to its control by",
    "option": [
      "allowing free elections, when necessary",
      "imposing prompt and severe repression",
      "obtaining United Nations assistance",
      "granting independence to its satellite nations"
    ],
    "answer": "imposing prompt and severe repression"
  },
  {
    "id": 1127,
    "question": "In the People s Republic of China, which factor best reflects Marxism?",
    "option": [
      "communal work teams on farms",
      "ownership of small farms by individuals",
      "small family-owned businesses in villages",
      "foreign influence on the economy"
    ],
    "answer": "communal work teams on farms"
  },
  {
    "id": 1128,
    "question": "The Great Leap Forward in China and the five-year plans in the Soviet Union were attempts to increase",
    "option": [
      "private capital investment",
      "religious tolerance",
      "individual ownership of land",
      "industrial productivity"
    ],
    "answer": "industrial productivity"
  },
  {
    "id": 1129,
    "question": "In China and the former Soviet Union, the communist governments discouraged organized religion because religions",
    "option": [
      "compete for the loyalties of the people",
      "support the principles of laissez-faire",
      "favor anarchy over organized government",
      "stress economic rather than political values"
    ],
    "answer": "compete for the loyalties of the people"
  },
  {
    "id": 1130,
    "question": "A major goal of the Cultural Revolution in China during the 1960 s was to",
    "option": [
      "restore China to the glory of the Han Dynasty",
      "reemphasize Confucian traditional values",
      "weaken communist ideas",
      "eliminate opposition to Mao Zedong"
    ],
    "answer": "eliminate opposition to Mao Zedong"
  },
  {
    "id": 1131,
    "question": "After World War II, the Chinese Communists were successful in their revolution mainly because the",
    "option": [
      "United States refused to support the Nationalists",
      "communists had the support of the peasants",
      "communists had more technologically advanced weapons",
      "nationalist had been defeated by Japan"
    ],
    "answer": "communists had the support of the peasants"
  },
  {
    "id": 1132,
    "question": "An immediate result of the Cultural Revolution in China was that it",
    "option": [
      "helped to establish democracy in urban centers in China",
      "led to economic cooperation with Japan and South Korea",
      "disrupted China s economic and educational systems",
      "strengthened political ties with the United States"
    ],
    "answer": "disrupted China s economic and educational systems"
  },
  {
    "id": 1133,
    "question": "The main reason the Chinese Communists gained control of mainland China in 1949 was that",
    "option": [
      "they were supported by many warlords and upper class Chinese",
      "the United States had supported the Chinese Communist Party during World War II",
      "the dynamic leadership of Mao Zedong had the support of the peasant class",
      "they had superior financial resources and were supported by Japan"
    ],
    "answer": "the dynamic leadership of Mao Zedong had the support of the peasant class"
  },
  {
    "id": 1134,
    "question": "In China, the Great Leap Forward was an attempt to",
    "option": [
      "promote democratic reform",
      "end the private ownership of land",
      "strengthen economic ties with Europe",
      "increase agricultural and industrial production"
    ],
    "answer": "increase agricultural and industrial production"
  },
  {
    "id": 1135,
    "question": "Deng Xioaping s economic reforms in China differ from the previous economic policies of Mao Zedong in that Deng s reforms",
    "option": [
      "discourage private ownership of businesses",
      "promote further collectivization",
      "include elements of capitalism",
      "decrease trade with the United States"
    ],
    "answer": "include elements of capitalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1136,
    "question": "The Confucian view of government and the Chinese Communist view of government were similar in that both stressed",
    "option": [
      "loyalty to the government",
      "the need for filial piety",
      "a civil service system",
      "equality of men and women"
    ],
    "answer": "loyalty to the government"
  },
  {
    "id": 1137,
    "question": "A major reason for the success of the Communist revolution in China was that the Communists",
    "option": [
      "stressed Buddhism in their military training",
      "included important businessmen in their ranks",
      "promised land and power to the peasant class",
      "fought successfully against the United States during World War II"
    ],
    "answer": "promised land and power to the peasant class"
  },
  {
    "id": 1138,
    "question": "In China, the Great Leap Forward and the Cultural Revolution promoted by Mao Zedong were similar in that both plans",
    "option": [
      "ended dynastic rule",
      "disrupted industrial development",
      "encouraged capitalism",
      "guaranteed human rights"
    ],
    "answer": "disrupted industrial development"
  },
  {
    "id": 1139,
    "question": "During the 1980 s, the Chinese government adopted policies designed to",
    "option": [
      "increase industrial productivity",
      "reestablish Confucian traditions and values",
      "gain colonies throughout East Asia",
      "maintain its isolation from world events"
    ],
    "answer": "increase industrial productivity"
  },
  {
    "id": 1140,
    "question": "Which statement about the economy of China in the 1980 s is most accurate?",
    "option": [
      "China surpassed the Soviet Union in steel production",
      "China s economy slowed down because of a lack of natural resources",
      "China increased its industrial capacity and foreign trade",
      "China s economy suffered from overproduction of consumer goods"
    ],
    "answer": "China increased its industrial capacity and foreign trade"
  },
  {
    "id": 1141,
    "question": "Sun Yat-sen s  Three Principles of the People  (1911) and the demonstrations in Tiananmen Square (1989) were similar in that they both demanded that the Chinese government",
    "option": [
      "achieve global interdependence",
      "restore dynastic rule",
      "introduce democratic reforms",
      "end foreign influences in China"
    ],
    "answer": "introduce democratic reforms"
  },
  {
    "id": 1142,
    "question": "The goal of Mao Zedong s policy known as the Great Leap Forward was to",
    "option": [
      "develop foreign export industries in China s coastal urban centers",
      "eliminate state-owned industries in rural China",
      "modernize China s economic system by dividing China into communes",
      "introduce capitalism to the Chinese economy"
    ],
    "answer": "modernize China s economic system by dividing China into communes"
  },
  {
    "id": 1143,
    "question": "Which statement about reforms in China during the 1980 s and 1990 s is most accurate?",
    "option": [
      "Political reforms resulted in the overthrow of communism.",
      "Economic reforms were more successful than political reforms.",
      "Political reforms increased individual rights.",
      "Economic reforms forced China to return to a policy of isolationism."
    ],
    "answer": "Economic reforms were more successful than political reforms."
  },
  {
    "id": 1144,
    "question": "A wind has been blowing from the West; now it will begin to blow from the East.   \tMao Zedong, 1949",
    "option": [
      "The monsoons will soon shift and bring destruction to the mainland of Asia.",
      "Chinese culture will no longer influence the people of Asia.",
      "European power will decline as a new center of power emerges in Asia.",
      "The Asian people have much to learn from the Western Europeans."
    ],
    "answer": "European power will decline as a new center of power emerges in Asia."
  },
  {
    "id": 1145,
    "question": "When I go to the office, I put on my shirt and I take off my Caste; when I come home, I take off my shirt and I put on my Caste.",
    "option": [
      "the Caste system continues to influence Indian society",
      "the Caste system has been reflected by most Indians",
      "successful urban workers in India belong the same Caste",
      "the Indian government officially supports the Caste system"
    ],
    "answer": "the Caste system continues to influence Indian society"
  },
  {
    "id": 1146,
    "question": "Which factor most limited the development of African nationalism?",
    "option": [
      "European support of an educational system based on local traditions and language",
      "the prior experience of Africans with economic self-sufficiency",
      "political boundaries imposed by Europeans that had little relationship to African tribal boundaries",
      "the European practice of making decisions based on local customs"
    ],
    "answer": "political boundaries imposed by Europeans that had little relationship to African tribal boundaries"
  },
  {
    "id": 1147,
    "question": "One way in which Kwame Nkurmah, Jomo Kenyatta, and Kenneth Kaunda are similar is that they all",
    "option": [
      "supported the United Nations military action in the Persian Gulf War",
      "played a major role in independence movements in Africa",
      "rejected financial aid from the World Bank",
      "opposed the Pan-African movement"
    ],
    "answer": "played a major role in independence movements in Africa"
  },
  {
    "id": 1148,
    "question": "Which statement best describes the political situation in Africa after World War II?",
    "option": [
      "increased nationalism led to independence for many African nations",
      "France and West Germany sought to establish colonies in Africa",
      "European nations increased their control over their African colonies",
      "the United Nations opposed the idea of self-determination for African nations"
    ],
    "answer": "increased nationalism led to independence for many African nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 1149,
    "question": "If we are to remain free, if we are to enjoy the full benefits of Africa s enormous wealth, we must unite to plan for the full exploitation of our human and material resources in the interest of all our people",
    "option": ["colonialism", "Pan-Africanism", "imperialism", "urbanization"],
    "answer": "Pan-Africanism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1150,
    "question": "After World War II, which action was taken by many African territories?",
    "option": [
      "demanding independence from their colonial rulers",
      "refusing to join international organizations",
      "rejecting most of the technology offered by western nations",
      "creating a strong, united Africa"
    ],
    "answer": "demanding independence from their colonial rulers"
  },
  {
    "id": 1151,
    "question": "Mohandas Gandhi is best known for his",
    "option": [
      "use of passive resistance to achieve Indian independence",
      "desire to establish and Islamic nations",
      "opposition to Hindus holding political office",
      "encouragement of violence to end British rule"
    ],
    "answer": "use of passive resistance to achieve Indian independence"
  },
  {
    "id": 1152,
    "question": "The primary goal of the Indian National Congress (1855-1947) was to",
    "option": [
      "reform the Hindu religion",
      "partition India between Muslims and Hindus",
      "create a socialist economy",
      "gain independence from Great Britain"
    ],
    "answer": "gain independence from Great Britain"
  },
  {
    "id": 1153,
    "question": "The rise of independent states in Asia and Africa after World War II demonstrates the",
    "option": [
      "failure of nationalist movements",
      "influence of socialism",
      "success of United Nations peacekeeping forces",
      "decline of European colonial empires"
    ],
    "answer": "decline of European colonial empires"
  },
  {
    "id": 1154,
    "question": "Which action best illustrates Mohandas Gandhi s concept of civil disobedience?",
    "option": [
      "a British army outpost was bombed as a protest against the British presence in Northern Ireland",
      "citizens in the United States went to jail for violation segregation laws",
      "French citizens wrote letters to their government to oppose arms sale to Iraq",
      "supporters of Ferdinand Marcos attempted a coup d etat against the Philippine government"
    ],
    "answer": "citizens in the United States went to jail for violation segregation laws"
  },
  {
    "id": 1155,
    "question": "Which has been a characteristic of many Southeast Asian countries since World War II?",
    "option": [
      "internal struggles for power that lead to political instability",
      "isolation from the influence of the superpowers",
      "democratic governments based on the principles of the French Revolution",
      "fundamentalist Islamic governments supported by Iran"
    ],
    "answer": "internal struggles for power that lead to political instability"
  },
  {
    "id": 1156,
    "question": "Which event was used by Mohandas Gandhi to bring world attention to the injustices of British colonialism?",
    "option": [
      "salt march",
      "partition of India",
      "Sepoy Mutiny",
      "formation of the Indian parliament"
    ],
    "answer": "salt march"
  },
  {
    "id": 1157,
    "question": "Since the 1950 s, India has experienced conflict with both Pakistan and China over",
    "option": [
      "United Nations peacekeeping efforts in the region",
      "India s increasing trade with Korea",
      "borders and related territorial issues",
      "the interpretation of common religious works"
    ],
    "answer": "borders and related territorial issues"
  },
  {
    "id": 1158,
    "question": "Which statement best reflects a belief of Mohandas Gandhi?",
    "option": [
      "Muslims and Hindus must be separated if true peace is to come to India",
      "India must adopt the British factory system",
      "The caste system must remain an important cornerstone of Hindu society",
      "India must achieve independence, but not at the expense of further dividing the Indian people"
    ],
    "answer": "India must achieve independence, but not at the expense of further dividing the Indian people"
  },
  {
    "id": 1159,
    "question": "Since India s independence in 1947, the government has had the greatest success in",
    "option": [
      "increasing overall food production",
      "reducing the population",
      "eliminating religious conflict",
      "controlling industrial pollution"
    ],
    "answer": "increasing overall food production"
  },
  {
    "id": 1160,
    "question": "The Canal was dug by Egypt s sons and 120,000 of them died while working.  The Suez Canal Company in Paris is an imposter company.  It usurped our concessions  Therefore, I have signed today the following law which has been approved by the Cabinet: Article 1 of the decree reads,  The Universal Company of the Suez Maritime Canal Egyptian Joint-Stock Company   is hereby nationalized. All its assets, rights and obligations are hereby transferred to the Nation.",
    "option": [
      "end trade with Mediterranean countries",
      "stop building canals",
      "take control of the Suez Canal",
      "sell the Suez Canal to France"
    ],
    "answer": "take control of the Suez Canal"
  },
  {
    "id": 1161,
    "question": "One reason India gained its independence from Great Britain in 1947 was that",
    "option": [
      "Great Britain was defeated in World War II",
      "the Treaty of Versailles required Great Britain to give up its colonies",
      "Great Britain did not have the resources to maintain an empire after World War II",
      "India had supported the Axis Powers during World War II"
    ],
    "answer": "Great Britain did not have the resources to maintain an empire after World War II"
  },
  {
    "id": 1162,
    "question": "One important similarity between Indira Gandhi of India and Benazir Bhutto of Pakistan is that both",
    "option": [
      "are Hindu leaders of Islamic nations",
      "became important national leaders in nations in which women have not traditionally had equal opportunities",
      "came into power as a result of the breakup of the Soviet Union",
      "became leaders of the Asian bloc of nations at the United Nations"
    ],
    "answer": "became important national leaders in nations in which women have not traditionally had equal opportunities"
  },
  {
    "id": 1163,
    "question": "One similarity between the Sepoys in India, the Boxers in China, and the Mau Mau in Kenya is that these groups",
    "option": [
      "tried to drive Europeans out of their countries",
      "depended on Western support for their success",
      "adopted Marxist economic and political principles",
      "sought independence through nonviolence"
    ],
    "answer": "tried to drive Europeans out of their countries"
  },
  {
    "id": 1164,
    "question": "The  homespun movement  and the Salt March promoted by Mohandas Gandhi in India are examples of his policy of",
    "option": [
      "industrialization",
      "isolationism",
      "nonalignment",
      "nonviolent protest"
    ],
    "answer": "nonviolent protest"
  },
  {
    "id": 1165,
    "question": "Which statement best explains why India was partitioned in 1947?",
    "option": [
      "the British feared a united India",
      "one region wanted to remain under British control",
      "religious differences led to political division",
      "communist supporters wanted a separate state"
    ],
    "answer": "religious differences led to political division"
  },
  {
    "id": 1166,
    "question": "During India s independence movement, Mohandas Gandhi s boycott of British-made products was effective because the British considered India a major",
    "option": [
      "shipping center",
      "industrial center",
      "market for manufactured goods",
      "source of mineral resources"
    ],
    "answer": "market for manufactured goods"
  },
  {
    "id": 1167,
    "question": "The stability of many African nations continues to be threatened by the",
    "option": [
      "spread of Animism among the people",
      "ethnic and tribal loyalties of the people",
      "use of command economies",
      "establishment of labor unions"
    ],
    "answer": "ethnic and tribal loyalties of the people"
  },
  {
    "id": 1168,
    "question": "The war between India and Pakistan in Kashmir in 1965, the sending of Indian troops to Sir Lanka in 1987, and the assassination of Rajiv Gandhi in 1991 all demonstrate that in South Asia",
    "option": [
      "a. the Shino religion is a significant force",
      "a. United Nations peacekeeping forces are ineffective",
      "b. regional and ethnic rivalries remain strong",
      "c. nations are vulnerable to a communist takeover"
    ],
    "answer": "b. regional and ethnic rivalries remain strong"
  },
  {
    "id": 1169,
    "question": "In India today, the continued discrimination based on caste illustrates",
    "option": [
      "a. a commitment to a capitalist economic system",
      "b. the gap between law and tradition",
      "c. the influence of the Cold War on India",
      "c. the declining role of religion in modern society"
    ],
    "answer": "b. the gap between law and tradition"
  },
  {
    "id": 1170,
    "question": "India has developed a mixed economy that",
    "option": [
      "a. guarantees government control over the economy",
      "b. provides open competition without government interference",
      "c. blends free enterprise with socialism",
      "d. relies on the traditional barter system"
    ],
    "answer": "c. blends free enterprise with socialism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1171,
    "question": "During the 1980 s, national unity in India was hindered by",
    "option": [
      "a. a foreign policy of nonalignment",
      "b. continued fear of attack from the Soviet Union",
      "c. political interference from China",
      "c. conflicts between Sikhs, Hindus, and Muslims"
    ],
    "answer": "c. conflicts between Sikhs, Hindus, and Muslims"
  },
  {
    "id": 1172,
    "question": "With which nation are Pol Pot, the Khmer Rouge, and genocide associated?",
    "option": ["Korea", "Japan", "Myanmar (Burma)", "Cambodia (Kampuchea)"],
    "answer": "Cambodia (Kampuchea)"
  },
  {
    "id": 1173,
    "question": "--Rebellion in the Congo during the 1960 s  --Civil war in Nigeria from 1967 to 1970",
    "option": [
      "poor food distribution systems",
      "communist interference",
      "demands for land reform",
      "ethnic rivalries"
    ],
    "answer": "ethnic rivalries"
  },
  {
    "id": 1174,
    "question": "In some African nations today, ethnic rivalries erupt when",
    "option": [
      "political differences are motivated by ancient resentments",
      "trading companies hire nonunion workers",
      "scarce funds halt the exploration for mineral resources",
      "groups share a common heritage"
    ],
    "answer": "political differences are motivated by ancient resentments"
  },
  {
    "id": 1175,
    "question": "Which statement is most accurate about many African societies today?",
    "option": [
      "modern medicines have been ineffective in decreasing infant mortality throughout Africa",
      "new attitudes and values often clash with traditional tribal practices",
      "agriculture is no longer the most important economic activity in Africa",
      "European influence no longer exists in the former colonial territories"
    ],
    "answer": "new attitudes and values often clash with traditional tribal practices"
  },
  {
    "id": 1176,
    "question": "Which situation would best encourage economic development in most African nations today?",
    "option": [
      "a. increasing the population growth rate",
      "b. attracting investment capital",
      "c. reducing the number of skilled workers",
      "d. depleting their natural resources"
    ],
    "answer": "b. attracting investment capital"
  },
  {
    "id": 1177,
    "question": "The caste system is still practiced in India today primarily because it is",
    "option": [
      "encouraged by village customs and traditions",
      "enforced by the military",
      "supported by Christian and Muslim teachings",
      "mandated by law"
    ],
    "answer": "encouraged by village customs and traditions"
  },
  {
    "id": 1178,
    "question": "In 1991, Pakistan amended its constitution and made the Koran the basis of all its laws.  Which group was responsible for this action?",
    "option": [
      "Kashmir separatists",
      "Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO)",
      "Buddhist monks",
      "Islamic fundamentalists"
    ],
    "answer": "Islamic fundamentalists"
  },
  {
    "id": 1179,
    "question": "In India, the people have resisted changing their attitudes toward the caste system because",
    "option": [
      "national Muslim leaders have supported the caste system",
      "the government is unwilling to end the caste system",
      "continued religious conflict prevents changes in the caste system",
      "the Hindu beliefs of karma and dharma reinforce the caste system"
    ],
    "answer": "the Hindu beliefs of karma and dharma reinforce the caste system"
  },
  {
    "id": 1180,
    "question": "Today you won t find a single African head of state who stands on a podium and declares:  I am a Marxist.  Instead all the talk is about currency, private enterprise, and getting hold of capital.    --Tei Mante of Ghana",
    "option": [
      "African nations remain heavily dependent on China and North Korea for trade, capital, and food",
      "African nations are more concerned with obtaining investment capital than with discussing political philosophies",
      "African nations realize they must cooperate",
      "the failure of capitalism in Africa has helped the communists grow in strength"
    ],
    "answer": "African nations are more concerned with obtaining investment capital than with discussing political philosophies"
  },
  {
    "id": 1181,
    "question": "The actions of Jomo Kenyatta, Kwame Nkrumah, Leopold Senghor, and Julius Nyerere were most closely associated with",
    "option": [
      "a rise in nationalism in several African countries",
      "the end of apartheid in South Africa",
      "a resurgence of colonialism in east Africa",
      "the revival of Islam in northern Africa"
    ],
    "answer": "a rise in nationalism in several African countries"
  },
  {
    "id": 1182,
    "question": "The wars that took place in the Democratic Republic of the Congo and Nigeria in the 1960 s and in Rwanda and Somalia in the early 1990 s are similar in that these wars were caused in part by disputes",
    "option": [
      "over water sources",
      "over oil and mineral rights",
      "between ethnic groups",
      "between communist and noncommunist forces"
    ],
    "answer": "between ethnic groups"
  },
  {
    "id": 1183,
    "question": "Indian National Congress Refuses To Support British War Effort    Indians Answer Call for the Production of Homespun Cloth",
    "option": [
      "attempts by the native people to gain Indian independence",
      "political reorganization in the British colonia empire",
      "programs to increase India s standard of living",
      "the benefits of economic interdependence between Britain and India"
    ],
    "answer": "attempts by the native people to gain Indian independence"
  },
  {
    "id": 1184,
    "question": "After World War II, the conflict between Hindus and Muslims in India resulted in the",
    "option": [
      "near genocide of the Hindu population",
      "creation of the Muslim state of Pakistan",
      "forced removal of most Hindus from northern and western India",
      "decision of Mohandas Gandhi to seek election as Prime Minister of India"
    ],
    "answer": "creation of the Muslim state of Pakistan"
  },
  {
    "id": 1185,
    "question": "Which statement is valid about the history of Southeast Asia?",
    "option": [
      "Industrialization has strengthened the traditional beliefs and lifestyles of the people.",
      "The area has experienced little European contact.",
      "Superpower influence has brought peace and prosperity to the region.",
      "Religious beliefs have both unified and divided the people of the region."
    ],
    "answer": "Religious beliefs have both unified and divided the people of the region."
  },
  {
    "id": 1186,
    "question": "Since Nigeria s independence in 1960, its government has frequently shifted between democracy and military dictatorship. This situation suggests that",
    "option": [
      "some Nigerians support British colonialism",
      "international problems are more easily solved by military governments",
      "democracy is often difficult to establish in nations where little democratic tradition exists",
      "economic prosperity is frequently achieved by military governments"
    ],
    "answer": "democracy is often difficult to establish in nations where little democratic tradition exists"
  },
  {
    "id": 1187,
    "question": "The desire for self-determination in African nations became a powerful force for change immediately after",
    "option": [
      "World War II",
      "the Boer War",
      "revolutions in Russia and France",
      "the end of the Cold War"
    ],
    "answer": "World War II"
  },
  {
    "id": 1188,
    "question": "Rhodesia Becomes Zimbabwe    Gold Coast Becomes Ghana",
    "option": [
      "avoid military overthrow",
      "reflect traditional cultures",
      "reinforce colonial influences",
      "increase foreign investments"
    ],
    "answer": "reflect traditional cultures"
  },
  {
    "id": 1189,
    "question": "In India today, a major reason the caste system remains strongest in rural areas is that",
    "option": [
      "economic change occurs rapidly in villages",
      "village laws have resulted in immediate social change",
      "tradition remains a strong influence in small villages",
      "Islam is the dominant religion"
    ],
    "answer": "tradition remains a strong influence in small villages"
  },
  {
    "id": 1190,
    "question": "During the Cold War period, India s foreign policy was committed to",
    "option": [
      "supporting communism in Asia",
      "rejecting democracy in Pakistan",
      "nonalignment with the world powers",
      "isolationism in international commerce"
    ],
    "answer": "nonalignment with the world powers"
  },
  {
    "id": 1191,
    "question": "Since the end of World War II, military rearmament in Japan has been limited by",
    "option": [
      "specific restrictions in Japan s constitution",
      "Japan s refusal to sign a nuclear nonproliferation treaty",
      "the United Nations refusal to sell weapons to the Japanese",
      "a scarcity of technology and resources in Japan"
    ],
    "answer": "specific restrictions in Japan s constitution"
  },
  {
    "id": 1192,
    "question": "A sense of national unity has been difficult to maintain in India because of",
    "option": [
      "its reliance on foreign aid",
      "the emergence of a mixed economic system",
      "the continuing influence of militarism",
      "the desire of religious groups for greater autonomy"
    ],
    "answer": "the desire of religious groups for greater autonomy"
  },
  {
    "id": 1193,
    "question": "Which statement about the problems of Indian independence is a fact rather than an opinion?",
    "option": [
      "Stronger government leadership would have prevented bloodshed.",
      "Control of India by Great Britain brought more benefits than difficulties.",
      "Muslim leaders wanted their own separate Muslim state.",
      "India would have been more prosperous if it had remained a colony."
    ],
    "answer": "Muslim leaders wanted their own separate Muslim state."
  },
  {
    "id": 1194,
    "question": "East Africa is changing. . . . When my children go . . . with us to visit my parents",
    "option": [
      "political problems of developing nations",
      "ethnic conflicts",
      "conflict between tradition and modernization",
      "prejudice against elderly family members"
    ],
    "answer": "conflict between tradition and modernization"
  },
  {
    "id": 1195,
    "question": "The main course of the Arab-Israeli conflicts from 1948 to 1973 was the clash between",
    "option": [
      "Islamic Fundamentalism and Orthodox Judaism",
      "Arab socialism and Israeli capitalism",
      "Arab nationalism and Jewish nationalism",
      "Israeli technology and Saudi Arabian economic goals"
    ],
    "answer": "Arab nationalism and Jewish nationalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1196,
    "question": "In Iran, the Revolution of 1979 and the rise of Islamic fundamentalism resulted in",
    "option": [
      "an increase in woman s rights",
      "the westernization and modernization of the nation",
      "a return to many traditional customs",
      "the introduction of a democratic form of government"
    ],
    "answer": "a return to many traditional customs"
  },
  {
    "id": 1197,
    "question": "Who were David Ben-Gurion, Golda Meir, and Menachem Begin?",
    "option": [
      "leaders of the modern state of Israel",
      "scientist who developed better methods of discovering oil",
      "clergy who supported Islamic Fundamentalism",
      "Egyptian presidents who encouraged peace with Israel"
    ],
    "answer": "leaders of the modern state of Israel"
  },
  {
    "id": 1198,
    "question": "During the late 1980 s and early 1990 s the greatest threat to the stability of the nations of Egypt, Algeria, and Morocco was the",
    "option": [
      "rising standard of living of their citizens",
      "economic reforms taking place in Eastern Europe",
      "rise of Islamic Fundamentalism",
      "lack of financial aid from the United States"
    ],
    "answer": "rise of Islamic Fundamentalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1199,
    "question": "Israel is a country that has",
    "option": [
      "an abundance of oil",
      "a democratically elected government",
      "Islam as its official religion",
      "friendly ties to Jordan"
    ],
    "answer": "a democratically elected government"
  },
  {
    "id": 1200,
    "question": "In 1979, the signing of the Camp David Accords by Egypt and Israel indicated that",
    "option": [
      "nationalism was no longer a force in middle Eastern politics",
      "the differences between Shi ite and Sunni Moslems had been settled",
      "former enemies were able to negotiate",
      "the Soviet Union dominated Middle Eastern affairs"
    ],
    "answer": "former enemies were able to negotiate"
  },
  {
    "id": 1201,
    "question": "During the 1980 s, the economic development of Iran and Iraq was disrupted because of",
    "option": [
      "increased emphasis on agricultural production for export",
      "the war fought between these nations",
      "communist revolutionary movements in these nations",
      "severe drought and famine in the area"
    ],
    "answer": "the war fought between these nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 1202,
    "question": "A major factor that continues to contribute to terrorist activities in the Middle East is",
    "option": [
      "a decrease in crude oil prices on the world market",
      "the Palestinian effort to establish a homeland",
      "the presence of United Nations forces in Syria",
      "the worldwide rejection of violence as a means to end conflict"
    ],
    "answer": "the Palestinian effort to establish a homeland"
  },
  {
    "id": 1203,
    "question": "The 1979 Islamic Revolution in Iran was a reaction to the failure of Shah Reza Pahlavi to",
    "option": [
      "modernize the nation s economy",
      "meet the social and political needs of the people",
      "establish political ties with western nations",
      "supply the military with advanced weapons technology"
    ],
    "answer": "meet the social and political needs of the people"
  },
  {
    "id": 1204,
    "question": "During the 1980 s the governments of Libya and Iran were similar in that both were linked to",
    "option": [
      "efforts to separate religion and politics",
      "advocates of judicial reform",
      "incidents of international terrorism",
      "promotion of democratic principles in third world nations"
    ],
    "answer": "incidents of international terrorism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1205,
    "question": "The actions of most Islamic fundamentalists show that they support",
    "option": [
      "a Zionist movement",
      "equal rights for women",
      "traditional Muslim teachings",
      "a renewed attempt at modernization"
    ],
    "answer": "traditional Muslim teachings"
  },
  {
    "id": 1206,
    "question": "In most of the nations of the Middle East, a major long-term economic concern will be the need for",
    "option": [
      "unskilled labor",
      "imported oil",
      "diversified industry",
      "herds of camels"
    ],
    "answer": "diversified industry"
  },
  {
    "id": 1207,
    "question": "Which type of government did Ayatollah Khomeini establish as a result of the Iranian Revolution in 1979?",
    "option": [
      "constitutional monarchy",
      "fundamentalist Islamic state",
      "democratic republic",
      "radical Marxist regime"
    ],
    "answer": "fundamentalist Islamic state"
  },
  {
    "id": 1208,
    "question": "One similarity in the leadership of Kemal Ataturk, Gamal Nasser, and Shah Reza Pahlavi is that all these leaders",
    "option": [
      "sought to modernize their nations",
      "came to power as a result of democratic elections",
      "encouraged their people to convert to Hinduism",
      "led invasions into Israel"
    ],
    "answer": "sought to modernize their nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 1209,
    "question": "As a peace process continues in the Middle East, a major stumbling block to a settlement of the Arab-Israeli conflict is the question of",
    "option": [
      "ownership and operation of the Suez Canal",
      "control of the Arabian Peninsula",
      "representation of Palestinian Arabs and Israelis",
      "land and civil rights for Palestinian Arabs"
    ],
    "answer": "land and civil rights for Palestinian Arabs"
  },
  {
    "id": 1210,
    "question": "The Middle Eastern leaders Kemal Ataturk, David Ben-Gurion, and Yasir Arafat are best known for their support of",
    "option": ["nationalism", "fascism", "colonialism", "communism"],
    "answer": "nationalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1211,
    "question": "The time has come for you to go  Live where you like, but not among us...",
    "option": ["socialism", "absolutism", "humanitarianism", "nationalism"],
    "answer": "nationalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1212,
    "question": "In the 1990 s, the action by the Israeli Government that has most divided Israeli society has been the decision to",
    "option": [
      "grant control of part of the West Bank and Gaza Strip to the Palestinians",
      "support the United States led Allied Coalition during the Persian Gulf War",
      "support the Camp David accords",
      "oppose Islamic fundamentalist rule in Iran"
    ],
    "answer": "grant control of part of the West Bank and Gaza Strip to the Palestinians"
  },
  {
    "id": 1213,
    "question": "The response of the international community to Iraq s invasion of Kuwait in 1990 best illustrates the",
    "option": [
      "lack of cooperation between the major world powers",
      "global acceptance of imperialism",
      "effect of oil on world politics",
      "ineffectiveness of United Nations peacekeeping forces"
    ],
    "answer": "effect of oil on world politics"
  },
  {
    "id": 1214,
    "question": "The statements below refer to changes in Afghanistan in the 1990 s.     The Taliban controls the government.",
    "option": [
      "Marxist ideology",
      "liberation theology",
      "constitutional reforms",
      "Islamic fundamentalism"
    ],
    "answer": "Islamic fundamentalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1215,
    "question": "Which conclusion is best supported by this cartoon?",
    "option": [
      "Imprisonment of political dissidents rarely ends opposition to the government.",
      "The United Nations supports punishment for acts of civil disobedience.",
      "Better media coverage would prevent the imprisonment of protesters.",
      "Mistreatment of political prisoners often results in their acceptance of government policies."
    ],
    "answer": "Imprisonment of political dissidents rarely ends opposition to the government."
  },
  {
    "id": 1216,
    "question": "In the Republic of South Africa, the primary goal of the African National Congress (ANC) has been to",
    "option": [
      "eliminate communist influence",
      "rule as the majority political party",
      "create a united Africa",
      "promote homeland areas for Blacks"
    ],
    "answer": "rule as the majority political party"
  },
  {
    "id": 1217,
    "question": "In the 1980 s, global concern for Blacks in the Republic of South Africa led many nations to",
    "option": [
      "impose economic sanctions on South Africa",
      "demand that Whites return to their European homelands",
      "sent troops to South Africa",
      "support policies of Apartheid"
    ],
    "answer": "impose economic sanctions on South Africa"
  },
  {
    "id": 1218,
    "question": "The Very First Thing You Should Know About South African Stocks and Bonds     Two Leading Financial Institutions Show You Around South Africa s Banking World",
    "option": [
      "a continuation of the international trade sanctions imposed on South Africa in 1985",
      "a renewed interest in investing in South Africa s economy",
      "the hazards associated with overseas economic investment",
      "a belief that the banks and the bond market in South Africa are inferior to those in Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "a renewed interest in investing in South Africa s economy"
  },
  {
    "id": 1219,
    "question": "In which way has the end of apartheid had a positive economic effect on South Africa?",
    "option": [
      "Black South African managers have increased industrial productivity throughout the nation",
      "the introduction of communism has led to a more equal distribution of income",
      "many foreign companies have resumed trading and investing in South Africa",
      "all profits of South Africa s industries are now reinvested out of the country"
    ],
    "answer": "many foreign companies have resumed trading and investing in South Africa"
  },
  {
    "id": 1220,
    "question": "Which statement best characterizes the period of apartheid in South Africa?",
    "option": [
      "the majority of the population had the right to vote",
      "the Boers attempted to conquer Nigeria",
      "many racist ideas of the ruling minority were adopted into laws",
      "French was declared the official language of the nation"
    ],
    "answer": "many racist ideas of the ruling minority were adopted into laws"
  },
  {
    "id": 1221,
    "question": "In the Republic of South Africa, the slogans  Freedom in Our Lifetime  and  New South Africa  changed from promises to reality after",
    "option": [
      "Frederik W. de Klerk took over the radical white police force",
      "Untied Nations troops occupied the Transvaal",
      "Nelson Mandela was elected President",
      "the majority of white South Africans returned to Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "Nelson Mandela was elected President"
  },
  {
    "id": 1222,
    "question": "A major problem currently facing the Republic of South Africa is the",
    "option": [
      "continuation of attacks from neighboring Zimbabwe",
      "move toward the creation of a theocratic state",
      "struggle for power between different groups within South Africa s black majority",
      "continued international economic embargo against South Africa"
    ],
    "answer": "struggle for power between different groups within South Africa s black majority"
  },
  {
    "id": 1223,
    "question": "Since the end of apartheid in South Africa, what has been one of the major challenges to the current government?",
    "option": [
      "establishing diplomatic relations with Europe",
      "resolving regional and ethnic rivalries",
      "guaranteeing religious freedom for all groups",
      "improving transportation throughout the country"
    ],
    "answer": "resolving regional and ethnic rivalries"
  },
  {
    "id": 1224,
    "question": "What is the main idea of this 1991 cartoon?",
    "option": [
      "The unification of Germany has been hurt by poor leadership in the country.",
      "The economic differences between East and West Germany have limited the growth of the total German economy.",
      "East Germany's strong economy has strengthened a united Germany.",
      "Both East Germany and West Germany have contributed equally to the new economy of a reunified Germany."
    ],
    "answer": "The economic differences between East and West Germany have limited the growth of the total German economy."
  },
  {
    "id": 1225,
    "question": "During the late 1980 s, the Soviet Union experienced internal unrest mainly as a result of",
    "option": [
      "widespread protests against involvement in Afghanistan",
      "a lack of raw materials and natural resources",
      "a failure to use modern technology in the military",
      "increased demands of minority ethnic groups"
    ],
    "answer": "increased demands of minority ethnic groups"
  },
  {
    "id": 1226,
    "question": "During the presidency of Mikhail Gorbachev, which problem faced the Soviet Union?",
    "option": [
      "ethnic minorities demanded the right of self-determination",
      "agricultural production grew faster than food consumption",
      "the nations of Eastern Europe insisted that the Soviet Union keep troops in Eastern Europe",
      "Western European nations refused to trade with the Soviet Union"
    ],
    "answer": "ethnic minorities demanded the right of self-determination"
  },
  {
    "id": 1227,
    "question": "Article 50 in accordance with the interests of the people and in order to strengthen and develop the socialist system, citizens of the USSR are guaranteed freedom of speech of the press, and of assembly, meetings, street processions and demonstrations.   Exercise of these political freedoms is ensured by putting public buildings, streets and squares at the disposal of the working people and their organizations, by broad dissemination of information, and by the opportunity to use the press, television, and radio.",
    "option": [
      "constitutional rights guarantee a free society",
      "a national constitution always guarantees human rights",
      "a constitutional guarantee must be very specific in order to be effective",
      "a constitutional guarantee may be limited by government actions"
    ],
    "answer": "a constitutional guarantee may be limited by government actions"
  },
  {
    "id": 1228,
    "question": "During the 1980 s, Mikhail Gorbachev introduced Perestroika in the Soviet Union to",
    "option": [
      "improve the economy and decentralize decision making",
      "abandon arms treaties with the United States and Western Europe",
      "tighten government controls over the communication media",
      "suppress the growing nationalist movements in Eastern Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "improve the economy and decentralize decision making"
  },
  {
    "id": 1229,
    "question": "The revolt in Hungary (1956), the demonstrations in Czechoslovakia (1968), and the formation of solidarity in Poland (1980 s) are similar in that they",
    "option": [
      "were movements in restore the power of the aristocracy",
      "were tolerated by the communist leaders, who accepted the need for change",
      "represented a challenge to communist leadership",
      "represented attempts to rid these countries of western ideas and influence"
    ],
    "answer": "represented a challenge to communist leadership"
  },
  {
    "id": 1230,
    "question": "One result of the collapse of the Soviet Union has been that",
    "option": [
      "some former republics have reorganized the Warsaw Pact",
      "ethnic violence has broken out in some regions",
      "an era of peace and stability has emerged in most of the former republics",
      "the republics have made an east transition to a market economy"
    ],
    "answer": "ethnic violence has broken out in some regions"
  },
  {
    "id": 1231,
    "question": "Polish Communist Party Fails in Election Bid    Romanians Depose Communist Dictator",
    "option": [
      "military buildups are continuing in Eastern Europe",
      "planned economies in Eastern Europe have become increasingly successful",
      "demands for democracy ended many totalitarian governments in Eastern Europe",
      "the Soviet Union stopped independence efforts in Eastern Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "demands for democracy ended many totalitarian governments in Eastern Europe"
  },
  {
    "id": 1232,
    "question": "The Soviet Union Splits into 15 Republics    Yugoslavia Experiences Internal Conflict",
    "option": [
      "communism remains an important force in Europe",
      "many Western European nations are experiencing civil war",
      "international sanctions strengthen a nation s ability to govern",
      "the forces of nationalism can either divide of unite a nation"
    ],
    "answer": "the forces of nationalism can either divide of unite a nation"
  },
  {
    "id": 1233,
    "question": "The initial reaction of the Russian government to the fighting that broke out in Chechnya in the 1990 s demonstrated that Russia",
    "option": [
      "is unwilling to grant independence to dissenting ethnic groups",
      "has little control over its arsenal of nuclear weapons",
      "will defend its remaining republics against foreign invasion",
      "favors reestablishing communism"
    ],
    "answer": "is unwilling to grant independence to dissenting ethnic groups"
  },
  {
    "id": 1234,
    "question": "In many Latin American nations, the leadership roles assumed by the military and by the Roman Catholic Church evolved from",
    "option": [
      "Native American beliefs",
      "the development of the triangular trade",
      "the effects of matriarchal societies",
      "Spanish colonial rule"
    ],
    "answer": "Spanish colonial rule"
  },
  {
    "id": 1235,
    "question": "In many Latin American nations, which group has most resisted social and economic changes since the end of World War II?",
    "option": [
      "poor farmers",
      "the military",
      "union leaders",
      "the middle class"
    ],
    "answer": "the military"
  },
  {
    "id": 1236,
    "question": "The main purpose of the Organization of American States (OAS) is to",
    "option": [
      "integrate the economies of Latin American nations",
      "encourage United States military involvement in the region",
      "destroy the power of Colombian drug lords",
      "provide a way to resolve regional problems peacefully"
    ],
    "answer": "provide a way to resolve regional problems peacefully"
  },
  {
    "id": 1237,
    "question": "During the last ten years, what has occurred in many of the nations of Latin America?",
    "option": [
      "successful communist revolutions",
      "an increase in the number of popularly elected leaders",
      "a growing dependence on Cuba for economic support",
      "a return to their former colonial status"
    ],
    "answer": "an increase in the number of popularly elected leaders"
  },
  {
    "id": 1238,
    "question": "Which group has been a major force in calling for the protection of human rights in Central America during the 1980 s and 1990 s?",
    "option": [
      "Caudillos",
      "military generals",
      "Landowners",
      "liberation theology clergy"
    ],
    "answer": "liberation theology clergy"
  },
  {
    "id": 1239,
    "question": "Brazil s establishment of an equal partnership with foreign investors and Venezuela s control of its highly profitable oil industry are examples of",
    "option": [
      "Neocolonialism",
      "new imperialism",
      "economic nationalism",
      "Fascism"
    ],
    "answer": "economic nationalism"
  },
  {
    "id": 1240,
    "question": "At the present time, which is a major economic problem for many Latin American governments?",
    "option": [
      "increased settlement in rural areas",
      "low rates of inflation",
      "inability to pay foreign debts",
      "lack of a chief executive"
    ],
    "answer": "inability to pay foreign debts"
  },
  {
    "id": 1241,
    "question": "Which major economic problem has been faced by many Latin American nations throughout their histories?",
    "option": [
      "lack of capital for industrial development",
      "declining birthrate",
      "widespread acceptance of Marxist economic policies",
      "lack of labor for factories"
    ],
    "answer": "lack of capital for industrial development"
  },
  {
    "id": 1242,
    "question": "During the 20th century, a major course of political problems in Latin American has been",
    "option": [
      "a decrease in population",
      "the declining importance of international trade",
      "widespread poverty",
      "increasing social mobility"
    ],
    "answer": "widespread poverty"
  },
  {
    "id": 1243,
    "question": "Which has been an important factor that has discouraged investment in the economic developments of many Latin American nations?",
    "option": [
      "lack of natural resources",
      "history of colonial dependence",
      "declining birthrate",
      "political instability"
    ],
    "answer": "political instability"
  },
  {
    "id": 1244,
    "question": "Which statement best describes the Roman Catholic Church in most Latin American countries in the 1980 s?",
    "option": [
      "the activities of the church are controlled by the national governments",
      "the church has confined its activities to religious issues",
      "the church has become active in social and human rights issues",
      "most people see the church as having little influence in daily life"
    ],
    "answer": "the church has become active in social and human rights issues"
  },
  {
    "id": 1245,
    "question": "Which type of government has resulted from the changing political trends in much of Latin America during the 1990 s?",
    "option": ["monarchy", "military juntas", "democracy", "fascism"],
    "answer": "democracy"
  },
  {
    "id": 1246,
    "question": "A major problem facing many Central American nations is that their nation s wealth is",
    "option": [
      "generally invested in consumer industries",
      "controlled by a small group of landed elite",
      "distributed throughout the large middle class",
      "held mainly by government agencies"
    ],
    "answer": "controlled by a small group of landed elite"
  },
  {
    "id": 1247,
    "question": "In the 20th century, an economic weakness of many Central American nations has been",
    "option": [
      "a reliance on monsoons for water to irrigate crops",
      "an overdependence on one or two cash crops for export",
      "chronic labor shortages caused by slow population growth",
      "excessive investment in foreign manufacturing industries"
    ],
    "answer": "an overdependence on one or two cash crops for export"
  },
  {
    "id": 1248,
    "question": "Since World War II, what action have many Latin American nations taken to improve their economies?",
    "option": [
      "reinforcing traditional farming methods",
      "encouraging citizens to emigrate to other nations",
      "adopting protectionist policies",
      "encouraging industrial development"
    ],
    "answer": "encouraging industrial development"
  },
  {
    "id": 1249,
    "question": "In Latin America during the 1960 s and 1970 s, which group became increasingly active in promoting human rights?",
    "option": [
      "wealthy landholders",
      "Roman Catholic clergy",
      "successful industrialists",
      "military leaders"
    ],
    "answer": "Roman Catholic clergy"
  },
  {
    "id": 1250,
    "question": "Which political trend exists in present-day Latin America?",
    "option": [
      "Most countries are becoming military juntas.",
      "Communism is spreading throughout the region.",
      "Democracy is replacing dictatorship.",
      "Religious leaders are making government policy."
    ],
    "answer": "Democracy is replacing dictatorship."
  },
  {
    "id": 1251,
    "question": "Which conclusion about the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) can be drawn from this 1994 cartoon?",
    "option": [
      "NATO did not react quickly enough to the crisis in Bosnia.",
      "Bosnia and NATO continue to disagree about the causes of the civil war.",
      "NATO's actions have allowed communism to take advantage of the destruction of Bosnia.",
      "The United States will probably withdraw from NATO as a result of the Bosnian crisis."
    ],
    "answer": "NATO did not react quickly enough to the crisis in Bosnia."
  },
  {
    "id": 1252,
    "question": "Russia Takes Soviet Union Seat",
    "option": [
      "is usually dominated by industrialized countries",
      "generally relies on the use of force to enforce its decisions",
      "responds to changing political conditions",
      "permits developing nations to block the proposals of Westerns nations"
    ],
    "answer": "responds to changing political conditions"
  },
  {
    "id": 1253,
    "question": "Recent events in the former nations of Czechoslovakia and Yugoslavia reflect a nationalist trend of",
    "option": [
      "dividing nations along ethnic lines",
      "encouraging multiethnic cooperation",
      "uniting nations with similar interests",
      "supporting the development of a command economy"
    ],
    "answer": "dividing nations along ethnic lines"
  },
  {
    "id": 1254,
    "question": "Disputes over India s control of Kashmir, Jammu, and Punjab are examples of the continuing problem of",
    "option": [
      "territorial claims based on religion",
      "Chinese claims to this region",
      "terrorist actions by Serbian refugees",
      "the policy of nonalignment"
    ],
    "answer": "territorial claims based on religion"
  },
  {
    "id": 1255,
    "question": "One reason North Korea has been the focus of worldwide attention in the mid-1990 s is because of its",
    "option": [
      "nuclear weapons development programs",
      "commitment to increasing political freedoms",
      "development of a strong and expanding economy",
      "efforts to revive communism in Eastern Europe"
    ],
    "answer": "nuclear weapons development programs"
  },
  {
    "id": 1256,
    "question": "The major goal of many minority groups, such as the Kurds, Tamils, and Sikhs, is to",
    "option": [
      "obtain self-rule and economic control of a homeland",
      "establish a multicultural state",
      "install Christianity as the state religion",
      "acquire economic aid from the World Bank"
    ],
    "answer": "obtain self-rule and economic control of a homeland"
  },
  {
    "id": 1257,
    "question": "Under the leadership of Fidel Castro, Cuba has become an example of",
    "option": [
      "the success of democracy in improving conditions in a developing nation",
      "a nation in which the efforts of the United Nations has improved human rights",
      "a communist government struggling to maintain power despite economic problems",
      "the successful reform of agriculture from single-crop to multicrop production"
    ],
    "answer": "a communist government struggling to maintain power despite economic problems"
  },
  {
    "id": 1258,
    "question": "Since the end of the Cold War, Cuba has experienced",
    "option": [
      "the loss of a major source of its foreign financial support",
      "increased economic growth from expanded trade",
      "expanded political influence in Latin American affairs",
      "greater independence from Communist China"
    ],
    "answer": "the loss of a major source of its foreign financial support"
  },
  {
    "id": 1259,
    "question": "In France, a person drinks coffee imported from Brazil, works at a computer made in Japan, and uses gasoline from Saudi Arabia in a German automobile.  This situation illustrates the concept of",
    "option": ["empathy", "scarcity", "interdependence", "world citizenship"],
    "answer": "interdependence"
  },
  {
    "id": 1260,
    "question": "Japan sells cars to the United States, the United States exports high technology to Saudi Arabia, and Saudi Arabia exports oil to Japan.  Which is a valid conclusion that can be drawn from this statement?",
    "option": [
      "Saudi Arabia controls most of the world's natural resources",
      "The United States is the world's leading exporter",
      "most nations of the world specialize in one export",
      "the nations of the world are economically interdependent"
    ],
    "answer": "the nations of the world are economically interdependent"
  },
  {
    "id": 1261,
    "question": "Global problems of uneven economic development, environmental pollution, and hunger reflect the need for",
    "option": [
      "a return to policies of economic nationalism",
      "increased military spending by all nations",
      "a reduction in foreign aid provided by industrialized nations",
      "increased international cooperation"
    ],
    "answer": "increased international cooperation"
  },
  {
    "id": 1262,
    "question": "The Middle East is a global importance today because it",
    "option": [
      "has become a model of economic and political equality",
      "allows major European powers to retain their spheres of influence",
      "provides much of the petroleum used by industrial nations",
      "remains a primary source of uranium"
    ],
    "answer": "provides much of the petroleum used by industrial nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 1263,
    "question": "A major purpose of the Organization of African Unity (OAU), the Organization of American States (OAS), and the European Union (EU) is to",
    "option": [
      "encourage political and economic cooperation between member nations",
      "end colonialism in member nations",
      "control overpopulation in member nations",
      "provide military assistance to member nations"
    ],
    "answer": "encourage political and economic cooperation between member nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 1264,
    "question": "In the past decade, Japanese automobile manufacturers have sought to improve Japanese-American trade relations by",
    "option": [
      "drastically lowering the price of Japanese automobiles for American consumers",
      "allowing an unlimited number of American automobiles to be sold in Japan",
      "importing most spare parts from Mexico",
      "building an increasing number of Japanese automobiles in the United States"
    ],
    "answer": "building an increasing number of Japanese automobiles in the United States"
  },
  {
    "id": 1265,
    "question": "In recent years, a major success of the European Union (EU) has been the",
    "option": [
      "creation of a single military force",
      "rejection of national sovereignty",
      "adoption of a single language",
      "elimination of trade barriers"
    ],
    "answer": "elimination of trade barriers"
  },
  {
    "id": 1266,
    "question": "The major reason the Mexican Government strongly supported the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) was that this agreement would",
    "option": [
      "raise tariffs on United States products entering Mexico",
      "reduce Mexico s economic dependence on Europe",
      "promote investment and economic growth in Mexico",
      "stimulate trade between Asia and Latin America"
    ],
    "answer": "promote investment and economic growth in Mexico"
  },
  {
    "id": 1267,
    "question": "Within the past decade, the decision of the United States Government to grant China  most favored nation  status was important to China because this decision",
    "option": [
      "allowed China to join the Southeast Treaty Organization (SEATO)",
      "increased China s ability to trade with the United States",
      "helped protect China from a possible Japanese invasion",
      "eliminated Russian influence in East Asia"
    ],
    "answer": "increased China s ability to trade with the United States"
  },
  {
    "id": 1268,
    "question": "Modern Japan must trade to maintain its industry and living standard because Japan has",
    "option": [
      "a limited amount of investment capital",
      "little access to the sea",
      "a lack of communication systems",
      "few mineral resources"
    ],
    "answer": "few mineral resources"
  },
  {
    "id": 1269,
    "question": "The main idea of this cartoon is that Japan",
    "option": [
      "practices free trade",
      "restricts foreign imports",
      "has a policy of balanced trade",
      "imports most of its ships"
    ],
    "answer": "restricts foreign imports"
  },
  {
    "id": 1270,
    "question": "Which action will help slow the trend indicated by the graph?",
    "option": [
      "expanding Green Revolution technology",
      "increasing industrialization in developing nations",
      "using alternative energy sources",
      "lowering worldwide oil prices"
    ],
    "answer": "using alternative energy sources"
  },
  {
    "id": 1271,
    "question": "Which conclusion can be drawn from the information in the chart?",
    "option": [
      "Developing countries are instituting programs to limit the growth of their populations.",
      "Infant mortality is a greater problem in Africa than in Asia.",
      "The nations with relatively low birthrates have relatively high per capita incomes.",
      "The national birthrate is determined by many different factors."
    ],
    "answer": "The nations with relatively low birthrates have relatively high per capita incomes."
  },
  {
    "id": 1272,
    "question": "In many Latin American nations, reliance on the production of a single cash crop has led to",
    "option": [
      "economic dependence on other nations",
      "rapid repayment of foreign loans",
      "a high per capita Gross National Product",
      "development of a strong industrial economy"
    ],
    "answer": "economic dependence on other nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 1273,
    "question": "Which fact about China has been the cause of the other three?",
    "option": [
      "the economy of China has trouble providing for all the needs of the people",
      "the Chinese government has set limits on the number of children families may have",
      "Chinese cities have a severe shortage of housing",
      "China s population exceeds one billion"
    ],
    "answer": "China s population exceeds one billion"
  },
  {
    "id": 1274,
    "question": "Since the collapse of the Soviet Union in the early 1990 s, Russia has attempted to build an economic system based on",
    "option": [
      "a return to feudalism",
      "the ideas of Marx and Lenin",
      "the writings of Mao Zedong",
      "free-market a system"
    ],
    "answer": "free-market a system"
  },
  {
    "id": 1275,
    "question": "Which conclusion is valid concerning the food shortages some nations of Africa and Asia during the 1970 s and 1980 s?",
    "option": [
      "misuse of the land has destroyed many rich food-producing regions",
      "too few people in Africa and Asia are involved in food production",
      "acid rain has been the major cause of crop failures",
      "European nations stopped shipping food to these regions"
    ],
    "answer": "too few people in Africa and Asia are involved in food production"
  },
  {
    "id": 1276,
    "question": "Which statement is best supported by the data in the graph?",
    "option": [
      "The urban areas of Honduras and Panama require the largest supply of water in Central America.",
      "Belize and Costa Rica are meeting the water needs of their urban population.",
      "Urban water supplies are declining in many Central American countries.",
      "Most Central American countries experienced a decrease in urban population between 1980 and 1988."
    ],
    "answer": "Belize and Costa Rica are meeting the water needs of their urban population."
  },
  {
    "id": 1277,
    "question": "In Mexico and India, the Green Revolution has been successful because it has",
    "option": [
      "promoted democratic reform",
      "increased agricultural productivity",
      "introduced western culture and values",
      "established economic equality among the people"
    ],
    "answer": "increased agricultural productivity"
  },
  {
    "id": 1278,
    "question": "The major goal of the Green Revolution has been to",
    "option": [
      "decrease the use of modern farm machinery",
      "decrease population growth",
      "increase agricultural output",
      "increase the number of traditional farms"
    ],
    "answer": "increase agricultural output"
  },
  {
    "id": 1279,
    "question": "The term ?Green Revolution? is used to describe the",
    "option": [
      "tensions between developing and developed nations",
      "heavy reliance on manual labor in agriculture",
      "protests against environmental destruction caused by industry",
      "development of new types of grains and new methods of growing them"
    ],
    "answer": "development of new types of grains and new methods of growing them"
  },
  {
    "id": 1280,
    "question": "The main goal of the Green Revolution was to",
    "option": [
      "prevent further destruction of the world?s rain forests",
      "solve chronic food shortages through the use of technology",
      "expand the economies of developing nations with foreign investment",
      "insure that foreign aid was received by people with the greatest need"
    ],
    "answer": "solve chronic food shortages through the use of technology"
  },
  {
    "id": 1281,
    "question": "A study of the accident at the Chernobyl nuclear power plant in the Soviet Union and of severe air pollution in Mexico would lead to the conclusion that",
    "option": [
      "technology can cause problems throughout the world",
      "international trade is more profitable than domestic commerce",
      "modern science cannot solve most political problems",
      "agricultural nations have caused major world environmental problems"
    ],
    "answer": "technology can cause problems throughout the world"
  },
  {
    "id": 1282,
    "question": "A major environmental problem affecting Latin America, Sub-Saharan Africa, and Southeast Asia has been",
    "option": [
      "air pollution",
      "Deforestation",
      "disposal of nuclear waste",
      "acid rain"
    ],
    "answer": "Deforestation"
  },
  {
    "id": 1283,
    "question": "Many scientist believe that the ?greenhouse effect? is the result of",
    "option": [
      "overgrazing on land in developing nations",
      "using large amounts of gasoline, oil, and coal in developed nations",
      "testing nuclear weapons in violation of the Nuclear Test Ban Treaty",
      "using natural fertilizers to increase crop production"
    ],
    "answer": "using large amounts of gasoline, oil, and coal in developed nations"
  },
  {
    "id": 1284,
    "question": "A major factor contributing to the destruction of the Amazon rain forests is the",
    "option": [
      "movement of people from rural to urban areas",
      "attempt of native peoples to end illegal drug traffic",
      "need for more farmland",
      "spread of Christianity"
    ],
    "answer": "need for more farmland"
  },
  {
    "id": 1285,
    "question": "The amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere has increased in recent years.  Environmentalists suggest this change is a direct result of the",
    "option": [
      "improper storage of solid and nuclear waste",
      "overcutting of forests and the increased use of fossil fuels",
      "dumping of inorganic material into lakes and rivers",
      "use of herbicides and toxic substances such as asbestos and DDT"
    ],
    "answer": "overcutting of forests and the increased use of fossil fuels"
  },
  {
    "id": 1286,
    "question": "In developing countries, the use of wood, charcoal, and dung as major sources of energy has created an increase in",
    "option": [
      "economic dependence on industrialized nations",
      "sales an profits for international oil corporations",
      "deforestation and other environmental problems",
      "nuclear waste products"
    ],
    "answer": "deforestation and other environmental problems"
  },
  {
    "id": 1287,
    "question": "A negative impact of the use of modern technology is that",
    "option": [
      "levels of air and water pollution often increase",
      "economic opportunities are frequently limited",
      "contacts with other cultures decrease",
      "international trade is limited"
    ],
    "answer": "levels of air and water pollution often increase"
  },
  {
    "id": 1288,
    "question": "In Latin America, the deforestation of the Amazon rain forest has led to",
    "option": [
      "the maintenance of a traditional way of life",
      "the discovery of new medicines",
      "overpopulation in rural regions",
      "environmental dangers"
    ],
    "answer": "environmental dangers"
  },
  {
    "id": 1289,
    "question": "In the 1980?s, the governments of both Brazil and Malaysia supported the cutting of timber in their rain forests as a means of",
    "option": [
      "achieving economic prosperity",
      "increasing the national debt",
      "controlling rebellions of indigenous peoples",
      "preventing exploitation by imperialist nations"
    ],
    "answer": "achieving economic prosperity"
  },
  {
    "id": 1290,
    "question": "?What harms the victim most is not the cruelty of the oppressor, but the silence of the bystander.?",
    "option": [
      "totalitarian governments generally support civil liberties",
      "nations of the world must always condemn human rights violations whenever they occur",
      "ethnic cleansing is not an issue to be addressed by the United Nations",
      "demonstrations against human rights violations are of limited value"
    ],
    "answer": "nations of the world must always condemn human rights violations whenever they occur"
  },
  {
    "id": 1291,
    "question": "?United States Adopts Economic Sanctions Against South Africa?  ?Chinese Dissidents Imprisoned After Student Protest?",
    "option": [
      "imperialist expansion",
      "peasant revolts",
      "human rights violation",
      "isolationist policies"
    ],
    "answer": "human rights violation"
  },
  {
    "id": 1292,
    "question": "The Tiananmen Square massacre in China was a reaction to",
    "option": [
      "Deng Xiaoping?s plan to revive the Cultural Revolution",
      "student demands for greater individual rights and freedom of expression",
      "China?s decision to seek Western investors",
      "Great Britain?s decision to return Hong Kong to China"
    ],
    "answer": "student demands for greater individual rights and freedom of expression"
  },
  {
    "id": 1293,
    "question": "Which statement best describes a result of the student demonstrations in Beijing?s Tiananmen Square in 1989?",
    "option": [
      "prodemocracy protestors were successful in achieving their goals",
      "a state-controlled education program was begun",
      "the government further restricted freedom of expression in China",
      "collectivization programs were started in China"
    ],
    "answer": "the government further restricted freedom of expression in China"
  },
  {
    "id": 1294,
    "question": "A common problem facing most Latin American and Eastern European nations today is that these nations",
    "option": [
      "have little arable land and few mineral resources with which to improve their economies",
      "have chosen not to belong to international organizations",
      "are struggling with a transition to democracy after experiencing years of dictatorial rule",
      "are experiencing major problems with the flood of illegal immigrants entering their nations"
    ],
    "answer": "are struggling with a transition to democracy after experiencing years of dictatorial rule"
  },
  {
    "id": 1295,
    "question": "Today, human rights violations most often occur in nations in which",
    "option": [
      "freedom of the press exists",
      "government is limited by law",
      "leaders have absolute control",
      "government has a multiparty system"
    ],
    "answer": "leaders have absolute control"
  },
  {
    "id": 1296,
    "question": "An analysis of the Chinese student demonstrations in Tiananmen Square in 1989 would show that",
    "option": [
      "communist governments continue to have little control over the actions of their citizens",
      "totalitarian governments frequently survive by the use of force",
      "peaceful demonstrations often succeed in achieving democratic reforms",
      "negative global reaction sometimes leads to economic decline"
    ],
    "answer": "totalitarian governments frequently survive by the use of force"
  },
  {
    "id": 1297,
    "question": "Which observation about the impact of colonialism on African development is most valid?:",
    "option": [
      "European nations respected the heritage of the ancient African kingdoms.",
      "historians have proved that the positive effects of colonialism have outweighted the negative effects.",
      "colonialism introduced Africans to a variety of non-African cultures.",
      "without the colonization of Africa, the continent would have continued in a period of stagnation."
    ],
    "answer": "colonialism introduced Africans to a variety of non-African cultures."
  },
  {
    "id": 1298,
    "question": "Which was a characteristic of Western European nations that most enabled them to establish colonies in Africa and Asia?:",
    "option": [
      "rigid social class structures.",
      "frequent political revolutions.",
      "self-sufficienty in natural resources.",
      "advanced technology."
    ],
    "answer": "advanced technology."
  },
  {
    "id": 1299,
    "question": "Which of the folowing was a major result of European imperialism in sub-Saharan Africa during the late 19c and early 20c?:",
    "option": [
      "adoption of Islam as the dominant African religion.",
      "decline of traditional African cultures.",
      "strengthening of tribal organization.",
      "beginning of slavery."
    ],
    "answer": "decline of traditional African cultures."
  },
  {
    "id": 1300,
    "question": "Which was a major effect of European rule in Africa?:",
    "option": [
      "decreased dependence of African nations on imports.",
      "development of subsistence agriculture.",
      "improved transportation and communication systems.",
      "increased use of barter as a basis of their economies."
    ],
    "answer": "improved transportation and communication systems."
  },
  {
    "id": 1301,
    "question": "European imperialism promoted the development of nationalism in Asian and African countries by?:",
    "option": [
      "unintentionally uniting people to oppose foreign domination.",
      "promoting free trade associations among the colonies.",
      "establishing Christianity as the common religion throughout the continent.",
      "discouraging patriotic feelings toward the mother country."
    ],
    "answer": "unintentionally uniting people to oppose foreign domination."
  },
  {
    "id": 1302,
    "question": "Which of the following is an accurate statement about the partitioning of Africa by European imperialist nations during the 1800s?:",
    "option": [
      "new nations were based on old tribal boundaries.",
      "the cultural and ethnic diversity of the African people was disregarded.",
      "the continent was divided equally among the colonial powers.",
      "African unity was encouraged."
    ],
    "answer": "the cultural and ethnic diversity of the African people was disregarded."
  },
  {
    "id": 1303,
    "question": "European imperialism in Africa in the late 19c and early 20c resulted from all of the following motives EXCEPT the?:",
    "option": [
      "demand for raw materials.",
      "desire to spread Christianity.",
      "desire for large empires.",
      "need for slaves."
    ],
    "answer": "need for slaves."
  },
  {
    "id": 1304,
    "question": "Which statement BEST describes the impact of European rule on traditional African cultures?:",
    "option": [
      "it encouraged unity among the peoples of Africa.",
      "it caused exports from africa to decline.",
      "it reduced the influence of local African rulers.",
      "it strengthened family ties in the villages."
    ],
    "answer": "it reduced the influence of local African rulers."
  },
  {
    "id": 1305,
    "question": "The Berlin Conference of 1884-1885 showed that European nations?:",
    "option": [
      "wanted to end the African slave trade.",
      "were ready to carve up Africa among themselves.",
      "wanted to convert Africans to Christianity.",
      "were ready to begin exploring the interior of Africa."
    ],
    "answer": "were ready to carve up Africa among themselves."
  },
  {
    "id": 1306,
    "question": "In the early 1800s, which two groups were competing for control of South Africa?:",
    "option": [
      "Boers and Zulus.",
      "Muslims and Hausa.",
      "British and Germans.",
      "Belgians and French."
    ],
    "answer": "Boers and Zulus."
  },
  {
    "id": 1307,
    "question": "Indirect rule as practiced by the British had all of the following characteristics EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "British authorities made the law for the colony.",
      "local rulers kept some of their traditional authority.",
      "British authorities and considerable authority.",
      "local rulers were replaced by British officials."
    ],
    "answer": "local rulers were replaced by British officials."
  },
  {
    "id": 1308,
    "question": "About half of the Congo Free State died between 1885 and 1908 as a result of?:",
    "option": [
      "the Boer War.",
      "a yellow fever epidemic.",
      "Jihadists.",
      "brutal treatment by European companies."
    ],
    "answer": "brutal treatment by European companies."
  },
  {
    "id": 1309,
    "question": "Why did westerners in the early 1800s call Africa the \"Dark Continent?:\"",
    "option": [
      "they got a lot of coal from Africa.",
      "they knew very little about the land.",
      "the sun rarely shone on Africa.",
      "the overgrowth in the rain forests made it dark."
    ],
    "answer": "they knew very little about the land."
  },
  {
    "id": 1310,
    "question": "Discovery of a treatment for which disease allowed Europeans to venture into the African interior?:",
    "option": ["smallpox.", "tuberculosis.", "malaria.", "scarlet fever."],
    "answer": "malaria."
  },
  {
    "id": 1311,
    "question": "The \"Scramble for Africa\" led to the European colonication of the whole African continent EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "Egypt and South Africa.",
      "Liberia and Ethiopia.",
      "Nigeria and Morocco.",
      "Kenya and the Congo."
    ],
    "answer": "Liberia and Ethiopia."
  },
  {
    "id": 1312,
    "question": "Cecil Rhodes made his African fortune by?:",
    "option": [
      "mining gold and diamonds.",
      "planting bananas, melons, and other exotic fruits.",
      "building steamships that sailed up and down the Nile River.",
      "planting and processing rubber."
    ],
    "answer": "mining gold and diamonds."
  },
  {
    "id": 1313,
    "question": "Colonial officials often discouraged native peoples from?:",
    "option": [
      "learning European languages.",
      "converting to Christianity.",
      "adopting Western lifestyles.",
      "practicing traditional customs and rituals."
    ],
    "answer": "practicing traditional customs and rituals."
  },
  {
    "id": 1314,
    "question": "After many Kenyans died fighting the Germans in World War I, the British?:",
    "option": [
      "granted Kenya full independence.",
      "allowed European settlers to seize the land of the native Kenyans.",
      "asked Jomo Kenyatta to help further Kenyan nationalism.",
      "let Harry Thuku govern Kenya for them."
    ],
    "answer": "allowed European settlers to seize the land of the native Kenyans."
  },
  {
    "id": 1315,
    "question": "Britain wanted to establish a colony in southern Africa to?:",
    "option": [
      "train missionaries for work in Africa.",
      "provide a homeland for former slaves.",
      "control the Dutch missionaries there.",
      "protest the route to India."
    ],
    "answer": "protest the route to India."
  },
  {
    "id": 1316,
    "question": "Which nation adopted and then largely abandoned the policy of assimilation in Africa?:",
    "option": ["France.", "Britain.", "the United States.", "Belgium."],
    "answer": "France."
  },
  {
    "id": 1317,
    "question": "Until the late 1800s, Europeans were discouraged from conquering Africa by all of the following EXCPEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "malaria.",
      "impassable rivers.",
      "Social Darwinism.",
      "powerful African armies."
    ],
    "answer": "Social Darwinism."
  },
  {
    "id": 1318,
    "question": "Which of the following was NOT a goal of independent African explorers?:",
    "option": [
      "finding the source of Africa\\'s mighty rivers.",
      "stirring up political unrest so that their imperial sponsors could move in and take advantage of the resulting chaos.",
      "assessing the continent\\'s possible mineral wealth.",
      "scouting out locations for possible Christian missions."
    ],
    "answer": "stirring up political unrest so that their imperial sponsors could move in and take advantage of the resulting chaos."
  },
  {
    "id": 1319,
    "question": "This African kingdom conquered Egypt in the 8c BCE?:",
    "option": ["Kush.", "Axum.", "Ghana.", "Zimbabwe."],
    "answer": "Kush."
  },
  {
    "id": 1320,
    "question": "The mixing of Bantu and Arabic cultures resulted in the?:",
    "option": [
      "Bantu migrations.",
      "development of Swahili.",
      "spread of iron smelting.",
      "rise of Great Zimbabwe."
    ],
    "answer": "development of Swahili."
  },
  {
    "id": 1321,
    "question": "East African city-states grew wealthy primarily through?:",
    "option": [
      "plantation agriculture.",
      "manufacturing.",
      "military conquests.",
      "trade."
    ],
    "answer": "trade."
  },
  {
    "id": 1322,
    "question": "The kingdom of Ethiopia is distinctive in Africa for its?:",
    "option": [
      "early abolition of the slave trade.",
      "conversion to Coptic Christianity.",
      "weak central government.",
      "very early conversion to Islam."
    ],
    "answer": "conversion to Coptic Christianity."
  },
  {
    "id": 1323,
    "question": "What is the main reason the city-states of East Africa became multicultural?:",
    "option": [
      "Arab and Persian traders settled in the city-states.",
      "the gold trade made them rich.",
      "African traders sailed to the Arabian Peninsula.",
      "iron from the city-states became widely used in the Arabian Peninsula and South Asia."
    ],
    "answer": "Arab and Persian traders settled in the city-states."
  },
  {
    "id": 1324,
    "question": "Great Zimbabwe was the?:",
    "option": [
      "military leader who unified the Khoisan peoples.",
      "great temple in Timbuktu.",
      "capital of a vast empire in south Africa.",
      "military and and economic alliance of the city-states of East Africa."
    ],
    "answer": "capital of a vast empire in south Africa."
  },
  {
    "id": 1325,
    "question": "Axum prospered partly because it had a port on the?:",
    "option": [
      "Red Sea.",
      "Atlantic Ocean.",
      "Mediterranean Sea.",
      "Zambezi River."
    ],
    "answer": "Red Sea."
  },
  {
    "id": 1326,
    "question": "People of the East African coastal towns who practiced various animistic religions were eventually converted to?:",
    "option": ["Hinduism.", "Christianity.", "Judaism.", "Islam."],
    "answer": "Islam."
  },
  {
    "id": 1327,
    "question": "A major factor in the development of 20c nationalist movements throughout Africa was a common?:",
    "option": [
      "language throughout most of Africa.",
      "goal to end European rule in Africa.",
      "ethnic bond among the people of Sub-Saharan Africa.",
      "religion throughout most of Africa."
    ],
    "answer": "goal to end European rule in Africa."
  },
  {
    "id": 1328,
    "question": "The boundaries of modern African nations do not usually follow tribal boundaries mainly because?:",
    "option": [
      "African nations are trying to decrease tribal influence.",
      "most tribes are unwilling to cooperate with the new national governments.",
      "modern national boundaries tend to follow former colonial boundaries.",
      "tribes have lost their importance in the lives of modern Africans."
    ],
    "answer": "modern national boundaries tend to follow former colonial boundaries."
  },
  {
    "id": 1329,
    "question": "During the 1950s and 1960s, the history of most African countries was characterized by?:",
    "option": [
      "colonization by imperialist nations.",
      "the achievement of political independence.",
      "a sharp decrease in the birth rate.",
      "the development of economic self-sufficiency."
    ],
    "answer": "the achievement of political independence."
  },
  {
    "id": 1330,
    "question": "The term \"Pan-Arabism\" can best be defined as a movement whose purpose is to?:",
    "option": [
      "promote African unity.",
      "encourage European investment in Africa.",
      "support cultural diversity.",
      "advocate a return to colonial conditions."
    ],
    "answer": "promote African unity."
  },
  {
    "id": 1331,
    "question": "The economic systems of most newly independent African nations have been characterized by?:",
    "option": [
      "private ownership with a minimum of government involvement.",
      "a Communist model of government ownership of agriculture.",
      "self-sufficiency with few exports or imports.",
      "a mixture of government and private ownership."
    ],
    "answer": "a mixture of government and private ownership."
  },
  {
    "id": 1332,
    "question": "One way in which Kwame Nkrumah, Jomo Kenyatta, and Patrice Lumumba are similar is that that all?:",
    "option": [
      "supported the United States military action in the Persian Gulf War.",
      "played a major role in independence movements in Africa.",
      "rejected financial aid from the World Bank.",
      "opposed the Pan-African movement."
    ],
    "answer": "played a major role in independence movements in Africa."
  },
  {
    "id": 1333,
    "question": "\"We are Nigerians and we wish to remain so.  We have our own customs and our own traditions.  Our immediate goal should be to develop the wealth of our country and improve our standard of living.\" This quotation is an expression of?:",
    "option": [
      "mercantilism.",
      "totalitarianism.",
      "imperialism.",
      "nationalism."
    ],
    "answer": "nationalism."
  },
  {
    "id": 1334,
    "question": "Many modern African nations depend on foreign aid because these nations?:",
    "option": [
      "have many different ethnic groups.",
      "want to have power in the United Nations.",
      "need help in developing their economies.",
      "want to establish democratic governments."
    ],
    "answer": "need help in developing their economies."
  },
  {
    "id": 1335,
    "question": "What was one factor that contributed to the downfall of apartheid in the Republic of South Africa?:",
    "option": [
      "the African National Congress was outlawed.",
      "Afrikaaners demanded that only they should have ruling power.",
      "many foreign countries boycotted South African products.",
      "President de Klerk and Desmond Tutu were imprisoned."
    ],
    "answer": "many foreign countries boycotted South African products."
  },
  {
    "id": 1336,
    "question": "Tribalism in modern African nations has frequently resulted in political?:",
    "option": ["disunity.", "equality.", "interdependence.", "harmony."],
    "answer": "disunity."
  },
  {
    "id": 1337,
    "question": "Which statement BEST describes the significance of awarding the 1984 Nobel Peace Prize to Bishop Desmund Tutu of South Africa?:",
    "option": [
      "the world community was endorsing the apartheid practices of the old white government of South Africa.",
      "the European policy of remaining neutral in regard to human rights issues was reaffirmed.",
      "the separation of church and state was promoted as a universal concept.",
      "non-violence was recognized as a way to bring about change in South Africa."
    ],
    "answer": "non-violence was recognized as a way to bring about change in South Africa."
  },
  {
    "id": 1338,
    "question": "In most of the nations of Africa, an important economic problem has been?:",
    "option": [
      "a shortage of unskilled labor.",
      "an increase in agricultural surpluses.",
      "a lack of capital for investment.",
      "excessive industrialization."
    ],
    "answer": "a lack of capital for investment."
  },
  {
    "id": 1339,
    "question": "Which statement is most accurate about many African societies today?:",
    "option": [
      "modern medicines have been ineffective in decreasing infant mortality throughout Africa.",
      "new attitudes and values often clash with traditional tribal practices.",
      "agriculture is no longer the most important economic activity in Africa.",
      "European influence no longer exists in the former colonial territories."
    ],
    "answer": "new attitudes and values often clash with traditional tribal practices."
  },
  {
    "id": 1340,
    "question": "Ethnicity and regionalism in Nigeria led to?:",
    "option": [
      "a tragic civil war.",
      "an increase in export crops.",
      "widespread government corruption.",
      "the restoration of civilian rule."
    ],
    "answer": "a tragic civil war."
  },
  {
    "id": 1341,
    "question": "African nations organized regional groups to?:",
    "option": [
      "reduce the poewr of OPEC.",
      "support the Free World in the Cold War.",
      "give landlocked nations access to the sea.",
      "encourage economic development."
    ],
    "answer": "encourage economic development."
  },
  {
    "id": 1342,
    "question": "One result of the \"Sharpeville massacre\" was?:",
    "option": [
      "the enactment of pass laws.",
      "the formation of the African National Congress.",
      "worldwide protests against the South African government.",
      "the repeal of laws that classified people by race."
    ],
    "answer": "worldwide protests against the South African government."
  },
  {
    "id": 1343,
    "question": "The Belgian Congo was renamed Zaire in order to?:",
    "option": [
      "reject its colonial past.",
      "make Belgians leave.",
      "force the UN to recognize its independence.",
      "end the civil war there."
    ],
    "answer": "reject its colonial past."
  },
  {
    "id": 1344,
    "question": "Before the late 1990s, blacks in South Africa?:",
    "option": [
      "could vote but could no form labor unions.",
      "were forced to live in Bantustans.",
      "had to vote for the African National Congress.",
      "could not work in industry."
    ],
    "answer": "were forced to live in Bantustans."
  },
  {
    "id": 1345,
    "question": "Cash crops are important to most African countries because these crops?:",
    "option": [
      "can be sold abroad to bring money into the country.",
      "are used for food by the farmers and their families.",
      "sell for higher prices than machinery and oil.",
      "are always in great demand by other countries."
    ],
    "answer": "can be sold abroad to bring money into the country."
  },
  {
    "id": 1346,
    "question": "In Rwanda, more than 500,000 Tusis died as a result of?:",
    "option": [
      "battles in an effort to stop the invasion of their country by Somalia.",
      "starvation.",
      "massacres by Hutu extremists.",
      "being imprisoned for treason by their own government."
    ],
    "answer": "massacres by Hutu extremists."
  },
  {
    "id": 1347,
    "question": "The colonial capital of African colonies usually became the capital of an independent African nation because?:",
    "option": [
      "it was usually the largest city.",
      "it already had good communication and transportation facilities.",
      "it was the country\\'s most prosperous market.",
      "all of these choices are correct."
    ],
    "answer": "all of these choices are correct."
  },
  {
    "id": 1348,
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true regarding African nations in the United Nations?:",
    "option": [
      "they are not allowed full membership.",
      "they are an important voice for other developing countries.",
      "they are a dividing force in the UN Security COouncil.",
      "they are under-represented in comparison with other regions in the world."
    ],
    "answer": "they are an important voice for other developing countries."
  },
  {
    "id": 1349,
    "question": "Which of the following countries became a battleground for the Cold War in Africa?:",
    "option": [
      "Tanzania and Zaire.",
      "Kenya and Ghana.",
      "Angola and Mozambique.",
      "South Africa and Zimbabwe."
    ],
    "answer": "Angola and Mozambique."
  },
  {
    "id": 1350,
    "question": "Why did United Nations forces intervene in Somalia in December 1992?:",
    "option": [
      "to help victims of famine there.",
      "to establish new colonies in that region.",
      "to defeat communist forces there.",
      "to stop the expansion of Somalia into Tanzania."
    ],
    "answer": "to help victims of famine there."
  },
  {
    "id": 1351,
    "question": "Since the African National Congress came to power in South Africa in 1994, its primary aim has been to?:",
    "option": [
      "establish one-party rule in South Africa.",
      "unite the people of South Africa in a democratic republic.",
      "restore Dutch influence on South African culture.",
      "create a homeland for white separatists."
    ],
    "answer": "unite the people of South Africa in a democratic republic."
  },
  {
    "id": 1352,
    "question": "The Hausa and Ibo of Nigeria and the Hutus and the Tutsis of Rwanda are similar in that?:",
    "option": [
      "their differences led to disastrous civil wars.",
      "they failed to unite to oust their colonial masters.",
      "their economic wealth led to declarations of independence.",
      "they quickly developed a common culture."
    ],
    "answer": "their differences led to disastrous civil wars."
  },
  {
    "id": 1353,
    "question": "Soweto referred to?:",
    "option": [
      "a trade union organization in South Africa.",
      "an opposition white political party that frequently sided with blacks in Zaire.",
      "a black South African township that had been the scene of many violent protests against apartheid.",
      "the underground arm of the African National Congress."
    ],
    "answer": "a black South African township that had been the scene of many violent protests against apartheid."
  },
  {
    "id": 1354,
    "question": "Which of the following statements is TRUE about sub-Saharan Africa today?:",
    "option": [
      "national political boundaries are the same as traditional tribal boundaries.",
      "tribal customs are most often practiced in urban areas.",
      "trade with non-African countries has stopped.",
      "many Africans still practice subsistence farming."
    ],
    "answer": "many Africans still practice subsistence farming."
  },
  {
    "id": 1355,
    "question": "When the white man came to Africa,  he had the Bible and the black man had the land.  Later the white man had the land  and the black man had the Bible.   The author of this statement above suggests that an important result of European involvement in Africa was that the?:'",
    "option": [
      "Africans exchanged their land for Bibles.",
      "Europeans exploited the Africans.",
      "Africans became good Christians.",
      "Europeans lost their religious beliefs."
    ],
    "answer": "Europeans exploited the Africans."
  },
  {
    "id": 1356,
    "question": "Which was a direct result of European slave trade in Africa?:",
    "option": [
      "it promoted a feeling of racial superiority among Europeans.",
      "West African kingdoms prospered.",
      "Africans moved in large numbers to rural areas.",
      "African military forces ended the slave trade."
    ],
    "answer": "it promoted a feeling of racial superiority among Europeans."
  },
  {
    "id": 1357,
    "question": "Which statement is most accurate about the African slave trade from the 15c through the 19c?:",
    "option": [
      "the slave trade was limited to East Africa.",
      "the slave traders brought ivory and timber to Africa.",
      "the slave trade involved African, Arab, and European slave traders.",
      "most slaves were transported from Africa to Europe."
    ],
    "answer": "the slave trade involved African, Arab, and European slave traders."
  },
  {
    "id": 1358,
    "question": "The development of which of the following led to importation of large numbers of African slaves to the Americas?:",
    "option": [
      "mercantilism.",
      "plantation agriculture.",
      "the spice trade.",
      "the joint stock company."
    ],
    "answer": "plantation agriculture."
  },
  {
    "id": 1359,
    "question": "The slave-gun cycle in West Africa during the 15c and 16c led to the?:",
    "option": [
      "abolition of slavery.",
      "revival of Islam.",
      "rise of several new, powerful African states.",
      "growing of cash crops such as cotton."
    ],
    "answer": "rise of several new, powerful African states."
  },
  {
    "id": 1360,
    "question": "The vast majority of the African slaves were to be employed in the?:",
    "option": [
      "coffee and sugar plantations in the Caribbean and South America.",
      "cotton plantations of British North America.",
      "gold and silver mines of the New World.",
      "colonial armies of the European conquerors."
    ],
    "answer": "coffee and sugar plantations in the Caribbean and South America."
  },
  {
    "id": 1361,
    "question": "The African state that played a very active and profitable role in the transatlantic slave trade was the?:",
    "option": [
      "Songhai Empire.",
      "Kingdom of Senegambia.",
      "Empire of Ethiopia.",
      "Kingdom of Dahomey."
    ],
    "answer": "Kingdom of Dahomey."
  },
  {
    "id": 1362,
    "question": "According to Olaudah Equiano, one of the worst sufferings the slaves endured was?:",
    "option": [
      "beatings.",
      "separation from their loved ones.",
      "sickness.",
      "overcrowding in the slave ships."
    ],
    "answer": "separation from their loved ones."
  },
  {
    "id": 1363,
    "question": "Which European nation first engaged in the African slave trade?:",
    "option": ["Spain.", "England.", "Portugal.", "the Netherlands."],
    "answer": "Portugal."
  },
  {
    "id": 1364,
    "question": "Otal tradition is important in African cultures because it?:",
    "option": [
      "led to most Africans speaking the same language.",
      "proves that humans originated in East Africa.",
      "prevented the development of written language in Africa.",
      "allows knowledge to be passed from one generation to the next."
    ],
    "answer": "allows knowledge to be passed from one generation to the next."
  },
  {
    "id": 1365,
    "question": "Which of the following is a major characteristic of traditional African art?:",
    "option": [
      "African art contains a great deal of symbolism.",
      "the human form is represented very realistically in African art.",
      "painting is the primary medium for traditional African art.",
      "African art reflects a highly urban culture."
    ],
    "answer": "African art contains a great deal of symbolism."
  },
  {
    "id": 1366,
    "question": "The age-group system served as a method of?:",
    "option": [
      "choosing brides for young men.",
      "limiting warfare among rival villages.",
      "teaching children the values of their society.",
      "encouraging cultural diffusion."
    ],
    "answer": "teaching children the values of their society."
  },
  {
    "id": 1367,
    "question": "Traditional African art has had the greatest influence on?:",
    "option": [
      "classical Roman mosaics and pottery.",
      "European Renaissance painting.",
      "medieval Islamic architecture.",
      "20c European painting and sculpture."
    ],
    "answer": "20c European painting and sculpture."
  },
  {
    "id": 1368,
    "question": "Diviners served an important role in some African societies because they?:",
    "option": [
      "were worshipped as gods.",
      "collected the taxes and supervised farming.",
      "helped people understand the cause of disasters and acted as intermediaries to the spirits.",
      "determined which age grade a boy or girl belonged to."
    ],
    "answer": "helped people understand the cause of disasters and acted as intermediaries to the spirits."
  },
  {
    "id": 1369,
    "question": "In many African cultures, political and social organization was based on the?:",
    "option": [
      "village.",
      "emperor\\'s court.",
      "civil service system.",
      "council of ancestors."
    ],
    "answer": "village."
  },
  {
    "id": 1370,
    "question": "Traditional African religions emphasized?:",
    "option": [
      "belief in only one god.",
      "the importance of the  Qur\\'an  and daily prayer.",
      "loyalty to the village priests.",
      "the connection of family, village, nature, and ancestors."
    ],
    "answer": "the connection of family, village, nature, and ancestors."
  },
  {
    "id": 1371,
    "question": "In African societies, lineage?:",
    "option": [
      "tied families to a common ancestor.",
      "allowed farmers and herders to trade more efficiently.",
      "gave women higher status than men.",
      "limited the power of the West African kingdoms."
    ],
    "answer": "tied families to a common ancestor."
  },
  {
    "id": 1372,
    "question": "Which of the following has been a chief reason for the changing social structure of the African tribal unit?:",
    "option": [
      "inter-tribal wars.",
      "movements to the cities.",
      "independence and self-government.",
      "a decrease in tribal population."
    ],
    "answer": "movements to the cities."
  },
  {
    "id": 1373,
    "question": "A griot\\'s role in West African society is similar to that of a?:",
    "option": ["scientist.", "musician.", "military leader.", "historian."],
    "answer": "historian."
  },
  {
    "id": 1374,
    "question": "Before West African civilizations had contact with Europeans, these civilizations developed?:",
    "option": [
      "sophisticated art works that included bronze, gold, and clay sculptures.",
      "economies that did not rely on trade for their wealth.",
      "one interconnected system of government for all of their empires.",
      "social systems that emphasized the nuclear family."
    ],
    "answer": "sophisticated art works that included bronze, gold, and clay sculptures."
  },
  {
    "id": 1375,
    "question": "One similarity between the ancient African kingdoms of Ghana, Mali, and Songhai is that all of these kingdoms were located?:",
    "option": [
      "in mountainous regions.",
      "in coastal areas.",
      "on major trading routes.",
      "in rain forest regions."
    ],
    "answer": "on major trading routes."
  },
  {
    "id": 1376,
    "question": "Mansa Musa\\'s journey to Mecca in the 1300s is evidence that?:",
    "option": [
      "the European Crusades had a great influence on western Africa.",
      "most African leaders were educated in the Middle East.",
      "European culture was superior to the cultures of western Africa.",
      "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire."
    ],
    "answer": "Islam had a major influence on the Mali Empire."
  },
  {
    "id": 1377,
    "question": "A major trading and university town in West Africa was?:",
    "option": ["Meroe.", "Timbuktu.", "Kinshasa.", "Mombasa."],
    "answer": "Timbuktu."
  },
  {
    "id": 1378,
    "question": "How did the ruler of Ghana profit from the trade routes that met in his empire?:",
    "option": [
      "by ambushing merchants and stealing their goods.",
      "by bribing merchants for a percentage of their profits.",
      "by collecting a toll on all goods entering or leaving Ghana.",
      "by allowing trade on only certain days of the week."
    ],
    "answer": "by collecting a toll on all goods entering or leaving Ghana."
  },
  {
    "id": 1379,
    "question": "The laws introduced by Askia Muhammad were based on?:",
    "option": [
      "the teachings of the  Qur\\'an.",
      "a respect for ancestor worship.",
      "the social code of the Berbers.",
      "the teachings of Sundiata."
    ],
    "answer": "the teachings of the  Qur\\'an."
  },
  {
    "id": 1380,
    "question": "With the collapse of the trade routes across the Sahara in the 15c and 16c, political and economic power in Africa shifted to the coast of the?:",
    "option": [
      "Red Sea.",
      "Indian Ocean.",
      "Mediterranean Sea.",
      "Atlantic Ocean."
    ],
    "answer": "Atlantic Ocean."
  },
  {
    "id": 1381,
    "question": "Which statement BEST describes the geography of Africa?:",
    "option": [
      "most of the continent is made up of tropical rain forests.",
      "deserts and savannas cover almost half of the continent.",
      "most major rivers are navigable for their entire lengths.",
      "the irregular coastline provides many natural harbors."
    ],
    "answer": "deserts and savannas cover almost half of the continent."
  },
  {
    "id": 1382,
    "question": "The major occupation of the people who live on the grasslands of Africa is?:",
    "option": ["lumbering.", "manufacturing.", "herding.", "mining."],
    "answer": "herding."
  },
  {
    "id": 1383,
    "question": "The geographic features of the African continent are partly responsible for the?:",
    "option": [
      "use of French or English as the official languages of many African nations.",
      "decline of the slave trade in the 19c.",
      "recent advances in technology in African nations.",
      "diversity of cultures found in Africa."
    ],
    "answer": "diversity of cultures found in Africa."
  },
  {
    "id": 1384,
    "question": "Which statement BEST describes the effects of the geography of Africa?:",
    "option": [
      "it has hindered economic development on the continent.",
      "it has stimulated political and cultural unity throughout the continent.",
      "it encouraged physical mobility throughout Africa.",
      "it resulted in most African countries having similar economic and social systems."
    ],
    "answer": "it has hindered economic development on the continent."
  },
  {
    "id": 1385,
    "question": "In East Africa, east-west travel is hindered by the?:",
    "option": [
      "Great Rift Valley.",
      "Zambezi River.",
      "savanna.",
      "Sahara Desert."
    ],
    "answer": "Great Rift Valley."
  },
  {
    "id": 1386,
    "question": "Africa\\'s largest eastern lakes were named after?:",
    "option": [
      "German explorers.",
      "French missionaries.",
      "British rulers.",
      "a famous Portuguese inventor."
    ],
    "answer": "British rulers."
  },
  {
    "id": 1387,
    "question": "What percentage of Africa is really jungle/rain forest?:",
    "option": ["5%.", "15%.", "35%.", "70%."],
    "answer": "15%."
  },
  {
    "id": 1388,
    "question": "Africa is called a \"tropical continent\" because of its?:",
    "option": ["longitude.", "size.", "altitude.", "latitude."],
    "answer": "latitude."
  },
  {
    "id": 1389,
    "question": "Most of the rivers in Africa are of little help in transporting large quantities of goods and people because these rivers?:",
    "option": [
      "flow toward the mountains.",
      "run only north and south.",
      "are not long enough.",
      "have many waterfalls and rapids."
    ],
    "answer": "have many waterfalls and rapids."
  },
  {
    "id": 1390,
    "question": "India\\'s greatest value to the British was as a source of?:",
    "option": [
      "minerals.",
      "cheap labor.",
      "agricultural products.",
      "ports and trade routes."
    ],
    "answer": "agricultural products."
  },
  {
    "id": 1391,
    "question": "All of the following are true of the Sepoy Mutiny EXCEPT that it?:",
    "option": [
      "was successful.",
      "occurred during the Raj.",
      "was led by Indian soldiers.",
      "marked a turning point in Indian history."
    ],
    "answer": "was successful."
  },
  {
    "id": 1392,
    "question": "Which of the following was a result of the Sepoy Mutiny?:",
    "option": [
      "the British East India Company went bankrupt.",
      "the British stopped trying to convert Indians to Christianity.",
      "British officials became more sensitive to the needs of Indians.",
      "the British government tightened its control over India."
    ],
    "answer": "the British government tightened its control over India."
  },
  {
    "id": 1393,
    "question": "The term  Raj  is used to refer to the period of Indian history during which India was?:",
    "option": [
      "independent.",
      "dominated by Britain.",
      "torn apart by civil war.",
      "loosely ruled by the British East India Company."
    ],
    "answer": "dominated by Britain."
  },
  {
    "id": 1394,
    "question": "Britain fought for control of India with?:",
    "option": ["France.", "Portugal.", "Spain.", "Hollard."],
    "answer": "France."
  },
  {
    "id": 1395,
    "question": "British efforts to modernize Indian transportation and communication systems served to?:",
    "option": [
      "promote handicraft production.",
      "satisfy Indian nationalist demands.",
      "encourage population growth.",
      "unite the people of India."
    ],
    "answer": "unite the people of India."
  },
  {
    "id": 1396,
    "question": "The Indian Civil Service was designed to?:",
    "option": [
      "open high-level posts in Britain to educated Indians.",
      "provide trained Indian administrators.",
      "modernize Indian transportation.",
      "encourage British emigration to India."
    ],
    "answer": "provide trained Indian administrators."
  },
  {
    "id": 1397,
    "question": "What caused the collapse of India\\'s textile industry?:",
    "option": [
      "an Indian boycott of British goods.",
      "high taxes paid by the Indians to Great Britain.",
      "an increase in the price of cotton.",
      "the importation of British cloth to India."
    ],
    "answer": "the importation of British cloth to India."
  },
  {
    "id": 1398,
    "question": "Which of the following was a primary goal of the British government after making India a part of the empire?:",
    "option": [
      "to reestablish the East India Company.",
      "to eliminate the caste system.",
      "to improve transportation and communication in India.",
      "to unite the people of India."
    ],
    "answer": "to improve transportation and communication in India."
  },
  {
    "id": 1399,
    "question": "Which of the following was a result of the Sepoy Rebellion?:",
    "option": [
      "the British East India Company took over many Indian kingdoms.",
      "Indian nationalist realized that the British provided needed leadership in India.",
      "the Mughal emperor\\'s power increased.",
      "the British East India Company was abolished."
    ],
    "answer": "the British East India Company was abolished."
  },
  {
    "id": 1400,
    "question": "The Buddha taught that people suffered in life because of a?:",
    "option": [
      "desire for happiness and riches.",
      "belief in  nirvana .",
      "refusal to obey the gods.",
      "belief in  kama ."
    ],
    "answer": "desire for happiness and riches."
  },
  {
    "id": 1401,
    "question": "Buddha\\'s Four Noble Truths stress the point that?:",
    "option": [
      "an individual commitment to involve oneself in the political aspects of life.",
      "only members of the highest class could achieve salvation because only they could do the things required in the Eightfold Path.",
      "that sorrow and misery did not exist.",
      "worldly sorrow and misery could be ended only by a life of selflessness."
    ],
    "answer": "worldly sorrow and misery could be ended only by a life of selflessness."
  },
  {
    "id": 1402,
    "question": "Buddhists reject the idea that?:",
    "option": [
      "there are no gods.",
      "all people can achieve salvation.",
      "only Brahmins can show people the way to  nirvana .",
      "the ultimate goal of life is escape from desire."
    ],
    "answer": "only Brahmins can show people the way to  nirvana ."
  },
  {
    "id": 1403,
    "question": "The teachings of the Buddha include all of the following EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "people\\'s purpose should be to attain  nirvana .",
      "life\\'s cycle of pain ends at death.",
      "people\\'s desire for pleasure actually causes pain.",
      "the way to escape life\\'s cycle of pain is be seeking wisdom."
    ],
    "answer": "life\\'s cycle of pain ends at death."
  },
  {
    "id": 1404,
    "question": "What happened to Buddhism in India?:",
    "option": [
      "it was absorbed back into Hinduism.",
      "it became the majority religion of the subcontinent.",
      "it gained few converts.",
      "eventually about half of the people of India became Buddhists."
    ],
    "answer": "it was absorbed back into Hinduism."
  },
  {
    "id": 1405,
    "question": "The teachings of Buddha challenged the power of the?:",
    "option": [
      "Hindu warrior caste.",
      "Persians.",
      "Dravidians.",
      "Brahmin priests."
    ],
    "answer": "Brahmin priests."
  },
  {
    "id": 1406,
    "question": "Buddha left his family and wealth in order to?:",
    "option": [
      "discover the secret of eternal life.",
      "explore the roots of human suffering.",
      "rediscover his Aryan roots.",
      "sit under  bodhi  trees."
    ],
    "answer": "explore the roots of human suffering."
  },
  {
    "id": 1407,
    "question": "One important difference between Hinduism and Buddhism is that?:",
    "option": [
      "Hindus worship only one God.",
      "Buddhists believe that human suffering is unnecessary.",
      "Hindus do not accept the concept of a \"world spirit\" or Brahman.",
      "Buddhists believe a person can gain enlightenment in a single lifetime."
    ],
    "answer": "Buddhists believe a person can gain enlightenment in a single lifetime."
  },
  {
    "id": 1408,
    "question": "The main belief of Mahayan Buddhism was that?:",
    "option": [
      " bodhisatvas  have postponed nirvana to help others achieve enlightenment.",
      "life was suffering.",
      "all should worship in their own language and according to their customs.",
      "monks should travel around converting many people to Buddhism."
    ],
    "answer": " bodhisatvas  have postponed nirvana to help others achieve enlightenment."
  },
  {
    "id": 1409,
    "question": "Buddha taught that by rejecting desire people could attain  nirvana , or?:",
    "option": [
      "a state of self-denial.",
      "oneness with Brahma.",
      "a state of perfect peace.",
      "a mystical union with nature."
    ],
    "answer": "a state of perfect peace."
  },
  {
    "id": 1410,
    "question": "In its earliest days, Buddhism was very popular among which of the following groups in India?:",
    "option": [
      "the Brahmins.",
      "the  Sudras .",
      "the Untouchables.",
      "warriors."
    ],
    "answer": "warriors."
  },
  {
    "id": 1411,
    "question": "The philosophies of Confucius and Mao Zedong both emphasized?:",
    "option": [
      "individual rather than cooperative gain.",
      "industry rather than agriculture.",
      "group rather than individual welfare.",
      "religious values rather than economic profits."
    ],
    "answer": "group rather than individual welfare."
  },
  {
    "id": 1412,
    "question": "The Chinese Communists were successful in their revolution during the 1930s and 1940s mainly because the Communists?:",
    "option": [
      "emphasized the needs of the rural peasant population.",
      "gave factory workers leadership positions in the Communist Party.",
      "accepted advanced military technology from Western nations.",
      "provided for universal suffrage and free elections."
    ],
    "answer": "emphasized the needs of the rural peasant population."
  },
  {
    "id": 1413,
    "question": "In 1958, China\\'s Great Leap Forward called for programs designed to?:",
    "option": [
      "break up the communal farm system.",
      "slow down industrial expansion and devote more resources to agricultural growth.",
      "restore a capitalist economic system.",
      "increase both industrial and agricultural production."
    ],
    "answer": "increase both industrial and agricultural production."
  },
  {
    "id": 1414,
    "question": "To improve economic conditions during the late 1980s and early 1990s, China adopted policies that?:",
    "option": [
      "restricted agricultural and industrial exports.",
      "moved China toward a modified form of private enterprise.",
      "led to a Chinese military invasion of Korea.",
      "prohibited involvement by foreign corporations in Chinese industries."
    ],
    "answer": "moved China toward a modified form of private enterprise."
  },
  {
    "id": 1415,
    "question": "In present-day China, the major goal of the government is to?:",
    "option": [
      "increase the freedom of the Chinese press.",
      "reduce its control over the economy.",
      "decrease Chinese trade with the United States.",
      "increase Chinese control over Southeast Asia."
    ],
    "answer": "reduce its control over the economy."
  },
  {
    "id": 1416,
    "question": "A major cause of the Tiananmen Square demonstrations in June 1989 was the?:",
    "option": [
      "influence of Western ideas on university students.",
      "memories of the Japanese invasion of China.",
      "teachings of Confucius.",
      "Chinese tradition of youthful rebellion."
    ],
    "answer": "influence of Western ideas on university students."
  },
  {
    "id": 1417,
    "question": "In China and the former Soviet Union, the Communist governments discouraged organized religion because religions?:",
    "option": [
      "support the principles of laissez faire.",
      "avor anarchy over organized government.",
      "compete for the loyalties of the people.",
      "stress economic rather than political values."
    ],
    "answer": "compete for the loyalties of the people."
  },
  {
    "id": 1418,
    "question": "In China during the 1980s, government efforts to adapt Western economic ideas resulted in?:",
    "option": [
      "increased dependence on the Soviet Union.",
      "a slowdown of economic growth.",
      "increased trade with many industrialized nations.",
      "military confrontations with other Asian nations."
    ],
    "answer": "increased trade with many industrialized nations."
  },
  {
    "id": 1419,
    "question": "An immediate result of the Cultural Revolution in China was that it?:",
    "option": [
      "helped to establish democracy in urban centers in China.",
      "disrupted China\\'s economic and educational systems.",
      "led to economic cooperation with Japan and South Korea.",
      "strengthened political ties with the United States."
    ],
    "answer": "disrupted China\\'s economic and educational systems."
  },
  {
    "id": 1420,
    "question": "Since the death of Mao Zedong, relations between China and the United States have improved because?:",
    "option": [
      "both nations see an economic advantage to increased trade.",
      "the new Chinese leadership has adopted a democratic government.",
      "illegal Chinese immigration to the United States has decreased.",
      "the United States has increased oil imports from China."
    ],
    "answer": "both nations see an economic advantage to increased trade."
  },
  {
    "id": 1421,
    "question": "Mao launched the Cultural Revolution in order to?:",
    "option": [
      "spread the responsibility system throughout China.",
      "weaken the influence of the communes.",
      "promote a revolutionary spirit among young Chinese.",
      "preserve traditional Chinese culture and customs."
    ],
    "answer": "promote a revolutionary spirit among young Chinese."
  },
  {
    "id": 1422,
    "question": "After 1949, the lives of Chinese women changed because they?:",
    "option": [
      "had to work in the fields for the first time.",
      "were guaranteed equality under the law.",
      "were allowed to have only two children.",
      "were forbidden to marry until they were 25 years old."
    ],
    "answer": "were guaranteed equality under the law."
  },
  {
    "id": 1423,
    "question": "In Chinese history, the dynastic cycle represents a continual process of?:",
    "option": [
      "strength and prosperity.",
      "marriage and divorce.",
      "death and rebirth.",
      "corruption and decline."
    ],
    "answer": "death and rebirth."
  },
  {
    "id": 1424,
    "question": "Under the Han dynasty, China?:",
    "option": [
      "set up a bureaucratic system of government.",
      "sent out armies to conquer the Roman Empire.",
      "forbade all trade with other lands.",
      "outlawed the teachings of Confucius."
    ],
    "answer": "set up a bureaucratic system of government."
  },
  {
    "id": 1425,
    "question": "Goods traveled from China to Greece and Rome in the West on the Silk Road by?:",
    "option": [
      "sea around the coast of India.",
      "land across central Asia.",
      "land across northeastern China.",
      "water along the Yangtze River."
    ],
    "answer": "land across central Asia."
  },
  {
    "id": 1426,
    "question": "The Chinese believed a ruler kept the Mandate of Heaven by?:",
    "option": [
      "abolishing ancestor worship.",
      "ending slavery.",
      "conquering new lands.",
      "governing wisely."
    ],
    "answer": "governing wisely."
  },
  {
    "id": 1427,
    "question": "During the Han dynasty, the Chinese invented?:",
    "option": ["paper.", "drama.", "bronze.", "the arch."],
    "answer": "paper."
  },
  {
    "id": 1428,
    "question": "Candidates for the Chinese civil service needed a thorough knowledge of?:",
    "option": [
      "the Confucian classics.",
      "the teachings of Buddha.",
      "science and mathematics.",
      "world geography."
    ],
    "answer": "the Confucian classics."
  },
  {
    "id": 1429,
    "question": "Han rulers encouraged education in order to?:",
    "option": [
      "increase the number of chinese inventions.",
      "improve the life of the common people.",
      "train government officials.",
      "spread Buddhist ideas."
    ],
    "answer": "train government officials."
  },
  {
    "id": 1430,
    "question": "The greatest problem faced by the later Han emperors was?:",
    "option": [
      "peasant upheavals.",
      "foreign invasion.",
      "succession crises.",
      "urban poverty."
    ],
    "answer": "peasant upheavals."
  },
  {
    "id": 1431,
    "question": "the Great Silk Road reached from China to?:",
    "option": ["India.", "Syria and Asia Minor.", "Mongolia.", "Persia."],
    "answer": "Persia."
  },
  {
    "id": 1432,
    "question": "The Han era is considered a golden age in China for all of the following reasons EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "the revival of learning.",
      "the defeat of the barbarians.",
      "the development of trade.",
      "the influence of Confucius\\' ideas."
    ],
    "answer": "the defeat of the barbarians."
  },
  {
    "id": 1433,
    "question": "During the 19c, Western nations were able to gain control over parts of China mainly because?:",
    "option": [
      "the CHinese had a strong tradition of non-violence.",
      "China lacked the military technology needed to stop these ventures.",
      "China was promised aid for its industries.",
      "the Chinese lacked a strong cultural identity."
    ],
    "answer": "China lacked the military technology needed to stop these ventures."
  },
  {
    "id": 1434,
    "question": "The Boxer Rebellion of the early 20c was an attempt to?:",
    "option": [
      "eliminate poverty among the Chinese peasants.",
      "bring Western-style democracy to China.",
      "restore trade between China and European nations.",
      "remove foreign influences from China."
    ],
    "answer": "remove foreign influences from China."
  },
  {
    "id": 1435,
    "question": "During the late 1800s, imperialistic nations divided China into?:",
    "option": [
      "plantations.",
      "independent city-states.",
      "communes.",
      "spheres of influence."
    ],
    "answer": "spheres of influence."
  },
  {
    "id": 1436,
    "question": "After the Revolution of 1911, Sun Yixian [Sun Yat-sen] was unable to achieve his goals for China because?:",
    "option": [
      "civil war broke out.",
      "Japan conquered China.",
      "the Communists took over.",
      "the empress Cixi opposed any changes."
    ],
    "answer": "civil war broke out."
  },
  {
    "id": 1437,
    "question": "The Long March occurred as a result of?:",
    "option": [
      "the ouitbreak of World War II.",
      "Jiang Jieshi\\'s efforts to wipe out the Communists.",
      "the Boxers\\' determination to win control of China.",
      "Chinese efforts to settle the interior."
    ],
    "answer": "Jiang Jieshi\\'s efforts to wipe out the Communists."
  },
  {
    "id": 1438,
    "question": "The right of extraterritoriality in the 19c and early 20c allowed the Westerner in China to?:",
    "option": [
      "establish an import-export business.",
      "be tried for crime under laws of his own country.",
      "take out temporary Chinese citizenship.",
      "serve as an advisor to the Chinese government."
    ],
    "answer": "be tried for crime under laws of his own country."
  },
  {
    "id": 1439,
    "question": "The Open Door Policy?:",
    "option": [
      "warned Western powers to leave China alone.",
      "divided China into four shperes of influence.",
      "urged that all Western powers have equal trading rights in China.",
      "established a trade agreement between China and Japan."
    ],
    "answer": "urged that all Western powers have equal trading rights in China."
  },
  {
    "id": 1440,
    "question": "One of the results of the Treaty of Nanjing of 1842 was that?:",
    "option": [
      "the East India Company was established.",
      "China gave Hong Kong to the British.",
      "China increased the tariff on British goods.",
      "the British paid damages for opium they destroyed."
    ],
    "answer": "China gave Hong Kong to the British."
  },
  {
    "id": 1441,
    "question": "During the 1800s, the British were interested in China mainaly as a?:",
    "option": [
      "market for opium.",
      "market for sugar and coffee.",
      "source of rubber and ginseng.",
      "source of raw cotton."
    ],
    "answer": "market for opium."
  },
  {
    "id": 1442,
    "question": "The Taiping Rebellion was caused in part by the?:",
    "option": [
      "war between China and Japan.",
      "death of the Empress Cixi.",
      "reforms of Kuang Hsu.",
      "demand for peasants for land."
    ],
    "answer": "demand for peasants for land."
  },
  {
    "id": 1443,
    "question": "A basic of Sun Yixian [Sun Yat-sen] was to?:",
    "option": [
      "declare war on Japan.",
      "implement The Three Principles of the People.",
      "execute Chinese missionaries.",
      "overthrow the Empress Cixi."
    ],
    "answer": "implement The Three Principles of the People."
  },
  {
    "id": 1444,
    "question": "In 1911, nationalism in China was the main reason for the struggle to?:",
    "option": [
      "overthrow the Manchus.",
      "capture Beijing.",
      "conquer the Japanese.",
      "complete the Long March."
    ],
    "answer": "overthrow the Manchus."
  },
  {
    "id": 1445,
    "question": "In Yanan, long after the Long March, the Chinese communists continued to fight Jiang Jieshu [Chiang Kai-shek] with the support of the?:",
    "option": ["Soviets.", "Manchus.", "Japanese.", "Chinese peasants."],
    "answer": "Chinese peasants."
  },
  {
    "id": 1446,
    "question": "In the Three Principles of the People, Sun Yixian [Sun Yat-sen] declared that?:",
    "option": [
      "the Chinese should organize a new government based on the teachings of Confucius.",
      "the Kuomintang had the Mandate of Heaven.",
      "China should be thoroughly reorganized in order to become a strong modern nation based on Western democratic principles.",
      "the CHinese should reject all western ideas."
    ],
    "answer": "China should be thoroughly reorganized in order to become a strong modern nation based on Western democratic principles."
  },
  {
    "id": 1447,
    "question": "Which best accounts for the lack of political unity in China between 1912 and 1937?:",
    "option": [
      "religious warfare.",
      "little popular loyalty to the central government in Nanjing.",
      "nonrecognition of the Chinese government by foreign powers.",
      "the declining strength of Chinese communism."
    ],
    "answer": "little popular loyalty to the central government in Nanjing."
  },
  {
    "id": 1448,
    "question": "The Long March was the journey undertaken by?:",
    "option": [
      "Armenians fleeing Turkish persecution.",
      "Indians protesting British rule.",
      "Chinese Communists fleeing the Kuomintang.",
      "Tibetans fighting Chinese rule."
    ],
    "answer": "Chinese Communists fleeing the Kuomintang."
  },
  {
    "id": 1449,
    "question": "Manchuria was a region of conflict between foreign powers because of?:",
    "option": [
      "its strategic location.",
      "its coal and iron mines.",
      "the rich farmlands there.",
      "its important seaport and transportation routes."
    ],
    "answer": "its coal and iron mines."
  },
  {
    "id": 1450,
    "question": "Mao Zedong\\'s goals included all of the following EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "launching a non-corrupt, Western-style democracy.",
      "overthrowing the Chinese Nationalists.",
      "starting a Communist revolution led by the peasants.",
      "driving the Japanese out of Chinese territory."
    ],
    "answer": "launching a non-corrupt, Western-style democracy."
  },
  {
    "id": 1451,
    "question": "Confucianism encouraged its followers to?:",
    "option": [
      "travel to foreign countries.",
      "respect traditional customs.",
      "experiment with science.",
      "conquer East Asia."
    ],
    "answer": "respect traditional customs."
  },
  {
    "id": 1452,
    "question": "In ancient China, one effect on government of the teachings of Confucius was the high status of?:",
    "option": ["soldiers.", "merchants.", "farmers.", "scholars."],
    "answer": "scholars."
  },
  {
    "id": 1453,
    "question": "A goal common to Confucianism, Taoism, and Buddhism is to?:",
    "option": [
      "establish peace and harmony in this life.",
      "provide the basis for democratic government.",
      "return the power of the emperors.",
      "promote individual artistic creativity."
    ],
    "answer": "establish peace and harmony in this life."
  },
  {
    "id": 1454,
    "question": "Yin and yang represented?:",
    "option": [
      "political conflict.",
      "domination of good over evil.",
      "balance in all of nature.",
      "chaos in society."
    ],
    "answer": "balance in all of nature."
  },
  {
    "id": 1455,
    "question": "According to Confucius, the best government was one which?:",
    "option": [
      "set a good example for the people it ruled.",
      "established laws and punishments which made men moral.",
      "took measures to insure economic growth.",
      "maintained a well-equipped army to keep Westerners out of China."
    ],
    "answer": "set a good example for the people it ruled."
  },
  {
    "id": 1456,
    "question": "Mencius gave the Chinese people a \"safety valve\" or way of getting rid of corrupt, evil dynasties.  This was called?:",
    "option": [
      "calligraphy.",
      "feudalism.",
      "filial piety.",
      "Mandate of Heaven."
    ],
    "answer": "Mandate of Heaven."
  },
  {
    "id": 1457,
    "question": "Confucius believed that a good society was one that?:",
    "option": [
      "produced great philosophers.",
      "was run according to Buddhist principles.",
      "protected the rights of individuals.",
      "preserved peace and order."
    ],
    "answer": "preserved peace and order."
  },
  {
    "id": 1458,
    "question": "Legalism was based on a view of human nature as?:",
    "option": [
      "balanced by yin and yang.",
      "selfish and untrustworthy.",
      "independent of outside influences.",
      "well-ordered and rigid."
    ],
    "answer": "selfish and untrustworthy."
  },
  {
    "id": 1459,
    "question": "Confucius believed the best ruler was?:",
    "option": [
      "someone who would pass strict laws.",
      "a man with little education.",
      "a virtuous man who led by example.",
      "a great military hero."
    ],
    "answer": "a virtuous man who led by example."
  },
  {
    "id": 1460,
    "question": "Confucius defined the rights and responsibilities of the citizens of imperial China by?:",
    "option": [
      "developing a code of ethical conduct.",
      "formulating a law code.",
      "writing rules for elections.",
      "drawing up lists of candidates for public office."
    ],
    "answer": "developing a code of ethical conduct."
  },
  {
    "id": 1461,
    "question": "In traditional Chinese culture, which philosophy had the greatest influence on the development of social order and political organization?:",
    "option": ["Taoism.", "Hinduism.", "Shintoism.", "Confucianism."],
    "answer": "Confucianism."
  },
  {
    "id": 1462,
    "question": "Confucianism emphasizes the idea that?:",
    "option": [
      "government should own the means of production.",
      "economic success is more desirable than knowledge and learning.",
      "each person has an important responsibility to family and society.",
      "an individual\\'s personal goals are more important than the goals of the group."
    ],
    "answer": "each person has an important responsibility to family and society."
  },
  {
    "id": 1463,
    "question": "Unlike Confucianism, Taoism emphasized?:",
    "option": [
      "getting a good education.",
      "seeking ways to live in harmony with nature.",
      "enforcing strict rules and laws.",
      "adapting new ideas from non-Chinese cultures."
    ],
    "answer": "seeking ways to live in harmony with nature."
  },
  {
    "id": 1464,
    "question": "Many Chinese were attracted to Buddhism because it?:",
    "option": [
      "offered comfort to the poor and suffering.",
      "glorified the emperor.",
      "taught respect for foreigners.",
      "encouraged peasants to revolt."
    ],
    "answer": "offered comfort to the poor and suffering."
  },
  {
    "id": 1465,
    "question": "Which of the following traditional Chinese philosophies would be most sympathetic to dictatorial, authoritarian goverments?:",
    "option": ["Taoism.", "Buddhism.", "Confucianism.", "Legalism."],
    "answer": "Legalism."
  },
  {
    "id": 1466,
    "question": "The Chinese attitude toward religion?:",
    "option": [
      "enabled many Chinese to practice more than one religion at the same time.",
      "dictated strict adherence to one religion.",
      "prevented the Chinese from adopting Buddhism.",
      "all of these choices are correct."
    ],
    "answer": "enabled many Chinese to practice more than one religion at the same time."
  },
  {
    "id": 1467,
    "question": "Why did the Chinese honor their ancestors\\' spirits?:",
    "option": [
      "they believed that their ancestors became part of Shang Di when they died.",
      "honoring their ancestors would help maintain the balance of yin and yang.",
      "they believed that their ancestors\\' spirits could bring good fortune to their families.",
      "honoring their ancestors would improve their own afterlife."
    ],
    "answer": "they believed that their ancestors\\' spirits could bring good fortune to their families."
  },
  {
    "id": 1468,
    "question": "According to Legalism, the way to achieve order was to?:",
    "option": [
      "provide a ruler who set a good moral example.",
      "pass strict laws and enforce them with harsh punishments.",
      "appeal to man\\'s natural goodness.",
      "live by the natural balance of yin and yang."
    ],
    "answer": "pass strict laws and enforce them with harsh punishments."
  },
  {
    "id": 1469,
    "question": "In Confucian thought, the ruler-subject relationship was modeled after?:",
    "option": [
      "the mother-daughter relationship.",
      "the father-daughter relationship.",
      "the father-son relationship.",
      "the older brother-younger brother relationship."
    ],
    "answer": "the father-son relationship."
  },
  {
    "id": 1470,
    "question": "A sincere follower of Confucius would be in most disagreement with which of the following statements?:",
    "option": [
      " I am the captain of my fate, I am the master of my soul.",
      " Let the ruler be a ruler and a subject be a subject.",
      " The Superior Man should spend his hours searching for the ways of Heaven and the truths taught by the past.",
      " Knowing your place in life will bring much happiness."
    ],
    "answer": " I am the captain of my fate, I am the master of my soul."
  },
  {
    "id": 1471,
    "question": "Shi Huang Di, the First Emperor, united China by?:",
    "option": [
      "importing European weapons.",
      "enforcing strict Legalist principles.",
      "encouraging Confucian teachings.",
      "setting up the civil service examination."
    ],
    "answer": "enforcing strict Legalist principles."
  },
  {
    "id": 1472,
    "question": "The Chinese, like many other peoples, have often been considered ethnocentric.  They have shown ethnocentric attitudes in the past by?:",
    "option": [
      "considering outsiders less civilized than themselves.",
      "following a non-religious way of life.",
      "failing to develop any long lasting cultural contributions until the West came to China.",
      "refusing to follow the tribute system."
    ],
    "answer": "considering outsiders less civilized than themselves."
  },
  {
    "id": 1473,
    "question": "The first unified Chinese empire came under which of the following dynasties?:",
    "option": ["Chou.", "Han.", "Ch\\'in.", "Shang."],
    "answer": "Ch\\'in."
  },
  {
    "id": 1474,
    "question": "Which of the following caused the decline of the Chou (Zhou) dynasty?:",
    "option": [
      "ancestor worship.",
      "feudal warfare.",
      "economic growth.",
      "foreign invasion."
    ],
    "answer": "feudal warfare."
  },
  {
    "id": 1475,
    "question": "Hatred of the Ch\\'in (Qin) was fostered by all of the following EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "the staggering tax burden.",
      "forced labor on such projects as the Great Wall.",
      "the ruthless suppression of Confucianism.",
      "widespread confiscation of peasant lands."
    ],
    "answer": "widespread confiscation of peasant lands."
  },
  {
    "id": 1476,
    "question": "In Chou (Zhou) times, the Chinese state was?:",
    "option": [
      "highly centralized.",
      "feudal in nature.",
      "an absolute monarchy.",
      "a loose confederation."
    ],
    "answer": "feudal in nature."
  },
  {
    "id": 1477,
    "question": "China\\'s most valuable commodity was?:",
    "option": ["silk.", "tea.", "porcelain.", "opium."],
    "answer": "silk."
  },
  {
    "id": 1478,
    "question": "The Great Wall of China was begun in 214 BCE to?:",
    "option": [
      "keep cattle from straying from Chinese territories.",
      "keep Chinese convicts from escaping their prisons in northern China.",
      "guard against nomadic invasions.",
      "all of these choices are correct."
    ],
    "answer": "guard against nomadic invasions."
  },
  {
    "id": 1479,
    "question": "The most important factor in developing agriculture in China was?:",
    "option": [
      "irrigating dry sections of the Gobi Desert.",
      "predicting when the seasonal rains would fall.",
      "controlling the floods of the Huang-He [Yellow] River.",
      "protecting China Proper from foreign invasion."
    ],
    "answer": "controlling the floods of the Huang-He [Yellow] River."
  },
  {
    "id": 1480,
    "question": "The amount of land in China that is arable land is approximately?:",
    "option": ["40%.", "10%.", "25%.", "50%."],
    "answer": "10%."
  },
  {
    "id": 1481,
    "question": "In China, the development of ethnocentrism was most influenced by?:",
    "option": [
      "its historic reliance on foreign nations.",
      "a long history of democratic government.",
      "a strong belief in Christianity.",
      "its geographic isolation."
    ],
    "answer": "its geographic isolation."
  },
  {
    "id": 1482,
    "question": "Which of the following geographic features would have the greatest effect on the lives of the Chinese people?:",
    "option": ["monsoons.", "mountains.", "deserts.", "North Current."],
    "answer": "monsoons."
  },
  {
    "id": 1483,
    "question": "As a person travels WEST in China, he/she is most likely to find?:",
    "option": [
      "densely populated cities.",
      "mountains and deserts.",
      "large agricultural areas.",
      "dry plains."
    ],
    "answer": "mountains and deserts."
  },
  {
    "id": 1484,
    "question": "The best way to discuss the climate of China is to?:",
    "option": [
      "study the entire country because there are few variations.",
      "compare the differences between China and Southeast Asia.",
      "study only the southern area because most of the Chinese live there.",
      "compare the differences between North and South China."
    ],
    "answer": "compare the differences between North and South China."
  },
  {
    "id": 1485,
    "question": "Shan : China  ::          ?        : India",
    "option": ["loess.", "Kuo.", "ghats.", "arigato."],
    "answer": "ghats."
  },
  {
    "id": 1486,
    "question": "The only answer to northern China\\'s agricultural problems is?:",
    "option": [
      "reforestation.",
      "building more canals.",
      "crop rotation.",
      "terrace farming."
    ],
    "answer": "reforestation."
  },
  {
    "id": 1487,
    "question": "The term \"China\\'s Sorrow\" refers to?:",
    "option": [
      "the oppression of the First Emperor.",
      "the violent flooding of the Yellow River.",
      "the constant invasions by nomadic tribes.",
      "the burning of Confucian writings."
    ],
    "answer": "the violent flooding of the Yellow River."
  },
  {
    "id": 1488,
    "question": "One major change in China during the Ming dynasty was?:",
    "option": [
      "giving peasants more power.",
      "ending naval expeditions and foreign trade.",
      "repudiating Confucian ideas.",
      "establishing colonies overseas."
    ],
    "answer": "ending naval expeditions and foreign trade."
  },
  {
    "id": 1489,
    "question": "The Tang strengthened the government by?:",
    "option": [
      "extending the Grand Canal into Korea.",
      "giving up the Mandate of Heaven.",
      "appointing a shogun to rule.",
      "reintroducing the civil service examination."
    ],
    "answer": "reintroducing the civil service examination."
  },
  {
    "id": 1490,
    "question": "The Chinese innovations of paper money and banking were the result of increased trade and?:",
    "option": [
      "political centralizatio.",
      "the invention of printing.",
      "agricultural productivity.",
      "exposure to similar European practices."
    ],
    "answer": "the invention of printing."
  },
  {
    "id": 1491,
    "question": "During the 1400s, the Grand Fleet of Cheng Ho sailed from China all the way to?:",
    "option": [
      "India.",
      "the Persian Gulf.",
      "the east coast of Africa.",
      "the East Indies."
    ],
    "answer": "the east coast of Africa."
  },
  {
    "id": 1492,
    "question": "Footbinding was primarily practiced on?:",
    "option": [
      "working women.",
      "poor women.",
      "just unmarried women.",
      "elite, upper class women."
    ],
    "answer": "elite, upper class women."
  },
  {
    "id": 1493,
    "question": "The Chinese viewed the first Europeans to arrive in the 16c?:",
    "option": [
      "with awe and fear.",
      "with eagerness to learn the latest Western science and technology.",
      "as just another group of unruly barbarian pirates.",
      "with eagerness to open new trade relations."
    ],
    "answer": "as just another group of unruly barbarian pirates."
  },
  {
    "id": 1494,
    "question": "Probably the best known aspect of Tang art was?:",
    "option": [
      "delicate flower arranging.",
      "glazed pottery figurines.",
      "silk-screening of scenes from daily life.",
      "elaborate decorative mosaics."
    ],
    "answer": "glazed pottery figurines."
  },
  {
    "id": 1495,
    "question": "In the 15c through the 18c, China\\'s ethnocentric concept of itself as the \"Middle Kingdom\" led to?:",
    "option": [
      "renewed attempts at Mediterranean conquest.",
      "religious missionary expeditions to the New World.",
      "a lack of interest in trade with European nations.",
      "granting independence to its tributary states in Southeast Asia."
    ],
    "answer": "a lack of interest in trade with European nations."
  },
  {
    "id": 1496,
    "question": "The civil service of the Song period was?:",
    "option": [
      "recruited through competitive examinations.",
      "chosen from the hereditary aristocracy.",
      "had little power and influence.",
      "highly illiterate and corrupt."
    ],
    "answer": "recruited through competitive examinations."
  },
  {
    "id": 1497,
    "question": "Which statement BEST describes an effect of the civil service system in China?:",
    "option": [
      "only the sons of gentry could take the exam.",
      "the exam tested young men on their knowledge of mathematics, science, and history.",
      "the exam protected China from corrupt officials.",
      "the exam ensured that officials shared Confucian values and traditions."
    ],
    "answer": "the exam ensured that officials shared Confucian values and traditions."
  },
  {
    "id": 1498,
    "question": "In Chinese society, the practice of foot-binding was a symbol of the?:",
    "option": [
      "harshness of lower class life.",
      "inferior place of women.",
      "influence of Taoism (Daoism).",
      "importance of the family."
    ],
    "answer": "inferior place of women."
  },
  {
    "id": 1499,
    "question": "In their painting and poetry, the Chinese?:",
    "option": [
      "copied Indian artistic styles.",
      "showed their dislike of foreigners.",
      "expressed respect for nature.",
      "emphasized the importance of the individual."
    ],
    "answer": "expressed respect for nature."
  },
  {
    "id": 1500,
    "question": "The T\\'ang and Sung dynasties are considered Golden Ages of China in part because?:",
    "option": [
      "new gold and silver mines were discovered.",
      "the economy prospered and the arts flourished.",
      "everyone learned to read and write.",
      "China conquered Korea, Japan, and Southeast Asia."
    ],
    "answer": "the economy prospered and the arts flourished."
  },
  {
    "id": 1501,
    "question": "How did the Sung emperors try to keep peace with their fierce northern neighbors, the Tatars?:",
    "option": [
      "by keeping a large army.",
      "by building a huge wall.",
      "by giving them expensive gifts.",
      "by conquering them."
    ],
    "answer": "by giving them expensive gifts."
  },
  {
    "id": 1502,
    "question": "Which of the following would an artist in China in 1000 most likely have chosen to paint?:",
    "option": ["a tree.", "children.", "a king.", "a table."],
    "answer": "a tree."
  },
  {
    "id": 1503,
    "question": "Genghis Khan is remembered as a famous conqueror who?:",
    "option": [
      "united CHina under Mongol rule.",
      "created the basic philosophy of China.",
      "introduced Buddhism into China.",
      "isolated China from the outside world."
    ],
    "answer": "united CHina under Mongol rule."
  },
  {
    "id": 1504,
    "question": "All of these statements about the Mongols\\' way of life are true EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "they were nomads from the central Asian steppes.",
      "they herded horses, cattle, and yaks.",
      "they were peaceful herders.",
      "they were skilled horsemen and fierce warriors."
    ],
    "answer": "they were peaceful herders."
  },
  {
    "id": 1505,
    "question": "To keep Mongols from being absorbed into Chinese civilization, Kublai Khan?:",
    "option": [
      "banned foreigners from China.",
      "welcomed foreigners to his court.",
      "allowed Chinese in the military.",
      "reserved government jobs for Mongols."
    ],
    "answer": "reserved government jobs for Mongols."
  },
  {
    "id": 1506,
    "question": "The Mongol conquest of China resulted in?:",
    "option": [
      "a revival of Chinese arts and literature.",
      "increased contact between China and the Western world.",
      "a lack of political stability.",
      "persecution of Muslims and Christians."
    ],
    "answer": "increased contact between China and the Western world."
  },
  {
    "id": 1507,
    "question": "The Zealots?:",
    "option": [
      "believed that Jesus was the Messiah.",
      "wanted to expel the Romans from Judea.",
      "were followers of a new Roman mystery religion.",
      "felt Christ\\'s message applied only to the Jews."
    ],
    "answer": "wanted to expel the Romans from Judea."
  },
  {
    "id": 1508,
    "question": "Jewish leaders of the 1c?:",
    "option": [
      "at first were pleased to see in Jesus a rebel leader that would push for the end of Roman rule in Judea.",
      "were satisfied at least that Jesus emphasized complete respect for Sabbath traditions.",
      "viewed Jesus as one of many who had already claimed to be the Messiah.",
      "were unsure about Jesus, with some supporting him and the priests of the Temple criticizing him."
    ],
    "answer": "were unsure about Jesus, with some supporting him and the priests of the Temple criticizing him."
  },
  {
    "id": 1509,
    "question": "Many people were attracted to Christianity because?:",
    "option": [
      "it taught that anyone could achieve salvation.",
      "it did not require people to obey any special laws.",
      "its teachings grew out of Judaism.",
      "it allowed people to keep their traditional beliefs along with Christian teachings."
    ],
    "answer": "it taught that anyone could achieve salvation."
  },
  {
    "id": 1510,
    "question": "Which of the following was a factor in the spread of Christianity?:",
    "option": [
      "discontent with Muslim rule.",
      "widespread use of the Hebrew language.",
      "system of Roman roads.",
      "popularity of the Pope."
    ],
    "answer": "system of Roman roads."
  },
  {
    "id": 1511,
    "question": "Bishops in the Christian Church?:",
    "option": [
      "decided on matters of Christian beliefs.",
      "did not believe in the sacred Trinity.",
      "led Christian armies against the Roman emperors.",
      "translated the Bible into Greek."
    ],
    "answer": "decided on matters of Christian beliefs."
  },
  {
    "id": 1512,
    "question": "The new religion of Christianity appealed particularly to?:",
    "option": [
      "people who sought political independence from Rome.",
      "people with low status in the Roman Empire.",
      "people who opposed Rome\\'s treatment of the Jews.",
      "people who sought to acquire great wealth."
    ],
    "answer": "people with low status in the Roman Empire."
  },
  {
    "id": 1513,
    "question": "The teachings of the Christian religion include all of the following EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "belief in a Kingdom of God.",
      "that people should live by the Golden Rule.",
      "that Jesus is the Messiah promised by God.",
      "that only certain people could become Christians and be saved."
    ],
    "answer": "that only certain people could become Christians and be saved."
  },
  {
    "id": 1514,
    "question": "Many Romans accused early Christians of treason because they?:",
    "option": [
      "said that Jesus was the Son of God.",
      "refused to honor the Roman Emperor as a god and rejected military service.",
      "tried to start a church in Rome.",
      "encouraged the poor to rebel against the Roman Emperor."
    ],
    "answer": "refused to honor the Roman Emperor as a god and rejected military service."
  },
  {
    "id": 1515,
    "question": "The most important source for our knowledge of early Hebrew society has been?:",
    "option": [
      "personal letters and diaries.",
      "government records.",
      "cuneiform tablets.",
      "the Bible."
    ],
    "answer": "the Bible."
  },
  {
    "id": 1516,
    "question": "The Hebrews believed that God would protect them if they?:",
    "option": [
      "conquered Palestine.",
      "placed their capital at Jerusalem.",
      "obeyed the Ten Commandments.",
      "revolted against Roman rule."
    ],
    "answer": "obeyed the Ten Commandments."
  },
  {
    "id": 1517,
    "question": "In the Hebrew tradition, a \"covenant\" is?:",
    "option": [
      "an agreement between God and man.",
      "a prophecy about the future.",
      "a law handed down by God to men.",
      "an ornamental chest for storing religious documents."
    ],
    "answer": "an agreement between God and man."
  },
  {
    "id": 1518,
    "question": "Mosaic law differed from earlier ancient law codes because of?:",
    "option": [
      "the harshness of its punishments.",
      "the value it placed on individual human life.",
      "its outlawing of slavery.",
      "its emphasis on polytheism."
    ],
    "answer": "the value it placed on individual human life."
  },
  {
    "id": 1519,
    "question": "Which statement about the ancient kingdom of Israel is accurate?:",
    "option": [
      "its rulers appointed governors to administer each province and enforce the law.",
      "it extended over a vast area from the Nile Valley to the Fertile Crescent.",
      "it lasted only a short time, but its religious believs had a major impact on the world.",
      "King David helped the Hebrews return from the  diaspora ."
    ],
    "answer": "it lasted only a short time, but its religious believs had a major impact on the world."
  },
  {
    "id": 1520,
    "question": "How did the Jewish view of God differ from the beliefs of most people in the ancient world?:",
    "option": [
      "Jews believed in many gods who shared equal power in the heavens.",
      "Jews believed in one main god with several minor gods and goddesses.",
      "Jews believed in only one God.",
      "Jews believed in no gods, but believed in sacred spirits in all of nature."
    ],
    "answer": "Jews believed in only one God."
  },
  {
    "id": 1521,
    "question": "Many Hebrews resented Solomon for all of the following reasons EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "his acceptance of other religions.",
      "his use of forced labor to build his Palace.",
      "higher taxes.",
      "his failure to create a united Jewish Empire."
    ],
    "answer": "his failure to create a united Jewish Empire."
  },
  {
    "id": 1522,
    "question": "King David was best known for which of the following accomplishments?:",
    "option": [
      "establishing Jerusalem as the capital of Israel.",
      "continued to consolidate Israel\\'s power throughout Persia.",
      "destroying the Ark of the Covenant.",
      "splitting Israel into two separate nations."
    ],
    "answer": "establishing Jerusalem as the capital of Israel."
  },
  {
    "id": 1523,
    "question": "To identify the location of a place, you would most likely describe its?:",
    "option": [
      "latitude and longitude.",
      "culture.",
      "vegetation.",
      "exports and imports."
    ],
    "answer": "latitude and longitude."
  },
  {
    "id": 1524,
    "question": "Altitude affects the climate of some regions because?:",
    "option": [
      "low-lying regions have lower temperatures.",
      "more rain falls at lower elevations.",
      "highlands have more rivers than lowlands.",
      "temperatures are cooler at higher elevations."
    ],
    "answer": "temperatures are cooler at higher elevations."
  },
  {
    "id": 1525,
    "question": "Heavy rainfall and high temperatures are constant throughout the year in the Zaire Basin.   Which climate does this describe?:",
    "option": [
      "Mediterranean.",
      "tropical rainy.",
      "savanna.",
      "tropical desert."
    ],
    "answer": "tropical rainy."
  },
  {
    "id": 1526,
    "question": "Two major factors that affect the climate of a place are?:",
    "option": [
      "altitude and latitude.",
      "population and culture.",
      "resources and vegetation.",
      "longitude and landforms."
    ],
    "answer": "altitude and latitude."
  },
  {
    "id": 1527,
    "question": "Desertification is caused by?:",
    "option": [
      "flooding of low lying plains.",
      "strip mining for gold.",
      "heavy rainfall.",
      "overgrazing, deforestation, and over-cultivating."
    ],
    "answer": "overgrazing, deforestation, and over-cultivating."
  },
  {
    "id": 1528,
    "question": "A geographer studies all of the following EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "topography.",
      "primary and secondary school enrollment data.",
      "climate.",
      "distribution of flora and fauna."
    ],
    "answer": "primary and secondary school enrollment data."
  },
  {
    "id": 1529,
    "question": "Why is geography important to history?:",
    "option": [
      "it helps us predict the future.",
      "it tells us when events took place.",
      "it uncovers artifacts left by early people.",
      "it shows us the connections between people, places, and events."
    ],
    "answer": "it shows us the connections between people, places, and events."
  },
  {
    "id": 1530,
    "question": "Why are the Suez Canal, the Strait of Hormuz, the Dardanelles, and the Bosporus strategic waterways?:",
    "option": [
      "the nation that controls these waterways can have economic control over other nations.",
      "they are natural geographic boundaries and have often separated warring nations.",
      "they are located along the Tropic of Cancer, the Equator, or the Tropic of Capricorn.",
      "the nations that adjoin these waterways depend on them as a source of fresh water."
    ],
    "answer": "the nation that controls these waterways can have economic control over other nations."
  },
  {
    "id": 1531,
    "question": "Why type of map would focus on showing land forms?:",
    "option": [
      "climatic patterns map.",
      "political boundaries map.",
      "physical features map.",
      "weather cycles map."
    ],
    "answer": "physical features map."
  },
  {
    "id": 1532,
    "question": "Which statement about the impact of geography on the development of a region\\'s culture is most accurate?:",
    "option": [
      "geography has little impact on culture.",
      "geographic diversity often leads to cultural diversity.",
      "geography rarely affects the development of early civilizations.",
      "geographic isolation encourages cultural diffusion."
    ],
    "answer": "geographic diversity often leads to cultural diversity."
  },
  {
    "id": 1533,
    "question": "An anthropologist working in a traditional African village would most probably engage in which activity?:",
    "option": [
      "assisting in setting up an irrigation project.",
      "working to set up a village legal system.",
      "studying the language and marriage patterns of the people.",
      "helping to implement a family planning program."
    ],
    "answer": "studying the language and marriage patterns of the people."
  },
  {
    "id": 1534,
    "question": "Which is the most fundamental economic question for every society?:",
    "option": [
      "What form of currency should be used?",
      "Wich which nations should the society trade?",
      "What level of personal income is appropriate?",
      "How should goods and services be produced and distributed?"
    ],
    "answer": "How should goods and services be produced and distributed?"
  },
  {
    "id": 1535,
    "question": "Nationalism is most likely to develop in areas where people have?:",
    "option": [
      "strong local traditions.",
      "a common language and system of laws.",
      "little contact with the outside world.",
      "an economy based on subsistence agriculture."
    ],
    "answer": "a common language and system of laws."
  },
  {
    "id": 1536,
    "question": "A historian would most likely agree with which of the following statements?:",
    "option": [
      "primary sources are subject to different interpretations.",
      "secondary sources are of little value in historical research.",
      "primary sources are effective only if accompanied by a written account by a contemporary author.",
      "secondary sources should primarily be used in studies of political institutions."
    ],
    "answer": "primary sources are subject to different interpretations."
  },
  {
    "id": 1537,
    "question": "Which situation BEST illustrates the concept of the interdependence among nations?:",
    "option": [
      "adoption of a policy of economic nationalism.",
      "establishment by a nation of a system of high protective tariffs.",
      "sales of goods by one nation to obtain scarce resources from another nation.",
      "expansion of international sporting events."
    ],
    "answer": "sales of goods by one nation to obtain scarce resources from another nation."
  },
  {
    "id": 1538,
    "question": "Which is the most valid statement about customs, religion, and family structure?:",
    "option": [
      "they are forms of social control.",
      "their main purpose is to prevent social change.",
      "they are seldom influenced by the existing economic system.",
      "they are often changed by political events."
    ],
    "answer": "they are forms of social control."
  },
  {
    "id": 1539,
    "question": "Which situation is most characteristic of a traditional society?:",
    "option": [
      "college students protest an administration decision.",
      "a local farmer purchases chemical fertilizer.",
      "men and women possess full social equality.",
      "a boy learns his father\\'s craft or occupation."
    ],
    "answer": "a boy learns his father\\'s craft or occupation."
  },
  {
    "id": 1540,
    "question": "The study of the art, music, and literature of a nation helps us better to understand the nation\\'s?:",
    "option": [
      "economic progress.",
      "political development.",
      "cultural values.",
      "technological advancement."
    ],
    "answer": "cultural values."
  },
  {
    "id": 1541,
    "question": "The MOST valid statement concerning societies which have had a \"Golden Age\" is that during these periods they?:",
    "option": [
      "surpassed all preceding cultures in scientific advances.",
      "experienced major accomplishments in the arts, sciences, and literature.",
      "possessed great quantities of natural resources.",
      "developed democratic governments."
    ],
    "answer": "possessed great quantities of natural resources."
  },
  {
    "id": 1542,
    "question": "Social mobility would most likely take place in a society where social class is based on?:",
    "option": [
      "inherited occupations.",
      "racial characteristics.",
      "religious beliefs.",
      "accumulation of weath."
    ],
    "answer": "accumulation of weath."
  },
  {
    "id": 1543,
    "question": "Which is generally characteristic of a nation undergoing the process of industrialization?:",
    "option": [
      "less opportunity for social mobility.",
      "shifts in the population from urban to rural areas.",
      "conflicts between modern ideas and traditional ways of life.",
      "increased reliance on the extended family to supply society\\'s basic needs."
    ],
    "answer": "conflicts between modern ideas and traditional ways of life."
  },
  {
    "id": 1544,
    "question": "Which best defines the term \"culture?:\"",
    "option": [
      "the total learned heritage of a people.",
      "the interaction of peoples within their environment.",
      "the acceptance by one ethnic group of another ethnic group\\'s values and customs.",
      "the adaptation by a less advanced people of the customs and values of a more advanced group."
    ],
    "answer": "the total learned heritage of a people."
  },
  {
    "id": 1545,
    "question": "According to Hinduism, the goal of life should be to?:",
    "option": [
      "free the soul from the cucle of reincarnation.",
      "memorize all prayers in the  Vedas .",
      "worship Vishnu above all other gods.",
      "obey the laws set out by Siddhartha Gautama."
    ],
    "answer": "free the soul from the cucle of reincarnation."
  },
  {
    "id": 1546,
    "question": "Belief in  karma  affects Hindus because it holds that?:",
    "option": [
      "only men can achieve  nirvana .",
      "by following the Eighthfold Path, a person will rise in caste status.",
      "the soul is reincarnated many times.",
      "one\\'s deeds in a current life affects a person\\'s fate in a future life."
    ],
    "answer": "one\\'s deeds in a current life affects a person\\'s fate in a future life."
  },
  {
    "id": 1547,
    "question": "Muslims could not understand the Hindu caste system because they believed that?:",
    "option": [
      "everyone should receive an equal piece of land.",
      "all followers are equal in the eyes of God.",
      "women have the same rights as men.",
      "the state should own all means of making goods."
    ],
    "answer": "all followers are equal in the eyes of God."
  },
  {
    "id": 1548,
    "question": "The religious importance of the story of Krishna in the  Bhagavad-Gita  is?:",
    "option": [
      "that it tells how to be a good Buddhist.",
      "the explanation of the orirings of the gods.",
      "that it explains the idea of deliverance from the wheel of rebirth by obeying one\\'s  dharma .",
      "the explanation of the decline of the caste system."
    ],
    "answer": "that it explains the idea of deliverance from the wheel of rebirth by obeying one\\'s  dharma ."
  },
  {
    "id": 1549,
    "question": "The Hindu religion is based on the traditions of which people?:",
    "option": ["Aryans.", " Vaishyas .", "Persians.", "Greeks."],
    "answer": "Aryans."
  },
  {
    "id": 1550,
    "question": "Why do Hindus believe it is important to follow the path of non-violence?:",
    "option": [
      "practicing non-violence allows them to escape the wheel of fate.",
      "it reinforces the importance of duty.",
      "practicing non-violence improves meditation.",
      "all people and things are aspects of Brahman and should be respected."
    ],
    "answer": "all people and things are aspects of Brahman and should be respected."
  },
  {
    "id": 1551,
    "question": "In addition to providing water for Indian agriculture, the Ganges River remains important to India because it is?:",
    "option": [
      "the only source of Indian hydroelectric power.",
      "a sacred river for the Hindu population.",
      "the birthplace of Hindu civilization.",
      "an unofficial boundary between the Hindus and Muslims."
    ],
    "answer": "a sacred river for the Hindu population."
  },
  {
    "id": 1552,
    "question": "Which of the following statements about Hinduism is an opinion rather than a fact?:",
    "option": [
      "in South Asia, Hindus have stricter beliefs than Muslims.",
      "Hindus worship thousands of gods, even though they are all different manifestations of Brahman.",
      "the majority of people in South Asia are Hindu.",
      "today, as in the past, Hinduism helps shape Indian culture."
    ],
    "answer": "in South Asia, Hindus have stricter beliefs than Muslims."
  },
  {
    "id": 1553,
    "question": "A similarity between Hinduism and Buddhism is that both?:",
    "option": [
      "support the caste system.",
      "are monotheistic.",
      "accept the idea of samsara.",
      "were founded by respected Brahmans."
    ],
    "answer": "accept the idea of samsara."
  },
  {
    "id": 1554,
    "question": "Which of the following is a specific stage of life for the Hindu?:",
    "option": [" ahimsa .", " moksha .", " satyagraha .", "student."],
    "answer": "student."
  },
  {
    "id": 1555,
    "question": "Which statement BEST explains why British India was partitioned in 1947?:",
    "option": [
      "the British feared a united India.",
      "one region of India wanted to remain under British control.",
      "religious differences led to political division.",
      "Communist forces refused to participate in a centralized Indian government."
    ],
    "answer": "religious differences led to political division."
  },
  {
    "id": 1556,
    "question": "In India, the Sikh struggle for independence for the Punjab State and the disagreement between Muslims and Hindus in Kashmir show that?:",
    "option": [
      "religious conflicts can often divide people.",
      "the economy rarely affects politics.",
      "India\\'s non-alignment policy will resolve these conflicts.",
      "foreign influence can help people solve their problems."
    ],
    "answer": "religious conflicts can often divide people."
  },
  {
    "id": 1557,
    "question": "In India, Mohandas Gandhi\\'s support for the rights of women and Harijans illustrates Gandhi\\'s?:",
    "option": [
      "ability to reach agreement with Muslim leaders.",
      "rejection of Western values.",
      "commitment to a policy of non-alignment in world affairs.",
      "willingness to break caste rules in the pursuit of justice."
    ],
    "answer": "willingness to break caste rules in the pursuit of justice."
  },
  {
    "id": 1558,
    "question": "Since the 1950s, India has experienced conflict with both Pakistan and China over?:",
    "option": [
      "United Nations peacekeeping efforts in the region.",
      "India\\'s incrasing trade with Korea.",
      "borders and related territorial issues.",
      "the interpretation of common religious works."
    ],
    "answer": "borders and related territorial issues."
  },
  {
    "id": 1559,
    "question": "The nation of Bangladesh was created as a result of the?:",
    "option": [
      "breakup of the East India Company.",
      "cultural and economic differences between East Pakistan and West Pakistan.",
      "fighting between Hindu and Muslim factors in Nepal.",
      "human rights policy of the United Nations."
    ],
    "answer": "cultural and economic differences between East Pakistan and West Pakistan."
  },
  {
    "id": 1560,
    "question": "Under its policy of non-alignment, India?:",
    "option": [
      "refused to join the United Nations.",
      "signed the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty.",
      "supported East Pakistan in its civil war with West Pakistan.",
      "accepted aid from both the United States and the Soviet Union during the Cold War era."
    ],
    "answer": "accepted aid from both the United States and the Soviet Union during the Cold War era."
  },
  {
    "id": 1561,
    "question": "During the 1980s, a major problem in India was?:",
    "option": [
      "violence resulting from cultural differences.",
      "widespread rejection of the policy of non-alignment.",
      "the increase in Christian missionary activities in Calcutta and Bombay.",
      "the threat of invasion from Pakistan."
    ],
    "answer": "violence resulting from cultural differences."
  },
  {
    "id": 1562,
    "question": "In India, the Green Revolution led directly to?:",
    "option": [
      "the creation of a democratic government.",
      "an increase in food production.",
      "the spread of Buddhism.",
      "the mass migration of people to rural areas."
    ],
    "answer": "an increase in food production."
  },
  {
    "id": 1563,
    "question": "Throughout most of its independent existence, Pakistan has been governed by?:",
    "option": [
      "Muhammed Ali Jinnah.",
      "a functioning parliamentary system.",
      "a military dictatorship.",
      "Islamic clerics."
    ],
    "answer": "a military dictatorship."
  },
  {
    "id": 1564,
    "question": "Many of India\\'s educated professionals have migrated to Europe and the United States.  How has India been affected by this migration?:",
    "option": [
      "many of its students are studying for advanced degrees in architecture.",
      "it has lost the services of many talented doctors and engineers.",
      "its exports to Western nations have decreased.",
      "its citizens have been encouraged to return to their farming villages."
    ],
    "answer": "it has lost the services of many talented doctors and engineers."
  },
  {
    "id": 1565,
    "question": "The problem over Kashmir has brought India into conflict with?:",
    "option": ["Afghanistan.", "China.", "Vietnam.", "Pakistan."],
    "answer": "Pakistan."
  },
  {
    "id": 1566,
    "question": "Which factor has contributed most to the social and cultural identity of the Middle East?:",
    "option": [
      "the political stability of the region.",
      "a lack of foreign involvement in the region.",
      "the ability of the region to export oil.",
      "the strong influence of Islam on the region."
    ],
    "answer": "the strong influence of Islam on the region."
  },
  {
    "id": 1567,
    "question": "Which BEST describes a characteristic of Islam?:",
    "option": [
      "Islam, like other major religions, is composed of sects which sometimes disagree on beliefs and practices.",
      "Islam has largely lost its influence on the daily lives of its followers.",
      "a major goal of Islamic religious leaders is the adaptation of Western cultural ideas.",
      "separation of church and state is a fundamental belief of Islam."
    ],
    "answer": "Islam, like other major religions, is composed of sects which sometimes disagree on beliefs and practices."
  },
  {
    "id": 1568,
    "question": "Which statement about women under Islam is CORRECT?:",
    "option": [
      "according to the  Quran , women had no legal rights.",
      "women were expected to be modest and to obey their fathers or husbands.",
      "in farming villages, women were forbidden to work in the fields.",
      "women had less rights after the spread of Islam than they had before."
    ],
    "answer": "women were expected to be modest and to obey their fathers or husbands."
  },
  {
    "id": 1569,
    "question": "Which statement BEST describes Islamic art and architecture?:",
    "option": [
      "most Islamic art and architecture used only Arab designs and styles.",
      "Islamic architects built mosques but were forbidden to design palaces.",
      "the Islamic world produced little art and architecture because the  Qur\\'an  forbade it.",
      "the architecture of the Islamic world blended Greek, Roman, Persian, and Islamic traditions."
    ],
    "answer": "the architecture of the Islamic world blended Greek, Roman, Persian, and Islamic traditions."
  },
  {
    "id": 1570,
    "question": "Before the appearance of Muhammed in Arabia, life in that area was organized along which of the following lines?:",
    "option": [
      "tribal nomadic societies and small trade towns.",
      "sheikhs ruling each city in Arabia.",
      "a strict rule by one Arabian king.",
      "a central government at Medina."
    ],
    "answer": "tribal nomadic societies and small trade towns."
  },
  {
    "id": 1571,
    "question": "A good Muslim does all of the following EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "believe that Muhammed was God\\'s messenger.",
      "goes to pray in a group at the mosque on Saturday.",
      "reads his holy book, the  Qur\\'an .",
      "fasts and makes a pilgrimage to Mecca at least once in his lifetime."
    ],
    "answer": "goes to pray in a group at the mosque on Saturday."
  },
  {
    "id": 1572,
    "question": "Which of the following is NOT closely related to the other three?:",
    "option": [" Kaabah .", "the Dome of the Rock.", "Mecca.", " Hadj ."],
    "answer": "the Dome of the Rock."
  },
  {
    "id": 1573,
    "question": "Saturday : Judaism ::   _____?_____  : Islam",
    "option": ["Sunday.", "Saturday.", "Monday.", "Friday."],
    "answer": "Friday."
  },
  {
    "id": 1574,
    "question": "Islam changed the status of women by?:",
    "option": [
      "permitting them to enter convents while still pre-teens.",
      "forbidding them to learn Arabic.",
      "giving them some legal and economic rights.",
      "making them equal to men."
    ],
    "answer": "giving them some legal and economic rights."
  },
  {
    "id": 1575,
    "question": "Muslims consider the  Qur\\'an  the greatest written work in Arabic mainly because it?:",
    "option": [
      "is believed to be the word of  Allah .",
      "tells of the life of Muhammed.",
      "protects the \"People of the Book.\"",
      "establishes a system of law, the  Shariah ."
    ],
    "answer": "is believed to be the word of  Allah ."
  },
  {
    "id": 1576,
    "question": "The split between Sunni and Shi\\'ite Muslims began with disagreements over?:",
    "option": [
      "the choice of caliph.",
      "acceptance of the  Qur\\'an  as the Muslim book of sacred scriptures.",
      "a belief in one God.",
      "the required pilgrimage to Mecca."
    ],
    "answer": "the choice of caliph."
  },
  {
    "id": 1577,
    "question": "All of the following are \"Pillars\" of Islam EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "the  shahada .",
      "making apilgrimage to Medina at least once in a Muslim\\'s lifetime.",
      "fasting during  Ramadan .",
      "almsgiving."
    ],
    "answer": "making apilgrimage to Medina at least once in a Muslim\\'s lifetime."
  },
  {
    "id": 1578,
    "question": "In the Middle East, during the Golden Age of Muslim culture, scholars were encouraged to?:",
    "option": [
      "reject all knowledge that was Western European in origin.",
      "ignore the achievements of Chinese culture.",
      "preserve and expand ancient Greek and Roman learning.",
      "accept medieval Western European religious ideas."
    ],
    "answer": "preserve and expand ancient Greek and Roman learning."
  },
  {
    "id": 1579,
    "question": "Ramadan : Islam ::   _____?_____   : Roman Catholicism",
    "option": ["Palm Sunday.", "Christmas.", "Easter.", "Lent."],
    "answer": "Lent."
  },
  {
    "id": 1580,
    "question": "The \\'Umayyads were able to conquer only one region in Europe. That region was?:",
    "option": ["Spain.", "France.", "Russia.", "southern Britain."],
    "answer": "Spain."
  },
  {
    "id": 1581,
    "question": "Generally Christians conquered by the Muslims were permitted to live in peace, but they were forbidden from doing all of the following EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "trying to convert Muslims to Christianity.",
      "intermarriage with Muslims.",
      "attending the same schools as Muslims.",
      "paying taxes."
    ],
    "answer": "paying taxes."
  },
  {
    "id": 1582,
    "question": "Muslim artists and scientists developed and excelled in all of the following crafts EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "mosaics.",
      "calligraphy.",
      "religious sculpture and paintings.",
      "arabesque design."
    ],
    "answer": "religious sculpture and paintings."
  },
  {
    "id": 1583,
    "question": "The economic prosperity of the Islamic Empire was due largely to?:",
    "option": [
      "the development of a feudal manorial economy system.",
      "the spoils of war.",
      "trade and commerce.",
      "the manufacture of steel swords sold to the Chinese and to the Western Europeans."
    ],
    "answer": "trade and commerce."
  },
  {
    "id": 1584,
    "question": "For Jews living under Islam?:",
    "option": [
      "their situation was similar to that of Jews living in Christian Europe.",
      "their status was considerably lower than that of Christians.",
      "they frequently found themselves subject to violent oppression by Muslim governments.",
      "they participated fully in commercial and professional activities and some even became advisors to the caliphs."
    ],
    "answer": "they participated fully in commercial and professional activities and some even became advisors to the caliphs."
  },
  {
    "id": 1585,
    "question": "In Japan, a major economic problem has been the lack of?:",
    "option": [
      "natural resources.",
      "skilled labor.",
      "investment capital.",
      "experienced management."
    ],
    "answer": "natural resources."
  },
  {
    "id": 1586,
    "question": "Only a small portion of Japan is suitable for agriculture because much of the land?:",
    "option": [
      "is covered by rain forests.",
      "lies near the Arctic Circle.",
      "is too mountainous.",
      "does not receive enough rainfall."
    ],
    "answer": "is too mountainous."
  },
  {
    "id": 1587,
    "question": "The rivers of Japan?:",
    "option": [
      "originate near the sea coast.",
      "are important for hydro-electricity.",
      "all flow northward.",
      "serve as ocean highways for many miles up-river."
    ],
    "answer": "are important for hydro-electricity."
  },
  {
    "id": 1588,
    "question": "Which of the following natural disasters strikes Japan frequently?:",
    "option": ["blizzards.", "drought.", "earthquakes.", "dust storms."],
    "answer": "earthquakes."
  },
  {
    "id": 1589,
    "question": "Which of the following is NOT an archipelago?:",
    "option": ["Japan.", "Indonesia.", "the Philippines.", "Taiwan."],
    "answer": "Taiwan."
  },
  {
    "id": 1590,
    "question": "Which of the following Japanese islands is most likely to receive a lot of snowfall in the winter?:",
    "option": ["Kyushu.", "Hokkaido.", "Shikoku.", "Honshu."],
    "answer": "Hokkaido."
  },
  {
    "id": 1591,
    "question": "In terms of resources for industrial use, Japan is most lacking in?:",
    "option": ["hydro-electric power.", "coal.", "petroleum.", "lumber."],
    "answer": "petroleum."
  },
  {
    "id": 1592,
    "question": "Because most of Japan is mountainous, its people lived mostly?:",
    "option": [
      "in the mountains.",
      "on the smallest islands.",
      "in houseboats on Japan\\'s major rivers.",
      "in river valleys and coastal plains."
    ],
    "answer": "in river valleys and coastal plains."
  },
  {
    "id": 1593,
    "question": "Which of the following has the most tropical climate?:",
    "option": ["Kyushu.", "Honshu.", "Shikoku.", "Hokkaido."],
    "answer": "Kyushu."
  },
  {
    "id": 1594,
    "question": "One effect of Japan\\'s geographic isolation was that?:",
    "option": [
      "the Japanese people developed no religion of their own.",
      "writing developed later there than in China.",
      "the people developed a highly centralized social and political life from the beginning.",
      "writing developed earlier than in China."
    ],
    "answer": "writing developed later there than in China."
  },
  {
    "id": 1595,
    "question": "During the 1930s, Japan\\'s foreign policy was based on the strategy of?:",
    "option": [
      "territorial expansion.",
      "rapid consumer growth.",
      "economic isolation.",
      "democratic alliance."
    ],
    "answer": "territorial expansion."
  },
  {
    "id": 1596,
    "question": "Between the Meiji Restoration and World War II, Japan tried to solve the problem of its scarcity of natural resources by?:",
    "option": [
      "establishing a policy of imperialism.",
      "exporting agricultural products in exchange for new technology.",
      "building nuclear power plants.",
      "cooperating with the Soviet Union to gain needed resources."
    ],
    "answer": "exporting agricultural products in exchange for new technology."
  },
  {
    "id": 1597,
    "question": "One reason for Japanese expansion in Asia in the early 1900s was its desire to?:",
    "option": [
      "gain equal status with western imperial powers.",
      "increase the power of the zaibatsu.",
      "attract foreign investment capital.",
      "reduce the power of the military."
    ],
    "answer": "gain equal status with western imperial powers."
  },
  {
    "id": 1598,
    "question": "The military gained influence in Japan as a result of the?:",
    "option": [
      "burning of the Japanese Parliament.",
      "assassination of Emperor Hirohito.",
      "depression of 1929.",
      "the Long March."
    ],
    "answer": "depression of 1929."
  },
  {
    "id": 1599,
    "question": "Which was the chief victim of Japan\\'s imperialistic aggression in Asia during the years 1915-1939?:",
    "option": ["Thailand.", "Japan.", "the U. S. S. R.", "China."],
    "answer": "China."
  },
  {
    "id": 1600,
    "question": "In the 1930s, Manchuria became a symbol of Japan\\'s?:",
    "option": [
      "attempts to aid underdeveloped regions.",
      "desire for empire.",
      "religious conversion to Christianity.",
      "experimentation with a socialist government."
    ],
    "answer": "desire for empire."
  },
  {
    "id": 1601,
    "question": "Japan was recognized to be a world power as a result of?:",
    "option": [
      "adoption of a new constitution.",
      "ending feudalism in 1871.",
      "returning Taiwan to China.",
      "defeating Russia in 1905."
    ],
    "answer": "defeating Russia in 1905."
  },
  {
    "id": 1602,
    "question": "One factor which contributed to the poor relations between the United States and Japan in the early part of the 20c was?:",
    "option": [
      "the US alliance with the Soviet Union and Germany.",
      "the US racial policies and practics against Oriental immigrants.",
      "the US refusal to participate in the Washington Naval Conference.",
      "the practice of taking over control of the zaibatsu."
    ],
    "answer": "the US racial policies and practics against Oriental immigrants."
  },
  {
    "id": 1603,
    "question": "The Greater East Asia Co-Prosperity Sphere was the label given to?:",
    "option": [
      "Japan\\'s plan for her economic and political control of East Asia.",
      "Japan\\'s puppet kingdom in Manchuria.",
      "Japan\\'s new capital.",
      "the military dominated zaibatsu."
    ],
    "answer": "Japan\\'s plan for her economic and political control of East Asia."
  },
  {
    "id": 1604,
    "question": "Under the militarists, the Japanese government taught schoolchildren?:",
    "option": [
      "Western ideas.",
      "communist ideology.",
      "independent thinking.",
      "service to the state."
    ],
    "answer": "service to the state."
  },
  {
    "id": 1605,
    "question": "During World War I, Japan declared itself?:",
    "option": [
      "allied with Germany to take control of the seas from Great Britain.",
      "against the United States for ideological reasons.",
      "neutral to continue to trade with both sides.",
      "against Germany to advance its interests in East Asia."
    ],
    "answer": "against Germany to advance its interests in East Asia."
  },
  {
    "id": 1606,
    "question": "Between the World Wars, Japanese politics?:",
    "option": [
      "were controlled by the absolutist emperor.",
      "became increasingly liberalized and democratic.",
      "were characterized by militarism and assassination.",
      "adhered to pacifist public opinion."
    ],
    "answer": "were characterized by militarism and assassination."
  },
  {
    "id": 1607,
    "question": "After the Manchurian [Mukden] Incident and the invasion of China, Japanese military leaders accurately concluded that?:",
    "option": [
      "neither the League of Nations, Great Britain, France, nor the United States was willing to take forceful steps to stop Japanese aggression.",
      "they had better retreat from their expansionist goals because of international opposition.",
      "they had accomplished all of their objectives.",
      "they had better launch an immediate attack on Germany."
    ],
    "answer": "neither the League of Nations, Great Britain, France, nor the United States was willing to take forceful steps to stop Japanese aggression."
  },
  {
    "id": 1608,
    "question": "By late 1941, the Japanese government was under the leadership and control of?:",
    "option": [
      "Premier Hara.",
      "General Tojo.",
      "zaibatsu leaders.",
      "the major political parties."
    ],
    "answer": "General Tojo."
  },
  {
    "id": 1609,
    "question": "In Japan, the samurai code of Bushido helped bring about?:",
    "option": [
      "equality among Japanese citizens.",
      "a culture that accepted militarism.",
      "peaceful relations with other nations.",
      "an increased interest in science and technology."
    ],
    "answer": "a culture that accepted militarism."
  },
  {
    "id": 1610,
    "question": "Japanese Emperors claimed to be descended from?:",
    "option": [
      "the Buddha.",
      "the Ainu.",
      "the first Chinese Emperor.",
      "the sun goddess, Amaterasu."
    ],
    "answer": "the sun goddess, Amaterasu."
  },
  {
    "id": 1611,
    "question": "During the 600s and 700s, the Japanese adapted many ideas from?:",
    "option": ["China.", "India.", "Islam.", "the Mongols."],
    "answer": "China."
  },
  {
    "id": 1612,
    "question": "During the feudal periods in Japan and Europe, a family\\'s wealth was mainly determined by the?:",
    "option": [
      "number of children in the family.",
      "size of the castles built by the family.",
      "amount of land the family controlled.",
      "value of the family\\'s gifts to religious leaders."
    ],
    "answer": "amount of land the family controlled."
  },
  {
    "id": 1613,
    "question": "Japan\\'s location influenced its early history in part because it?:",
    "option": [
      "encouraged close ties with India.",
      "protected Japan from invasion.",
      "helped Japan control most of Asia.",
      "protected Japan from earthquakes."
    ],
    "answer": "protected Japan from invasion."
  },
  {
    "id": 1614,
    "question": "Which has been most consistently true of Japanese emperors throughout history?:",
    "option": [
      "they have ruled Japan with absolute power.",
      "they have periodically been elected by the people.",
      "they have continued to occupy the throne, but at times with little power.",
      "they have headed parliamentarly governments."
    ],
    "answer": "they have continued to occupy the throne, but at times with little power."
  },
  {
    "id": 1615,
    "question": "Which figure would compare best to feudal Japan\\'s shogun?:",
    "option": [
      "a president of a modern corporation.",
      "a military dictator.",
      "the Prime Minister of England.",
      "a Christian missionary."
    ],
    "answer": "a military dictator."
  },
  {
    "id": 1616,
    "question": "Yoritomo, who became the first Shogun?:",
    "option": [
      "outlawed further cultural borrowing from China.",
      "helped establish Christianity as a major religion.",
      "began to build Japan into a modern industrial nation.",
      "took political power away from the emperor."
    ],
    "answer": "took political power away from the emperor."
  },
  {
    "id": 1617,
    "question": "The Kamakura Shogunate began after the?:",
    "option": [
      "Mongol invasion.",
      "fall of the Manchu Dynasty in China.",
      "end of the Heian period.",
      "reign of Ieyasu."
    ],
    "answer": "end of the Heian period."
  },
  {
    "id": 1618,
    "question": "The samurai code of Bushido stressed?:",
    "option": [
      "loyalty and indifference to pain.",
      "individualism and self-interest.",
      "generosity and social reform.",
      "scholarship and gentility."
    ],
    "answer": "loyalty and indifference to pain."
  },
  {
    "id": 1619,
    "question": "The shoen was they?:",
    "option": [
      "highly stylized theater popular in Tokugawa Japan.",
      "traditional form of dress worn by the samurai warrior.",
      "complex relationship between the emperor and shogunate established by Tokugawa Ieyasu.",
      "land and the corresponding right to its income held by feudal lords in Japan."
    ],
    "answer": "land and the corresponding right to its income held by feudal lords in Japan."
  },
  {
    "id": 1620,
    "question": "Upper class women played an important role in Japanese?:",
    "option": [
      "religious teachings.",
      "govenrment.",
      "literary development.",
      "economic growth."
    ],
    "answer": "literary development."
  },
  {
    "id": 1621,
    "question": "Which one of the following BEST characterizes the government of early Heian Japan?:",
    "option": [
      "local governments that had strong authority.",
      "a strong central government.",
      "a democracy with an assembly of citizens.",
      "a separate empire in each of the Japanese islands."
    ],
    "answer": "a strong central government."
  },
  {
    "id": 1622,
    "question": "The Japanese learned all of these from China EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "the belief that the emperor was divine and could do no wrong.",
      "the Confucian stress on forms of behavior and ancestor worship.",
      "central government administraiton.",
      "Buddhism."
    ],
    "answer": "the belief that the emperor was divine and could do no wrong."
  },
  {
    "id": 1623,
    "question": "Japan\\'s closeness to the Asian mainland resulted in the Japanese borrowing the?:",
    "option": [
      "tomb culture from China.",
      "Indian caste system.",
      "Shinto religion from Korea.",
      "Chinese writing system."
    ],
    "answer": "Chinese writing system."
  },
  {
    "id": 1624,
    "question": "A samurai committed seppuku?:",
    "option": [
      "when he wished to avoid surrender.",
      "to make up for a mistake or a crime.",
      "when his actions had been questioned.",
      "all of these choices are correct."
    ],
    "answer": "all of these choices are correct."
  },
  {
    "id": 1625,
    "question": "A major difference between the societies of the United States and Japan is the presence in the United States of a higher degree of?:",
    "option": [
      "religious conformity.",
      "cultural diversity.",
      "economic security.",
      "access to elementary education."
    ],
    "answer": "cultural diversity."
  },
  {
    "id": 1626,
    "question": "In the period since World War II, Japan has dealt with its shortage of natural resources mainly by following a policy of?:",
    "option": [
      "becoming an agriculturally oriented nation.",
      "enforcing a program of austerity for its civilian population.",
      "attempting to take over nearby resource-rich nations.",
      "developing many industrial products for export."
    ],
    "answer": "developing many industrial products for export."
  },
  {
    "id": 1627,
    "question": "An accurate description of life in Japan today is that the Japanese people have?:",
    "option": [
      "remained a largely rural, agricultural society.",
      "isolated themselves from Western culture.",
      "blended traditional ways with Western ways to meed the needs of modern life.",
      "achieved their goal of a classless society in which all people benefit from economic progress."
    ],
    "answer": "blended traditional ways with Western ways to meed the needs of modern life."
  },
  {
    "id": 1628,
    "question": "Which is the best explanation for Japan\\'s current industrial success?:",
    "option": [
      "need to support heavy military expenses.",
      "vast reserves of raw materials and fossil fuels.",
      "the government\\'s role in setting and supporting national goals.",
      "emphasis on individual achievement rather than group effort."
    ],
    "answer": "the government\\'s role in setting and supporting national goals."
  },
  {
    "id": 1629,
    "question": "Growth in the Japanese economy since World War II has been accomplished despite the fact that Japan has?:",
    "option": [
      "little modern technology.",
      "high unemployment.",
      "low worker productivity.",
      "few natural resources."
    ],
    "answer": "few natural resources."
  },
  {
    "id": 1630,
    "question": "Even though Japan has few natural resources, it has a high standard of living mainly because it has?:",
    "option": [
      "developed technology that can be exchanged for the resources it needs.",
      "printed more money whenever living standards have started to decline.",
      "imported manufactured goods.",
      "produced goods and services without obtaining resources."
    ],
    "answer": "developed technology that can be exchanged for the resources it needs."
  },
  {
    "id": 1631,
    "question": "Which reform took place in Japan after World War II?:",
    "option": [
      "Japan\\'s industrial capability was greatly reduced.",
      "the emperor\\'s position was abolished.",
      "Japan became a representative democracy.",
      "labor unions were declared illegal."
    ],
    "answer": "Japan became a representative democracy."
  },
  {
    "id": 1632,
    "question": "In recent years, which factor has been a major reason for the economic tensions between the United States and Japan?:",
    "option": [
      "the United States imported more from Japan than it exported to Japan.",
      "Japan\\'s trade deficit with the United States was very high.",
      "the United States refused to place quotas on Japanese goods.",
      "Japan lowered tariffs on goods imported from the United States."
    ],
    "answer": "the United States imported more from Japan than it exported to Japan."
  },
  {
    "id": 1633,
    "question": "\"Tokyo Stock Market Drops 130 Points\"                      \"London Exchange Falls Following Japanese Drop\" These headlines reflect?:",
    "option": [
      "an attitude of ethnocentrism on the part of the European nations.",
      "global interdependence in economic matters.",
      "the growth of socialism in Europe and Asia.",
      "the problems arising from a positionn of non-alignment."
    ],
    "answer": "global interdependence in economic matters."
  },
  {
    "id": 1634,
    "question": "The government of Japan is best described as?:",
    "option": [
      "a military dictatorship.",
      "an absolute monarchy.",
      "a parliamentary system.",
      "a Communist dictatorship."
    ],
    "answer": "a parliamentary system."
  },
  {
    "id": 1635,
    "question": "A major goal of the Christian Church during the Crusades [1096-1291] was to?:",
    "option": [
      "establish Christianity in Western Europe.",
      "capture the Holy Land from Islamic rulers.",
      "unite warring Arab peoples.",
      "strengthen English dominance in the Arab world."
    ],
    "answer": "capture the Holy Land from Islamic rulers."
  },
  {
    "id": 1636,
    "question": "A major result of the Crusades was the?:",
    "option": [
      "conversion of the majority of Europeans to Protestantism.",
      "weakening of the power of the middle class in the Ottoman Empire.",
      "growth of trade between Europe and Asia.",
      "development of feudalism in Africa."
    ],
    "answer": "growth of trade between Europe and Asia."
  },
  {
    "id": 1637,
    "question": "One way in which the Seljuk Turks and Mongols were similar is that they both?:",
    "option": [
      "emerged from Central Asia.",
      "were defeated by the Byzantine Empire.",
      "traded along the sea routes of the Mediterranean with Rome.",
      "developed unique forms of Christianity."
    ],
    "answer": "emerged from Central Asia."
  },
  {
    "id": 1638,
    "question": "An observation about the Ottoman Empire in the 15c and 16c is that the Empire?:",
    "option": [
      "originated in Hungary.",
      "had a strategic location between Europe and Asia.",
      "was totally landlocked.",
      "had control over most of Western Europe."
    ],
    "answer": "had a strategic location between Europe and Asia."
  },
  {
    "id": 1639,
    "question": "The rivalry between Ottoman and Safavid Empires was fueled in par by differences over?:",
    "option": [
      "religion.",
      "whether to recognize European diplomats in their courts.",
      "language.",
      "who should control the Bosphorus Straits."
    ],
    "answer": "religion."
  },
  {
    "id": 1640,
    "question": "Which statement about the Ottoman Empire is supported by the facts?:",
    "option": [
      "the Ottomans destroyed the Arab Empire.",
      "the Ottoman Empire ruled the Middle East during the Golden Age of Islam.",
      "the Ottomans were generally tolerant of the diverse peoples in their empire.",
      "Ottoman rulers relied on the Persians to enforce their control over the Middle East."
    ],
    "answer": "the Ottomans were generally tolerant of the diverse peoples in their empire."
  },
  {
    "id": 1641,
    "question": "The elite army corps composed primarily of Christian slaves was known as the?:",
    "option": ["ghazis.", "pashas.", "sahibs.", "janissaries."],
    "answer": "janissaries."
  },
  {
    "id": 1642,
    "question": "The final collapse of the Byzantine and Arab Islamic empires was caused by?:",
    "option": [
      "the revival of the Roman Empire in Western Europe.",
      "the success of Slavic invasions of the Balkan Peninsula.",
      "their defeat by the Seljuk Turks.",
      "the conquests of the Ottoman Turks."
    ],
    "answer": "the conquests of the Ottoman Turks."
  },
  {
    "id": 1643,
    "question": "The Ottoman and Safavid empires shared the Muslim tradition of?:",
    "option": [
      "the  Sharia.",
      "peaceful non-violent protests by the people against their government.",
      "religious intolerance.",
      "massive, gaudy architectural styles."
    ],
    "answer": "the  Sharia."
  },
  {
    "id": 1644,
    "question": "The Ottoman Empire reached its Golden Age during the reign of?:",
    "option": ["Abu Bakr.", "Mehmet I.", "Osman.", "Suleiman the Great."],
    "answer": "Suleiman the Great."
  },
  {
    "id": 1645,
    "question": "In 1453, the Ottomans captured which of the following cities?:",
    "option": ["Isfahan.", "Constantinople.", "Baghdad.", "Cairo."],
    "answer": "Constantinople."
  },
  {
    "id": 1646,
    "question": "Which event brought about the breakup of the Ottoman Empire?:",
    "option": [
      "Six-Day War.",
      "the Crusades.",
      "World War I.",
      "World War II."
    ],
    "answer": "World War I."
  },
  {
    "id": 1647,
    "question": "A major threat to the Ottoman Empire in the 1800s was?:",
    "option": [
      "socialism.",
      "anti-Semitism.",
      "industrialization.",
      "nationalism."
    ],
    "answer": "nationalism."
  },
  {
    "id": 1648,
    "question": "Ataturk is best remembered for?:",
    "option": [
      "modernizing Turkey.",
      "overthrowing the Safavid Shahs.",
      "ending European imperialism in Egypt.",
      "forcing the British to leave Jerusalem."
    ],
    "answer": "modernizing Turkey."
  },
  {
    "id": 1649,
    "question": "The Zionist movement primarily desired to?:",
    "option": [
      "create a Jewish homeland in Palestine.",
      "stop the persecution of Jews in England.",
      "free Jerusalem from Arab control.",
      "fight against the Ottoman Turks."
    ],
    "answer": "create a Jewish homeland in Palestine."
  },
  {
    "id": 1650,
    "question": "Under the League of Nations, the former colonies of the Ottoman and German empires were to be assisted in forming their own government.  The result of this new mandate system was to?:",
    "option": [
      "establish dictatorships in the mandated countries.",
      "put the former colonial peoples on the road to self-government.",
      "prohibit the colonization of these territories.",
      "take economic advantage of the former colonies."
    ],
    "answer": "put the former colonial peoples on the road to self-government."
  },
  {
    "id": 1651,
    "question": "The Sykes-Picot Agreement and the Balfour Declaration ignored the nationalistic feelings of the?:",
    "option": [
      "African people.",
      "Arab people.",
      "Iranian people.",
      "Turkish people."
    ],
    "answer": "Arab people."
  },
  {
    "id": 1652,
    "question": "The primary cause of the Armenian Massacres of 1915 was?:",
    "option": [
      "Armenian aid to the Germans during World War I.",
      "the refusal of the Armenians to sell oil to the Central Powers.",
      "centuries long Russian hatred toward the Armenians.",
      "Turkish fears that Armenians might be conspiring with the Russians."
    ],
    "answer": "Turkish fears that Armenians might be conspiring with the Russians."
  },
  {
    "id": 1653,
    "question": "In 1907, Persia was divided into spheres of influence by?:",
    "option": [
      "France and the United States.",
      "Russia and Britain.",
      "the United States and Russia.",
      "Afghanistan and the Ottoman Empire."
    ],
    "answer": "Russia and Britain."
  },
  {
    "id": 1654,
    "question": "A major result of the growth of Zionism in the late 1800s was the?:",
    "option": [
      "defeat of the Ottoman Empire.",
      "formation of the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO).",
      "immigration of European Jews to Palestine.",
      "increased tensions between the superpowers in the Middle East."
    ],
    "answer": "immigration of European Jews to Palestine."
  },
  {
    "id": 1655,
    "question": "After 1929, the majority of Jewish emigrants to Palestine came from?:",
    "option": [
      "the United States.",
      "Europe (largely Germany and Poland).",
      "Russia.",
      "the Arab states."
    ],
    "answer": "Europe (largely Germany and Poland)."
  },
  {
    "id": 1656,
    "question": "In the Middle East, most of the land suitable for farming is found in the?:",
    "option": [
      "rain forest.",
      "savanna regions.",
      "mountain areas.",
      "river valleys."
    ],
    "answer": "river valleys."
  },
  {
    "id": 1657,
    "question": "A major problem for most nations of the Middle East has been the?:",
    "option": [
      "lack of fresh water.",
      "long, frigid winters.",
      "monsoon flooding.",
      "lack of mineral resources."
    ],
    "answer": "lack of fresh water."
  },
  {
    "id": 1658,
    "question": "The Middle East has many deserts. The main effect of the desert has been?:",
    "option": [
      "an expanding rain forest.",
      "political instability.",
      "difficulty in raising sufficient food.",
      "a lack of religious unity."
    ],
    "answer": "difficulty in raising sufficient food."
  },
  {
    "id": 1659,
    "question": "A study of the population distribution of the Middle East would show that people?:",
    "option": [
      "are evenly distributed throughout the Middle East.",
      "generally settle near water supplies.",
      "want to live near the large oil reserves.",
      "generally live in the mountains."
    ],
    "answer": "generally settle near water supplies."
  },
  {
    "id": 1660,
    "question": "Which geographic feature has been most responsible for the population distribution in the Middle East?:",
    "option": [
      "abundance of oil deposits.",
      "presence of high plateaus.",
      "availability of natural harbors.",
      "location of water."
    ],
    "answer": "location of water."
  },
  {
    "id": 1661,
    "question": "The lands of the Middle East can be studied as one region because they are similar in all of the following ways EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "they are ruled by similar types of governments.",
      "they all have the same kind of climate.",
      "most of the people are Muslims.",
      "they have similar problems."
    ],
    "answer": "they are ruled by similar types of governments."
  },
  {
    "id": 1662,
    "question": "Which of the following countries does NOT lie within the Fertile Crescent?:",
    "option": ["Lebanon.", "Syria.", "Libya.", "Iraq."],
    "answer": "Libya."
  },
  {
    "id": 1663,
    "question": "The most densely populated area of the Middle East today is the?:",
    "option": [
      "Iranian Plateau.",
      "Nile River Delta.",
      "Jordan River Valley.",
      "Lebanon."
    ],
    "answer": "Nile River Delta."
  },
  {
    "id": 1664,
    "question": "The Fertile Crescent is the arc of land that?:",
    "option": [
      "lies between the Tigris and Euphrates rivers.",
      "lies along the banks of the Nile River.",
      "reaches down to the African kingdom of Axum.",
      "curves from the Persian Gulf to the Nile Delta."
    ],
    "answer": "curves from the Persian Gulf to the Nile Delta."
  },
  {
    "id": 1665,
    "question": "The Gupta Empire enjoyed a Golden Age in part because of the?:",
    "option": [
      "spread of Buddhism.",
      "general peace and prosperity of the times.",
      "invention of the decimal system.",
      "power of the Dehil sultans."
    ],
    "answer": "general peace and prosperity of the times."
  },
  {
    "id": 1666,
    "question": "Which statement is best supported by a study of the history of South Asia?:",
    "option": [
      "invaders and local princes battled for control of the northern plain.",
      "the British were the first rulers to unite India.",
      "cultural diversity helped strong Indian leaders unify their kingdoms.",
      "powerful kingdoms in southern India after conquered the Indo-Gangetic Plain."
    ],
    "answer": "invaders and local princes battled for control of the northern plain."
  },
  {
    "id": 1667,
    "question": "During India\\'s early history, Indian social and family life centered on the?:",
    "option": ["city-state.", "mosque.", "village.", "sultanate."],
    "answer": "village."
  },
  {
    "id": 1668,
    "question": "All of the following are true statements about the reign of Asoka EXCEPT that?:",
    "option": [
      "under his rule, the Gupta Empire reached it greatest size.",
      "he converted to Buddhism during his reign.",
      "he practiced toleration of all religions.",
      "he sent Buddhist missionaries to Southeast Asia."
    ],
    "answer": "under his rule, the Gupta Empire reached it greatest size."
  },
  {
    "id": 1669,
    "question": "Which region of India was never united by a conqueror?:",
    "option": [
      "the Deccan.",
      "southern India.",
      "northern India.",
      "eastern India."
    ],
    "answer": "southern India."
  },
  {
    "id": 1670,
    "question": "The plays of the Indian dramatist Kalidasa were known for their?:",
    "option": [
      "use of tragedy as a main theme of each play.",
      "focus on religious themes.",
      "skill with comedic timing.",
      "focus on emotions."
    ],
    "answer": "focus on emotions."
  },
  {
    "id": 1671,
    "question": "What impact did Gupta mathematicians have on civilization?:",
    "option": [
      "they developed basid algebra.",
      "they developed the Arabic number system and the concept of zero.",
      "very few advances were made in mathematics during the Gupta dynasty.",
      "they developed Euclidean geometry."
    ],
    "answer": "they developed the Arabic number system and the concept of zero."
  },
  {
    "id": 1672,
    "question": "One cause of the Maurya Empire\\'s collapse was?:",
    "option": [
      "the death of Chandragupta II.",
      "invasions along the northwestern border.",
      "Hindu resentment of pro-Buddhist policies.",
      "popular unrest generated by heavy taxation."
    ],
    "answer": "popular unrest generated by heavy taxation."
  },
  {
    "id": 1673,
    "question": "Throughout most of its history, the political structure of India consisted of?:",
    "option": [
      "a strong centralized government tightly controlling the entire territory.",
      "total domination by Europeans.",
      "a complex pattern of separate independent states.",
      "control by the rival Chinese empire."
    ],
    "answer": "a complex pattern of separate independent states."
  },
  {
    "id": 1674,
    "question": "Which of the following were examples of the many accomplishments of the Gupta period in Indian history?: 1 - a lunar calandar of 28-day months. 2 - the idea that the earth was round. 3 - the classification of over 500 new viruses. 4 - brain surgery. 5 - the setting of broken bones.",
    "option": ["5 only.", "1, 3, 4, and 5.", "2, 3, and 4.", "1 and 5 only."],
    "answer": "5 only."
  },
  {
    "id": 1675,
    "question": "The primary reason that the Japanese policy of near-isolation ended in 1853-54 was that Japan?:",
    "option": [
      "needed additional territory as an outlet for its surplus population.",
      "became involved in a war with China.",
      "needed European markets for its manufactured goods.",
      "was pressured by American naval power to open its ports."
    ],
    "answer": "was pressured by American naval power to open its ports."
  },
  {
    "id": 1676,
    "question": "In an attempt to modernize Japan during the late 1800s, the leaders of the Meiji government decided to?:",
    "option": [
      "study Western institutions and technology.",
      "established close relations with China.",
      "maintain a policy of isolationism.",
      "end the political power of the Buddhists in the government."
    ],
    "answer": "study Western institutions and technology."
  },
  {
    "id": 1677,
    "question": "Which statement best explains Japan\\'s relationships with other nations since the 1860s?:",
    "option": [
      "an abundance of natural resources has made Japan self-sufficient.",
      "Japan\\'s island location has discouraged Japanese imperialism.",
      "Japan has needed to acquire sufficient raw materials for its industries.",
      "rejection of foreign technology has forced Japan into isolation."
    ],
    "answer": "Japan has needed to acquire sufficient raw materials for its industries."
  },
  {
    "id": 1678,
    "question": "Japan\\'s defeat of Russia in 1905 encouraged natinonalist hopes in Southeast Asia because?:",
    "option": [
      "Japan promised to supported independence movements in Southeast Asia.",
      "an Asian nation defeated a major European power.",
      "all the Russian colonies in the area became independent.",
      "Japan was China\\'s chief rival in the area."
    ],
    "answer": "an Asian nation defeated a major European power."
  },
  {
    "id": 1679,
    "question": "A social reform of the Meiji Restoration was to?:",
    "option": [
      "make Japan a multiparty democracy.",
      "expand Japanese power in Asia.",
      "build factories on western models.",
      "make everyone equal before the law."
    ],
    "answer": "make everyone equal before the law."
  },
  {
    "id": 1680,
    "question": "Unlike China during the Age of European Imperialism, Japan?:",
    "option": [
      "modernized rapidly.",
      "had to sign unequal treaties with western nations.",
      "was able to isolate itself from the world.",
      "rejected its Confucian traditions."
    ],
    "answer": "modernized rapidly."
  },
  {
    "id": 1681,
    "question": "Which of the following exports financed Japan\\'s economic expansion during the Meiji period?:",
    "option": [
      "electronics.",
      "porcelain.",
      "steam locomotive technology.",
      "silk."
    ],
    "answer": "silk."
  },
  {
    "id": 1682,
    "question": "The modernization of Japan during the Meiji Restoration resulted in?:",
    "option": [
      "a return to a feudal system of government.",
      "the rise of Japan as an imperialistic nation.",
      "an alliance between China, Korea, Russia, and Japan.",
      "a strengthening of Japan\\'s isolationist policies."
    ],
    "answer": "the rise of Japan as an imperialistic nation."
  },
  {
    "id": 1683,
    "question": "In the past, the flooding of the Nile River resulted in?:",
    "option": [
      "huge loss of human lives.",
      "the building of large temples and palaces.",
      "the deposit of rich soil along the valley.",
      "dangerous leaching of the soil."
    ],
    "answer": "the deposit of rich soil along the valley."
  },
  {
    "id": 1684,
    "question": "What evidence supports the conclusion that government and religion were closely linked in ancient Egypt?:",
    "option": [
      "Egyptians believed their ruler was a god.",
      "the people believed in an afterlife.",
      "priests conducted ceremonies to please the gods.",
      "Egyptians were polytheistic."
    ],
    "answer": "Egyptians believed their ruler was a god."
  },
  {
    "id": 1685,
    "question": "The Rosetta Stone was most useful for?:",
    "option": [
      "identifying the early gods of the Egyptians.",
      "tracing the wanderings of the Jews.",
      "predicting ancient eclipses.",
      "deciphering hieroglyphic writing."
    ],
    "answer": "deciphering hieroglyphic writing."
  },
  {
    "id": 1686,
    "question": "Which of the following statements about Egyptian society is true?:  1 -- A person was born into his or her social class.  2 -- The majority of Egyptians were peasants.  3 -- Soldiers were more powerful than priests.  4 -- Only slaves learned to read and write.",
    "option": ["1 only.", "1 & 2.", "2 & 3.", "4 only."],
    "answer": "1 & 2."
  },
  {
    "id": 1687,
    "question": "The need to survey land after the Nile\\'s floods led to the development of?:",
    "option": ["astronomy.", "navigation.", "geometry.", "engineering."],
    "answer": "geometry."
  },
  {
    "id": 1688,
    "question": "The contribution of Menes to the development of Egypt was?:",
    "option": [
      "to build the first pyramid.",
      "to develop a system of irrigation.",
      "to organize villags into individual city-states.",
      "to unite Upper and Lower Egypt."
    ],
    "answer": "to unite Upper and Lower Egypt."
  },
  {
    "id": 1689,
    "question": "The Egyptian  Book of the Dead  contains?",
    "option": [
      "the Ten Commandments, which Moses gave to the Israelites.",
      "the story of the pharaoh Akhenaton\\'s worship of Ra, the sun.",
      "rituals and secret magical formulas to help individuals pass into the afterlife.",
      "all of these choices are correct."
    ],
    "answer": "rituals and secret magical formulas to help individuals pass into the afterlife."
  },
  {
    "id": 1690,
    "question": "How did Egyptians respond to Hatshepsut\\'s rule?:",
    "option": [
      "they were opposed to the concept of having a woman as a ruler.",
      "they welcomed such an able ruler.",
      "they never knew she was a woman because drawings always showed her wearing a beard.",
      "they feared her because they thought she was a sorceress."
    ],
    "answer": "they were opposed to the concept of having a woman as a ruler."
  },
  {
    "id": 1691,
    "question": "A comparison of Mesopotamian and Egyptian civilizations shows that both?:",
    "option": [
      "used cuneiform.",
      "had identical river systems.",
      "had rulers who were preceived as omnipotent gods.",
      "had a powerful priesthood."
    ],
    "answer": "had a powerful priesthood."
  },
  {
    "id": 1692,
    "question": "An Egyptian pharaoh was different from other monarchs of the ancient world in that?:",
    "option": [
      "he could only marry after the death of his father.",
      "he was worshipped as a living god.",
      "he was considered divine after his death, when he became lord of the underworld.",
      "he was not allowed to marry until his mother had approved his choice for a wife."
    ],
    "answer": "he was worshipped as a living god."
  },
  {
    "id": 1693,
    "question": "In Ancient Egypt, the early pharaohs\\' belief in their own divinity led them to?:",
    "option": [
      "be mummified for their afterlife.",
      "rule with the aid of viziers or personal ministers and advisors.",
      "conquer surrounding peoples.",
      "maintain large standing armies."
    ],
    "answer": "be mummified for their afterlife."
  },
  {
    "id": 1694,
    "question": "Compared with other ancient societies, women in ancient Egypt?:",
    "option": [
      "had far less independence and fewer rights.",
      "were never seen in public or allowed to work outside the home.",
      "had far more independence and rights.",
      "never held political offices."
    ],
    "answer": "had far more independence and rights."
  },
  {
    "id": 1695,
    "question": "A long-term effect of the Balfour Declaration on the Middle East was the?:",
    "option": [
      "oppression of the Kurds by the government of Iraq.",
      "conflict between the Palestinians and the Israelis.",
      "strengthening of parliamentary rule in Turkey.",
      "establishment of a two-party system in Lebanon."
    ],
    "answer": "conflict between the Palestinians and the Israelis."
  },
  {
    "id": 1696,
    "question": "The main goal of the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO) is to?:",
    "option": [
      "win parliamentary seats in Israel.",
      "reduce international involvement in Middle Eastern affairs.",
      "strengthen Israeli control over the occupied territories.",
      "create an independent Palestinian state."
    ],
    "answer": "create an independent Palestinian state."
  },
  {
    "id": 1697,
    "question": "The Egyptian-Israeli War in 1973 led directly to the?:",
    "option": [
      "freedom of the Palestinian people.",
      "first Arab oil embargo.",
      "creation of the PLO.",
      "expansion of OPEC."
    ],
    "answer": "first Arab oil embargo."
  },
  {
    "id": 1698,
    "question": "The mass murder of European Jews during the Holocaust directly influenced the growth of which of the following movements?:",
    "option": ["Zionism.", "industrialism.", "communism.", "Pan-Africanism."],
    "answer": "Zionism."
  },
  {
    "id": 1699,
    "question": "One factor that has greatly contributed to instability in the Middle East has been the?:",
    "option": [
      "European demand for Mideast oil.",
      "issue of a Palestinian homeland.",
      "attempt to unify all Arab peoples.",
      "UN peace-keeping forces there."
    ],
    "answer": "issue of a Palestinian homeland."
  },
  {
    "id": 1700,
    "question": "UN Resolution 242 and the Camp David Accords were attempts to?:",
    "option": [
      "force Israeli withdrawal from Jerusalem.",
      "settle water rights to the Jordan River.",
      "bring about peace in the Middle East.",
      "provide better housing for Palestinian refugees."
    ],
    "answer": "bring about peace in the Middle East."
  },
  {
    "id": 1701,
    "question": "A goal of the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) is to?:",
    "option": [
      "find alternative fuel for automobiles.",
      "control world oil prices.",
      "force Syrian troops to leave Lebanon.",
      "stop the production of oil."
    ],
    "answer": "control world oil prices."
  },
  {
    "id": 1702,
    "question": "The Suez Canal and the Persian Gulf are important bodies of water because they are?:",
    "option": [
      "considered holy to Middle Eastern religions.",
      "sources of hydroelectric power.",
      "barriers to invasions of the Middle East.",
      "routes for trade with other regions."
    ],
    "answer": "routes for trade with other regions."
  },
  {
    "id": 1703,
    "question": "Many Arab nations in the past had conflicts with the nation of Israel because?:",
    "option": [
      "the government of Israel was supported by the Soviet Union.",
      "Israel refused to share its technology with those Arab nations.",
      "Israel occupied territory that was formerly held by the Arabs.",
      "Israel has tried to convert the Arabs to Judaism."
    ],
    "answer": "Israel occupied territory that was formerly held by the Arabs."
  },
  {
    "id": 1704,
    "question": "One goal of Islamic fundamentalist governments in the Middle East is to?:",
    "option": [
      "protect Islamic culture from becoming westernized.",
      "increase Arab trade around the world.",
      "improve economic opportunities for women in Islamic nations.",
      "join the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO)."
    ],
    "answer": "protect Islamic culture from becoming westernized."
  },
  {
    "id": 1705,
    "question": "Of the four Arab-Israeli wars fought since 1948, Jewish forces have won?:",
    "option": ["two.", "one.", "all.", "three."],
    "answer": "all."
  },
  {
    "id": 1706,
    "question": "The British, French, and Israelis were forced to withdraw from Egypt by?:",
    "option": [
      "Egypt and Syria.",
      "Russia and Egypt.",
      "the Palestinians and Libya.",
      "the United States and the Soviet Union."
    ],
    "answer": "the United States and the Soviet Union."
  },
  {
    "id": 1707,
    "question": "Which statement concerning the Islamic world is most accurate?:",
    "option": [
      "religious unity has led to political unity among Islamic nations.",
      "the only Islamic nations of the world are found in the Middle East.",
      "all Islamic nations are totally committed to the destruction of Israel.",
      "significant religious and political differences exist among Islamic sects."
    ],
    "answer": "significant religious and political differences exist among Islamic sects."
  },
  {
    "id": 1708,
    "question": "During the 20c, the governments of Afghanistan and Iran were similar in that both were linked to?:",
    "option": [
      "efforts to separate religion and politics.",
      "incidents of international terrorism.",
      "advocates of international terrorism.",
      "promotion of democratic principles in Third World nations."
    ],
    "answer": "incidents of international terrorism."
  },
  {
    "id": 1709,
    "question": "During the 1980s, the economic development of Iran and Iraq was disrupted because of?:",
    "option": [
      "the war fought between these nations.",
      "increased emphasis on agricultural production for export.",
      "Communist revolutionary movements in these nations.",
      "severe drought and famine in the area."
    ],
    "answer": "the war fought between these nations."
  },
  {
    "id": 1710,
    "question": "The major goal of the Iranian Revolution and of Ayatollah Khomeini was to?:",
    "option": [
      "establish closer ties with Israel.",
      "prevent the expansion of communism into Iraq.",
      "nationalize the oil industry.",
      "create an Islamic Republic."
    ],
    "answer": "create an Islamic Republic."
  },
  {
    "id": 1711,
    "question": "One cause of the Iranian Revolution was?:",
    "option": [
      "Iran\\'s defeat in the Iran-Iraq War.",
      "the Shah\\'s refusal to modernize the Iranian legal system.",
      "failure of the Shah\\'s reforms to improve life for many Iranians.",
      "the death of the Ayatollah Khomeini."
    ],
    "answer": "failure of the Shah\\'s reforms to improve life for many Iranians."
  },
  {
    "id": 1712,
    "question": "In Operation Desert Storm, American forces freed Kuwait from occupation by?:",
    "option": ["Iran.", "Iraq.", "Syria.", "Israel."],
    "answer": "Iraq."
  },
  {
    "id": 1713,
    "question": "One purpose of the UN sanctions after the Gulf War was to force Saddam Hussein to destroy?:",
    "option": [
      "chemical weapons.",
      "Iraqi oil reserves.",
      "vital shipping lanes in the Persian Gulf.",
      "illegal poppy fields in northern Iraq."
    ],
    "answer": "chemical weapons."
  },
  {
    "id": 1714,
    "question": "The United States became involved in wars in the Persian Gulf in order to?:",
    "option": [
      "keep the region safe for democracy.",
      "protect the lives of American in the region.",
      "prevent environmental disasters.",
      "protect the flow of oil to the West and the rest of the world."
    ],
    "answer": "protect the flow of oil to the West and the rest of the world."
  },
  {
    "id": 1715,
    "question": "A major result of Iraq\\'s invasion of Kuwait was?:",
    "option": [
      "the immediate overthrow of Saddam Hussein.",
      "the introduction of Communism into Kuwait.",
      "a show if international cooperation under the guise of the United Nations.",
      "lasting peace throughout the world."
    ],
    "answer": "a show if international cooperation under the guise of the United Nations."
  },
  {
    "id": 1716,
    "question": "In the aftermath of the Persian Gulf War?:",
    "option": [
      "Saddam Hussein was overthrown and assassinated as a result of a coup organized and funded by the American CIA.",
      "the United States was slow in reacting to Hussein\\'s repression of Iraqi Shi\\'ites and Kurds.",
      "the Kuwaiti government instituted reforms that turned it into a model of democracy.",
      "the United Nations oversaw the dismantling of Iraq\\'s military establishment and the destruction of its war-making weapons."
    ],
    "answer": "the United States was slow in reacting to Hussein\\'s repression of Iraqi Shi\\'ites and Kurds."
  },
  {
    "id": 1717,
    "question": "In Iran under Ayatollah Khomeini and in Afghanistan throughout the 1990s, an effect of the Islamic fundamentalist government has been to?:",
    "option": [
      "produce an agrarian-based economy.",
      "eliminate anti-Israeli terrorist groups within their borders.",
      "create a strong military alliance with the Soviet Union.",
      "limit rights for women."
    ],
    "answer": "limit rights for women."
  },
  {
    "id": 1718,
    "question": "The Soviet invasion of Afghanistan was similar to United States involvement in the Vietnam War because?:",
    "option": [
      "both wars were unpopular and sparked protests at home.",
      "the superpowers primarily used guerrilla tactics.",
      "their victories increased their international prestige.",
      "the UN Security Council supported their actions."
    ],
    "answer": "both wars were unpopular and sparked protests at home."
  },
  {
    "id": 1719,
    "question": "Compared to the classical cities of the late 4c and 5c of Western Europe, Constantinople?:",
    "option": [
      "was much larger and more prosperous.",
      "had less protection from invaders.",
      "produced fewer scholars and works of art.",
      "gave people greater freedom of religion and though."
    ],
    "answer": "was much larger and more prosperous."
  },
  {
    "id": 1720,
    "question": "The Byzantine emperor Justinian tried to rebuild the Roman Empire by?:",
    "option": [
      "defeating the armies of Islam.",
      "recognizing the Pope as the highest authority in the Church.",
      "signing treaties with the Huns.",
      "fighting the Germanic peoples who had invaded the Empire."
    ],
    "answer": "fighting the Germanic peoples who had invaded the Empire."
  },
  {
    "id": 1721,
    "question": "Constantinople\\'s location had all of the following advantages EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "being a crossroads for trade by land and sea.",
      "being easy to defend.",
      "being midway between the Eastern and Western Roman Empires.",
      "having a harbor on a major strait."
    ],
    "answer": "being midway between the Eastern and Western Roman Empires."
  },
  {
    "id": 1722,
    "question": "Byzantine artists made a lasting impact in the areas of?:",
    "option": [
      "charcoal and watercolors.",
      "religious art, mosaics, and architecture.",
      "sculpture and painting.",
      "carpet weaving and textiles."
    ],
    "answer": "religious art, mosaics, and architecture."
  },
  {
    "id": 1723,
    "question": "Under Justinian, the old Roman Empire was?:",
    "option": [
      "restored almost to its former borders.",
      "conquered by the Persian Empire.",
      "made more democratic.",
      "threatened by Muslim armies."
    ],
    "answer": "restored almost to its former borders."
  },
  {
    "id": 1724,
    "question": "Today, the person most likely to study  Justinian\\'s Code  would be a?:",
    "option": [
      "professor of surgery.",
      "mathematician.",
      "philosopher.",
      "legal scholar."
    ],
    "answer": "legal scholar."
  },
  {
    "id": 1725,
    "question": "The Byzantine Empire made its most important contribution to later civilizations by?:",
    "option": [
      "defeating the Hun invaders.",
      "trading with merchants from the Middle East.",
      "preserving much of the Greco-Roman heritage.",
      "recognizing the Pope as head of the Byzantine Church."
    ],
    "answer": "preserving much of the Greco-Roman heritage."
  },
  {
    "id": 1726,
    "question": "A Babylonian schoolboy wrote his lessons on?:",
    "option": [
      "clay tablets.",
      "block of slate.",
      "papyrus scroll.",
      "stones."
    ],
    "answer": "clay tablets."
  },
  {
    "id": 1727,
    "question": "The movement of peoples across the Fertile Crescent resulted in the?:",
    "option": [
      "invention of hieroglyphics.",
      "constant exchange of ideas.",
      "belief in one god.",
      "building of irrigation systems."
    ],
    "answer": "constant exchange of ideas."
  },
  {
    "id": 1728,
    "question": "Sumerians influenced later civilizations through each of the following EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "arithmetic and geometry.",
      "architecture.",
      "cuneiform.",
      "law codes."
    ],
    "answer": "law codes."
  },
  {
    "id": 1729,
    "question": "What important invention is first known to have been used by the Sumerians?:",
    "option": ["the pulley.", "paper.", "the wheel.", "the battering ram."],
    "answer": "the wheel."
  },
  {
    "id": 1730,
    "question": "Which of the following statements best describes the principle behind Hammurabi\\'s Code?:",
    "option": [
      "Church and state must be separate.",
      "An eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth.",
      "Judge not lest you be judged.",
      "Justice must be tempered by mercy."
    ],
    "answer": "An eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth."
  },
  {
    "id": 1731,
    "question": "The  Epic of Gilgamesh  is?:",
    "option": [
      "the story of the Hebrew\\'s flight from Egypt.",
      "an Egyptian folktale.",
      "a tale about King Nebuchadnezzar.",
      "a poem recounting the adventures of a Sumerian hero."
    ],
    "answer": "a poem recounting the adventures of a Sumerian hero."
  },
  {
    "id": 1732,
    "question": "Hammurabi\\'s Code provided for different penalties according to?:",
    "option": ["social class.", "age.", "motive.", "the whim of the judge."],
    "answer": "social class."
  },
  {
    "id": 1733,
    "question": "Sumerian sites such as Ur, Uruk, and Eridu are considered by historians to be?:",
    "option": [
      "the birthplace of spoken language.",
      "among the world\\'s first cities.",
      "the birthplace of polytheism.",
      "the finest examples of Egyptian architecture."
    ],
    "answer": "among the world\\'s first cities."
  },
  {
    "id": 1734,
    "question": "During the rule of King Nebuchadnezzar, Babylon?:",
    "option": [
      "became capital of the Hittite Empire.",
      "was destroyed by the Persians.",
      "was built by the Hebrews.",
      "became known as one of the world\\'s most beautiful cities."
    ],
    "answer": "became known as one of the world\\'s most beautiful cities."
  },
  {
    "id": 1735,
    "question": "Which statement about the Fertile Crescent is accurate?:",
    "option": [
      "rich soil and abundant water, especially in the Tigris-Euphrates Valley made it a center of early civilization.",
      "because it was protected from invasion, strong empires emerged there.",
      "it was located on the Arabian Peninsula and sat atop abundant oil resources.",
      "it stretches in an arc along the southern rim of the Mediterranean Sea."
    ],
    "answer": "rich soil and abundant water, especially in the Tigris-Euphrates Valley made it a center of early civilization."
  },
  {
    "id": 1736,
    "question": "Scholars have included the Akkadians in their study of the advance of civilization because?:",
    "option": [
      "Solomon\\'s mines hinted at the magnificence of the culture.",
      "they came close to achieving a monotheistic religion.",
      "they built the first empire of the Near East.",
      "they developed the use of iron weapons."
    ],
    "answer": "they built the first empire of the Near East."
  },
  {
    "id": 1737,
    "question": "What is meant by the tern \"cuneiform?\":",
    "option": [
      "the process by which copper and tin are combined to create the more valuable metal bronze.",
      "a script using wedge-shaped marks impressed into clay tablets, first used by the Sumerians, to record spoken language.",
      "a mathematical algebraic innovation that enabled people to solve complex problems.",
      "the channels through which water was diverted in order to irrigate the fields of early city-states."
    ],
    "answer": "a script using wedge-shaped marks impressed into clay tablets, first used by the Sumerians, to record spoken language."
  },
  {
    "id": 1738,
    "question": "The Persians united their vast empire by?:",
    "option": [
      "forcing all the conquered people to learn cuneiform.",
      "using Hammurabi\\'s code of law.",
      "adopting the achievements of ancient Greek civilization.",
      "developing an excellent system of roads."
    ],
    "answer": "developing an excellent system of roads."
  },
  {
    "id": 1739,
    "question": "The ancient land of Persia is known today as?:",
    "option": ["Iran.", "Turkey.", "Iraq.", "Lebanon."],
    "answer": "Iran."
  },
  {
    "id": 1740,
    "question": "Which of the following beliefs did both Zoroastrians and Hebrews hold?:",
    "option": [
      "the gods controlled the forced of nature.",
      "on the final judgment day, individuals would be held responsible for their actions.",
      "G_d revealed the Ten Commandments to Moses.",
      "every year, the gods came down to earth using the ziggurat as a ladder."
    ],
    "answer": "on the final judgment day, individuals would be held responsible for their actions."
  },
  {
    "id": 1741,
    "question": "The  Zend Avesta  is?:",
    "option": [
      "the law code of the Persian Empire.",
      "an epic poem about Cyrus\\'s accomplishments.",
      "a collection of religious hymns and poems.",
      "a collection of essays on politics by Cyrus."
    ],
    "answer": "a collection of religious hymns and poems."
  },
  {
    "id": 1742,
    "question": "Zoroaster taught that?:",
    "option": [
      "humans are mere pawns, manipulated by the gods.",
      "life is a constant struggle between good and evil.",
      "priests should have power over political leaders.",
      "there is only one god."
    ],
    "answer": "life is a constant struggle between good and evil."
  },
  {
    "id": 1743,
    "question": "The Persian Empire maintained order through?:",
    "option": [
      "a policy of terror and oppression.",
      "use of missionaries and public legal proclamations.",
      "belief in one god.",
      "tolerance and good government."
    ],
    "answer": "tolerance and good government."
  },
  {
    "id": 1744,
    "question": "A major accomplishment of Sargon I was to?:",
    "option": [
      "unite the city-states of Mesopotamia.",
      "restore the royal archives at Ebla.",
      "develop a 365-day calendar.",
      "facilitate the spread of the Sumerian language."
    ],
    "answer": "unite the city-states of Mesopotamia."
  },
  {
    "id": 1745,
    "question": "Which of the following was most characteristic of the Persian Empire?:",
    "option": [
      "it did not engage in extensive trade.",
      "it had cruel and intolerant rulers.",
      "people were especially noted for their interest in astrology.",
      "its military engineers developed new techniques of war."
    ],
    "answer": "people were especially noted for their interest in astrology."
  },
  {
    "id": 1746,
    "question": "Under the rule of Cyrus of Persia?:",
    "option": [
      "the kings of conquered territories were replaced by democracies.",
      "local self-rule was permitted under Persian supervision.",
      "extreme leniency of local rulers was tolerated.",
      "the Hebrews were exterminated."
    ],
    "answer": "local self-rule was permitted under Persian supervision."
  },
  {
    "id": 1747,
    "question": "The supreme deity of Zoroastrianism, who personified power, majesty, and of positive ethical principles, was?:",
    "option": ["Ahriman.", "Zarathustra.", "Avesta.", "Ahura-Mazda."],
    "answer": "Ahura-Mazda."
  },
  {
    "id": 1748,
    "question": "Probably the earliest people to use iron were the?:",
    "option": ["Lydians.", "Hittites.", "Phoenicians.", "Hebrews."],
    "answer": "Hittites."
  },
  {
    "id": 1749,
    "question": "The Phoenicians were important in history because they?:",
    "option": [
      "invented the coinage of money.",
      "were the first people to make use of iron.",
      "first developed the idea of monotheism.",
      "invented the alphabet which eventually was used by the West."
    ],
    "answer": "invented the alphabet which eventually was used by the West."
  },
  {
    "id": 1750,
    "question": "Ideas were spread throughout the Mediterranean by Phoenician?:",
    "option": ["merchants.", "priests.", "armies.", "kings."],
    "answer": "merchants."
  },
  {
    "id": 1751,
    "question": "The pattern of political rule in Southwest Asia after 900 BCE was one of?:",
    "option": [
      "continuous control by one group.",
      "a series of empires created by various invaders.",
      "continuous migration, with no one group in full control.",
      "small rival kingdoms fighting for control of the area."
    ],
    "answer": "a series of empires created by various invaders."
  },
  {
    "id": 1752,
    "question": "What did Phoenician traders develop to help them do business?:",
    "option": [
      "faster ships that could hold more goods.",
      "an alphabet using symbols to represent sounds.",
      "a sought-after dye called \"Tyrian purple\".",
      "papyrus to make scrolls for books."
    ],
    "answer": "an alphabet using symbols to represent sounds."
  },
  {
    "id": 1753,
    "question": "The Assyrians earned a reputation in the ancient world for?:",
    "option": [
      "their seafaring talent.",
      "allowing conquered peoples to retain their customs.",
      "many significant scientific achievements.",
      "their extreme cruelty."
    ],
    "answer": "their extreme cruelty."
  },
  {
    "id": 1754,
    "question": "Which effect did the Mughals have on India during their rule?:",
    "option": [
      "parliamentary republics were established.",
      "India became unified under one language.",
      "Muslim culture dominated in parts of India.",
      "Hinduism became the dominant religion in northern India."
    ],
    "answer": "Muslim culture dominated in parts of India."
  },
  {
    "id": 1755,
    "question": "Unlike the Delhi sultans, Akbar believed in?:",
    "option": [
      "the custom of  suttee.",
      "no taxes.",
      "Hindu inferiority.",
      "religiouis freedom."
    ],
    "answer": "religiouis freedom."
  },
  {
    "id": 1756,
    "question": "Shah Jahan made the people pay high taxes mainly to?:",
    "option": [
      "finance the building of magnificent palaces.",
      "improve their living conditions.",
      "maintain their right to practice Hinduism.",
      "construct vast irrigation systems."
    ],
    "answer": "finance the building of magnificent palaces."
  },
  {
    "id": 1757,
    "question": "Muslims and Hindus clashed in India because?:",
    "option": [
      "Hindus believed all people were equal in the sight of God.",
      "the Hindu belief in many gods offended Muslims.",
      "Muslims worshipped sacred animals.",
      "Hindus wanted to change the caste system."
    ],
    "answer": "the Hindu belief in many gods offended Muslims."
  },
  {
    "id": 1758,
    "question": "Mughal art and literature reflected the?:",
    "option": [
      "importance of the caste system.",
      "growing influence of Christianity.",
      "blending of Hindu and Muslim traditions.",
      "decline in Islam."
    ],
    "answer": "blending of Hindu and Muslim traditions."
  },
  {
    "id": 1759,
    "question": "Akbar is considered the greatest Mughal ruler because he?:",
    "option": [
      "defeated the Delhi Sultanate.",
      "built the Taj Mahal.",
      "spread Buddist ideas.",
      "tried to ensure peace between Hindus and Muslims."
    ],
    "answer": "tried to ensure peace between Hindus and Muslims."
  },
  {
    "id": 1760,
    "question": "Unlike Hindus, Muslims in India?:",
    "option": [
      "were tolerant of the religious practices of other peoples.",
      "used music in their worship.",
      "preached the equality of all believers.",
      "regarded cattle as sacred animals."
    ],
    "answer": "preached the equality of all believers."
  },
  {
    "id": 1761,
    "question": "Aurangzeb\\'s policies toward Hinduism included all of the following EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "taxing Hindus more than Muslims.",
      "destroying Hindu temples.",
      "appointing Hindus to high office.",
      "making India an Islamic state."
    ],
    "answer": "appointing Hindus to high office."
  },
  {
    "id": 1762,
    "question": "After Turkish sultans gained control of northern India in 1206, they established?:",
    "option": [
      "Hinduism as the state religion of the Delhi sultanate.",
      "the Ghaznavid Empire.",
      "religious toleration that fostered the growth of Hinduism and Buddhism.",
      "a new regime known as the Delhi sultanate."
    ],
    "answer": "a new regime known as the Delhi sultanate."
  },
  {
    "id": 1763,
    "question": "A unique aspect of religion in Japan is that?:",
    "option": [
      "most major religions have no formal priesthood.",
      "many Japanese practice both Buddhism and Shinto.",
      "all Japanese religions are monotheistic.",
      "the current Emperor is regarded as a god."
    ],
    "answer": "many Japanese practice both Buddhism and Shinto."
  },
  {
    "id": 1764,
    "question": "A person who practices the Shinto faith would be most likely to?:",
    "option": [
      "visit a shrine placed on the shore of a lake.",
      "bathe in the Ganges River.",
      "pray five times a day.",
      "make a pilgrimage to Jerusalem."
    ],
    "answer": "visit a shrine placed on the shore of a lake."
  },
  {
    "id": 1765,
    "question": "Which was Shintoism\\'s major teaching?:",
    "option": [
      "achievement of human perfection.",
      "love for fellow humans.",
      "reverence for the land.",
      "reincarnation of the soul."
    ],
    "answer": "reverence for the land."
  },
  {
    "id": 1766,
    "question": "All of the following are characteristics of Shintoism EXCEPT?:",
    "option": [
      "love of beauty.",
      "an emphasis on cleanliness.",
      "animism.",
      "very elaborate decorations and gawdy architectural styles."
    ],
    "answer": "very elaborate decorations and gawdy architectural styles."
  },
  {
    "id": 1767,
    "question": "In Japan, the traditional arts of flower arranging, haiku poetry, and origami show the Japanese love and respect for?:",
    "option": ["nature.", "the family.", "the military.", "technology."],
    "answer": "nature."
  },
  {
    "id": 1768,
    "question": "Which of the following did Shintoism and Confucianism have in common in Japan?:",
    "option": [
      "emphasis on military virtues and the arts of war.",
      "respect and submission to higher authority.",
      "worship of the spirits and deities in nature.",
      "rebellion against the emperor, which both religions permitted under certain circumstances."
    ],
    "answer": "respect and submission to higher authority."
  },
  {
    "id": 1769,
    "question": "Shinto beliefs?:",
    "option": [
      "were closely integrated with political authority.",
      "held Amaterasu, the female solar deity, as its chief deity.",
      "were animistic.",
      "all of these choices are correct."
    ],
    "answer": "all of these choices are correct."
  },
  {
    "id": 1770,
    "question": "Population density is greatest in the northern part of India because?:",
    "option": [
      "people tend to settle along the seacoast.",
      "the population centers in China are easy to reach from this area.",
      "families in this area traditionally are larger than families in southern India.",
      "the major river systems are located in this area."
    ],
    "answer": "the major river systems are located in this area."
  },
  {
    "id": 1771,
    "question": "The monsoons are important to India mainly because the monsoons?:",
    "option": [
      "bring needed rainfall.",
      "isolate India from Southeast Asia.",
      "prevent the spread of disease.",
      "are associated with religious values."
    ],
    "answer": "bring needed rainfall."
  },
  {
    "id": 1772,
    "question": "The Khyber and other passes through the Kindu Kush were important because they?:",
    "option": [
      "had fertile farmland.",
      "were the source of India\\'s greatest rivers.",
      "aided the movement of people and goods and established an invasion route.",
      "kept invaders from reaching the fertile river valleys."
    ],
    "answer": "aided the movement of people and goods and established an invasion route."
  },
  {
    "id": 1773,
    "question": "One reason that the Indus, Ganges, and Brahmaputra are important is that they?:",
    "option": [
      "form borders between India and its neighbors.",
      "provide water for irrigation.",
      "protect India from outside invasions.",
      "link northern and southern India."
    ],
    "answer": "provide water for irrigation."
  },
  {
    "id": 1774,
    "question": "The climate of India is largely determined by monsoons, which are?:",
    "option": [
      "seasonal winds.",
      "heavy rains.",
      "large, dark clouds.",
      "typhoons."
    ],
    "answer": "seasonal winds."
  },
  {
    "id": 1775,
    "question": "The level, fertile heartland of India is the?:",
    "option": [
      "Indus Valley.",
      "Deccan Plateau.",
      "Indo-Gangetic Plain.",
      "Hindu Kush."
    ],
    "answer": "Indo-Gangetic Plain."
  },
  {
    "id": 1776,
    "question": "Floods are an all too common natural disaster in this low-lying river delta subject to wind-driven tidal surges?:",
    "option": ["Bangladesh.", "Nepal.", "Phutan.", "Sikkim."],
    "answer": "Bangladesh."
  },
  {
    "id": 1777,
    "question": "The Deccan Plateau?:",
    "option": [
      "provided a geographic barrier that prevented foreign invasion of the Indian subcontinent.",
      "was the site of India\\'s earliest civilization.",
      "was the location of major trade routes.",
      "separated southern India from the rest of the subcontinent."
    ],
    "answer": "separated southern India from the rest of the subcontinent."
  },
  {
    "id": 1778,
    "question": "The Ghats were?:",
    "option": [
      "the earliest known inhabitants of India.",
      "mountain ranges which separate the eastern and western coastal regions from the Deccan Plateau.",
      "the two major river systems on the Indian subcontinent.",
      "two culturally different peoples who ilve in the mountain regions of the north."
    ],
    "answer": "mountain ranges which separate the eastern and western coastal regions from the Deccan Plateau."
  },
  {
    "id": 1779,
    "question": "Moral results can only be obtained through moral restraints. -- Mohandas K. Gandhi. This quotation BEST represents the policy of?:",
    "option": [
      "westernization.",
      "neutrality.",
      "balance of power.",
      "passive resistance."
    ],
    "answer": "passive resistance."
  },
  {
    "id": 1780,
    "question": "Which situation contributed to the success of Mohandas Gandhi\\'s campaign of civil disobedience in India?:",
    "option": [
      "Pakistan and Bangladesh were involved in civil wars.",
      "the United States came to Gandhi\\'s aid with food and clothing.",
      "Great Britain was weakened by World War II.",
      "Sikhs and Muslims wanted to create a new nation."
    ],
    "answer": "Great Britain was weakened by World War II."
  },
  {
    "id": 1781,
    "question": "It has impoverished the dumb millions by a system of progressive exploitation....It has reduced us politically to serfdom. It has sapped the foundation of our culture...and degraded us spiritually. --- Mohandas K. Gandhi, 1930. In the statement, the it referred to by Gandhi is?:",
    "option": [
      "British imperialism in India.",
      "India\\'s involvement in World War I.",
      "the exploitation of the proletariat by the bourgeoisie.",
      "the British endorsement of apartheid in South Africa."
    ],
    "answer": "British imperialism in India."
  },
  {
    "id": 1782,
    "question": "Which action is most consistent with Mohandas Gandhi\\'s ideas about civil disobedience?:",
    "option": [
      "bombing a government office building.",
      "refusing to pay taxes.",
      "blackmailing a political official.",
      "holding diplomats as hostages."
    ],
    "answer": "refusing to pay taxes."
  },
  {
    "id": 1783,
    "question": "Which action illustrates the ideas of Mohandas K. Gandhi\\'s policy of civil disobedience?:",
    "option": [
      "blowing up an airplane to call attention to injustice.",
      "voting in a national election.",
      "accepting a jail sentence for participating in an illegal peaceful protest.",
      "kidnapping a government official and demanding ransom."
    ],
    "answer": "accepting a jail sentence for participating in an illegal peaceful protest."
  },
  {
    "id": 1784,
    "question": "During India\\'s independence movement, Mohandas Gandhi\\'s boycott of British-made goods was effective because the British considered India a major?:",
    "option": [
      "shipping center.",
      "industrial center.",
      "source of mineral resources.",
      "market for manufactured goods."
    ],
    "answer": "market for manufactured goods."
  },
  {
    "id": 1785,
    "question": "Which event was used by Mohandas Gandhi to bring world attention to the injustices of British colonialism in India?:",
    "option": [
      "Salt March.",
      "outbreak of World War I.",
      "formation of India\\'s Parliament.",
      "Sepoy Mutiny."
    ],
    "answer": "Salt March."
  },
  {
    "id": 1786,
    "question": "\"Indian National Congress Refuses to Support British War Effort\" \"Indians Answer Call for the Production of Homespun Cloth\" \"Indians Call for Boycott of Imported British Cloth\" These three headlines all refer to?:",
    "option": [
      "political reorganization in the British colonial empire.",
      "attempts by the native people to gain India\\'s independence.",
      "programs to increase India\\'s standard of living.",
      "the benefits of economic interdependence between Britain and India."
    ],
    "answer": "attempts by the native people to gain India\\'s independence."
  },
  {
    "id": 1787,
    "question": "Gandhi transformed the Indian independence movement from?:",
    "option": [
      "a previously violent to a non-violent movement.",
      "an urban to a rural movement.",
      "an elite to a mass movement.",
      "a British to a primarily Indian movement."
    ],
    "answer": "an elite to a mass movement."
  }
]
